<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The stewards last account Deliuered in fiue sermons vpon the sixteenth chapter of the gospell by Saint Luke, the first and second verses. By Robert Bagnall, Minister of the Word of God, at Hutton in Somersetshire.</title>
            <author>Bagnall, Robert, b. 1559 or 60.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 245 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01737</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1187</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119158</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854365</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854365</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19782</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01737)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19782)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1194:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The stewards last account Deliuered in fiue sermons vpon the sixteenth chapter of the gospell by Saint Luke, the first and second verses. By Robert Bagnall, Minister of the Word of God, at Hutton in Somersetshire.</title>
                  <author>Bagnall, Robert, b. 1559 or 60.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 86, 79-99, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Purslowe, for Iohn Clarke: and are to be sold at his shop vnder Saint Peters Church in Cornhill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Luke XVI, 1-2 --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Stewardship, Christian --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19782:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19782:1"/>
            <p>THE STEWARDS LAST ACCOVNT.</p>
            <p>DELIVERED IN FIVE Sermons vpon the ſixteenth Chapter of the Goſpell by Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> the firſt and ſecond Verſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY Robert Bagnall,</hi> Miniſter of the Word of God, at <hi>Hutton</hi> in Somerſetſhire.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATH. 25.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Watch therefore: for yee know neither the day, nor the houre, when the Sonne of Man will come</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MATH. 12.36.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>For I ſay vnto you, that of euery idle word that men ſhall ſpeake, they ſhall giue account thereof at the Day of Iudgement.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>George Purſlowe,</hi> for <hi>Iohn Clarke:</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop vnder Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Church in <hi>Cornhill.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19782:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19782:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in God, ARTHVR, by Gods prouidence, Lord Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells,</hi> ROBERT BAGNALL wiſheth all health and true comfort in this world, and eternall happineſſe in the <hi>World to come.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S to the building of the materiall Temple (Right Reuerend Father in God, and my very Honorable good Lord) many co adiutors and fellow-labourers were admitted, ſome more excellent then others, yet none were repelled, nor reiected, although they were of the meaner ſort, as Morter carriers: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were neceſſarie. Euen ſo reaſon willeth, and neceſsitie requireth, that they which are lawfully called to the office of the Miniſtery, although they are not Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tects,
<pb facs="tcp:19782:3"/> yet if they may do good in the Church of God, ſhould be ſuffered to help a little to build vp the Spirituall Temple of the Lord: For many hands make light worke. The conſideration hereof hath emboldened me, being as it were, the leaſt of the Apoſtles, and alſo requeſted of many who ſaw my notes, and heard mee preach them, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt this worke; wherein if I may adde but one mite to the treaſurie of the Church, to help a little to build the Lords ſpirituall Houſe, I ſhall thinke my labour well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed. Howſoeuer, I would not with that ſmall Talent which I haue concredited vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, be like to that euill ſeruant, which made no good vſe of his, but hid it in the ground, and therefore was ſhamefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued.</p>
            <p>The ſubiect, or matter, which I haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vpon mee to intreat of, is, of our laſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count at the generall Aſſize in the laſt Day. A matter moſt fitting and beſeeming my gray haires going to the graue, and requiſite for all ſorts of people liuing in this careleſſe age, and very auaileable to ſhake them out
<pb facs="tcp:19782:3"/> of the cradle of ſecuritie, wherein they lye lulled and rocked, and to ſtirre them vp to vigilance and watchfulneſſe. This worke, I confeſſe, is a withered fruit of my old age, but if it may obtaine your Honours fauour ſo farre, as to cheriſh and protect it vnder the ſhadow of your wings, it growing to maturitie, in proceſſe of time may obtaine ſome fauour in the world, eſpecially among the Children of God, whom it may ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what benefit. I therefore beſeech your good Honour and reuerend Paternitie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a moſt godly and vigilant Watchman ouer vs all, to patronize this my Doctrine of warchfulneſſe, and to take in good part my endeuours therin: hoping that it may make many waking, and looking for the Lords ſecond comming to their ſaluation. So cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing your Honourable fauour herein, I humbly take my leaue: Reſting (as dutie bindeth me) your Honours poore Miniſter vnder God, in all Chriſtian dutie to bee or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and commanded:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ROBERT BAGNALL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19782:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19782:4"/>
            <head>TO THE GODLY READER, GRACE, MERCY, and Peace from God the Father, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S in the contriuing, managing, and bringing to good effect worldly buſineſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that tend to the maintenance of the body in this preſent life, we account op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of time, and fit occaſions, the greateſt furtherers; and loſse of time, the greatest hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers: and therefore in euery thing, wee take the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt time; as in planting, ſowing, gathering in the fruits of the earth, and all other affaires: So nothing doth more helpe in the courſe of Piety, and further our iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to eternall life, then to be vigilant and carefull, to take all times and occaſions to ſerue God, and to let no time paſse away vnprofitable. For time hasteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and tarrieth for no man, and fooliſhly ſpent, cannot be recalled: And therefore the Heathens painted out Time with wings at her hands, and alſo at her feet, with a locke of haire before, but bald behinde. This velocitie of time, and irrecuperableneſſe of her being careleſſely and idly let ſlip, <hi>Bernard</hi> laid downe to his Schollers,
<pb facs="tcp:19782:5"/> when hee ſaid:<note place="margin">Bern. ad Scho.</note> 
               <hi>Volat tempus irreuocabile, volat tempus irremeabile, nec aduertit inſipiens quid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittat, &amp;c.</hi> that is, Time flyeth away, that cannot bee recalled; Time flyeth away, that cannot come againe, and fooliſh man doth not conſider what he loſeth: and yet (alas) hee loſeth all the good vſe of time, and all the benefit that hee might make of the ſame, when it offereth it ſelfe.<note place="margin">Baſil.</note> And therefore <hi>Baſil</hi> well ſaid: <hi>Nemo vſum temporis habere queat, niſi quis cum ſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fert, arripiat:</hi> that is, no man can receiue any profit of Time, but he that ſpeedily layeth hold on it, when it offereth it ſelfe. Let the parabolicall example of the ten Virgins teach and admoniſh vs herein, and make vs take <hi>Bildad</hi> the Shuhites counſell: Early to ſeeke the Lord, and ſeeke him while he may be found, and ſpeedily to goe about the Lords buſineſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.</note> as the Cherubims did, and therefore were pourtraied with wings before the place where the Iſraelites prayed. O good Chriſtian Reader, conſider, I beſeech thee, what a fooliſh thing it is for thee, to let time paſse away ſecurely, to let thy rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>konings runne ſo long without any examination of thy life, and doings, and without calling thy wayes to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, that thou ſhouldeſt be growne obdurate, paſt ſenſe and feeling, yea, and ſo forgetfull of thy dealings, that thou canſt not bring in a true reckoning.</p>
            <p>Conſider this in time, and call thine owne wayes to remembrance, ſleepe no longer in ſecuritie; but be ſober and watch, that thou maiſt not bee called to account when thou thinkeſt not thereof, and be found falſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and ſo he proued and conuicted a falſe Steward. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie will bring thee to extremities, and to all theſe
<pb facs="tcp:19782:5"/> diſtreſſes, as it did the people in <hi>Noah</hi> his time, in <hi>Lots</hi> time, and many other people in all ages, and ſo it will doe many at the laſt audit. Therefore let me beſeech thee; yea, and perſwade thee by the tender mercies of God, to ſuffer mee to pull thee backe by the ſleeue from running into the pit of perdition, haue thy bookes of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in a readineſſe, be a vigilant and watchfull Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that at the laſt Day it may be ſaid vnto thee, <hi>O well done, thou good and faithfull Seruant, thou haſt been faithfull ouer few things, I will make thee Ruler ouer many things: enter thou into the ioy of thy Lord.</hi> I haue (good Chriſtian Reader) beſtowed my ſmall skill and labour in this Treatiſe, to make thee a good Steward and accountant at the laſt audit and Generall Aſsize. I pray thee reade the ſame, not with a preiudicate opinion, but with a yeelding reſolution to the truth, as thou ſhalt finde it, and perſwade thy ſelfe that this is written (howſoeuer it may croſſe thy humours in taking thy fleſhly pleaſures) yet for thy learning, and to doe thee good, and to ſet thee in the way to Heauen, in the which way God ſpeed thee with faithfulneſse and conſtancie to the end, and then thou ſhalt be ſure of thy wiſhed deſire, a crowne of incorruptible glory: Which God of his infinite goodneſse and mercy grant mee, and thee, and the whole Church quickly. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:19782:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19782:6"/>
            <head>THE STEVVARDS LAST ACCOVNT. <hi>The firſt Sermon.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>LVK. 16.1, 2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1.</hi>
                     </bibl> There was a certaine rich man, which had a Steward, and he was accuſed vnto him that he waſted his goods.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>2.</hi>
                     </bibl> And he called him, and ſaid vnto him, How is it that I beare this of thee? Giue an accounts of thy ſtewardſhip: for thou maiſt be no longer Steward.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe two verſes, and the other fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing vnto the ninth verſe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the plaine literall and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball ſenſe and meaning, containe a parable ſpoken by our Sauiour Chriſt vnto his Diſciples, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a certaine rich man which had a Steward, that dealt falſely with him, iniuriouſly ſcraped and raked together great ſtore of worldly riches, and all that he could get from his Maſter by hooke and by crooke, by any meanes, were they neuer
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19782:7"/> ſo vngodly, vniuſt, and wrongfull, that hee ill imployed, and waſtfully ſpent in pleaſures and ſinfull courſes of life. Of which fraudulent dealing and waſting his goods, as ſoone as his Maſter had intelligence; hee called him, and reprehended him, ſaying: <hi>How commeth it to paſſe that I heare this of thee?</hi> And preſently calleth him to account, and putteth him out of his Office. Which thing when the Steward perceiued, he knowing hee could not frame himſelfe to painefull labours, as to digge and delue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in former times he had liued idly, and pleaſantly, but yet in reputation; and therefore he was aſhamed to begge; for that (as hee was perſwaded) would much abaſe him, and make him contemptible: then he reſolueth himſelfe of a third way, which was, priuily to call his Maſters debters together, and to abate the debts which they owed him; and to one that owed his Maſter an hundred mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of Oyle, he parteth at halfe, and abates fifty. And another that owed his Maſter an hundred meaſures of Wheate, hee bids take his writing and write foureſcore, cutting large thongs of another mans leather, thinking by theſe meanes to procure friends, that afterward when he was put out of his Office, might receiue him into their houſes and maintaine him, thus carefully prouiding for the time to come. And the Lord not allowing falſehood and wrongfull dealing, (for he loueth righteouſneſſe) but to ſhewe that worldly men are more carefull to obtaine earthly things and prouide for this world, then the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God are deſirous of heauenly treaſures that inrich them in the world to come, (for the children of this world are wiſer in their generation then the children of light) is ſaid to commend the vniuſt Steward for dealing ſo wiſely, and ſo carefully prouiding for this world, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing a farre greater care to the children of light to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for the world to come. Which thing we may ſee to be true, by the fit application of the parable, made by our Sauiour in the ninth verſe, ſaying thus: <hi>And I ſay vnto
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19782:7"/> you, Make you friends with the riches of iniquitie, that when yee ſhall want, they may receiue you into euerlasting ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To bee yet ſomewhat more plaine: The true ſenſe, ſcope and purpoſe of the holy Ghoſt, as it were by way of compariſon and reſoluing vpon the beſt, is this; The Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of a certaine rich man is carefull what ſhall become of himſelfe, when hee is put from his Office: much more therefore Chriſtians who are Stewards vnto God in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry gifts, ſhould be carefull what ſhall befall them when they ſhall depart out of this life, and make their accounts vnto God for the ſame. But as the worldly Steward pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſeth him friends with the Mammon of vnrighteouſnes, that may receiue and maintaine him when hee is remoued from his Office: So ſhould Chriſtian folke with their goods, gifts, and talents concredited vnto them, make the poore ſo beholding vnto them, that they by their prayers made to God for them,<note place="margin">Verſe 9.</note> may receiue them into euerlaſting habitations, as in the ninth verſe. This briefely is the ſum of this preſent Goſpell. Howbeit, to the intent that it may miniſter more plentifull inſtruction to all Gods people, I will by the aſſiſtance of Gods holy ſpirit intreate of theſe two points. Firſt, the perſons mentioned in the parable, which are three: Firſt, the rich man; in theſe words: <hi>There was a certaine rich man.</hi> Secondly, the Steward, in theſe words; <hi>which had a Steward.</hi> Thirdly, the accuſers of the Steward, in theſe words: <hi>and he was accuſed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The ſecond point: What the rich man did to his Steward, when hee found him falſe and vniuſt? in the ſecond verſe, in theſe words: <hi>And hee called him, and ſaid vnto him, How is it that I heare this of thee? Giue accounts of thy Stewardſhip: for thou maieſt bee no longer Steward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt part, I will ſhew vnto you who the rich man is? who is the Steward? and who are the accuſers? when I come to handle that point.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19782:8"/>
            <p>In the ſecond part, to wit, what the Lord did to his Steward when he proued him vntrue, is declared in foure points.</p>
            <p>Firſt, hee called him, in theſe words: <hi>And hee called him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, he reprehended him, ſaying: <hi>How is it that I heare this of thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, he calleth him to account, ſaying: <hi>Come render account of thy Stewardſhip, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, he putteth him out of his Office: <hi>For thou maieſt be no longer Steward.</hi> Of theſe in order, and firſt of the rich man.</p>
            <p>The rich man is God, who is chiefe Emperour, Lord, King, true owner and poſſeſſor of all good things tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and ſpirituall, earthly and heauenly. For of earthly things <hi>Dauid,</hi> Pſalme 24.<note place="margin">Pſal. 24.1.</note> truly ſpeaketh, ſaying: <hi>The earth is the Lords, and all that therein is, the world and they that dwell therein.</hi> Againe, Pſal. 50.10, 11, 12, verſes, he ſaith, <hi>All the beaſts of the forreſt are mine, and the beaſts on a thouſand mountaines. I know all the fowles of the mountaines; and the wilde beaſts of the field are mine. If I be hungry, I will not tell thee: for the world is mine, and all that therein is.</hi> This is moſt plainely proued in the 115. Pſal. verſe, 16. where the Pſalmiſt ſaith: <hi>The Heauens are the Lords, and the earth, which hee hath giuen to the ſonnes of men.</hi> Hee is rich alſo in ſpirituall and heauenly things, and ſo euery way rich, as <hi>Bernard</hi> 57. Sermon noteth: <hi>Deus vndique diues, diues miſericordia, magnifious in iuſtitia, munificus in gratia:</hi> that is to ſay, God is rich euery way, rich in mercy,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 2.4. Epheſ. 3.16. Iam. 2.5. 1. Pet. 5.10.</note> magnificent in iuſtice, liberall in Grace. Hee is rich in mercy, rich in glory, rich in wiſedome, rich in grace: for he is called the God of all grace. All which gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and gifts he giueth vs in his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus, the moſt plentifull fountaine of all goodneſſe, in whom, and by whom, all theſe and many other good gifts ineffable are conferred vnto vs,<note place="margin">Chap. 1.16.</note> as <hi>Iohn</hi> well proueth, ſaying: <hi>Of his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19782:8"/> fulnes haue all we receiued, and grace for grace:</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, grace vpon grace, or graces heaped one vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of this doctrine ſhould make vs in faith and full aſſurance to pray to this rich God, and to none other: for vnto whom ſhould wee pray? and of whom ſhould wee craue for all good things, but of him which hath all to giue, and from whom euery good giuing and perfect gift commeth?<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17. Gen. 17.1.</note> who is able to helpe in all extremities: for hee is omnipotent; is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with vs, and neare vs, as hee is vnto all that call vpon him faithfully. And laſtly, he is willing to helpe and ſaue, for hee would haue all to bee ſaued, and to come to the knowledge of his truth.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.4.</note> And therefore our Sauiour Chriſt calleth all vnto him, promiſing vnto all that come vnto him in repentance and faith, refreſhing, <hi>Math.</hi> 11.28.<note place="margin">Math. 28.</note> He commands his Goſpell to be freely preached vnto all, and he biddeth all to his great Supper, <hi>Luk.</hi> 14. O let vs in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and faith come vnto him, and pray vnto him continually: for he is the rich man here ment able to grant our requeſts.</p>
            <p>Againe, if all the good things we haue come from our rich God, it ſhould make vs moſt thankfully to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him to be the giuer, and to returne all laude and praiſe to him, from whom the benefit commeth, for as all the waters come from the Sea, and returne thither againe: ſo all the benefits which we receiue, come from God,<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> and by our thankes-giuing ſhould returne to him againe. O let vs be thankefull, and ſay with <hi>Dauid</hi> from our hearts, and ſpeake to our owne ſoules as he did: <hi>Praiſe the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 103.1, 2, 3, 4, 5.</note> 
               <hi>O my ſoule, and all that is within mee, praiſe his holy name. Praiſe the Lord, O my ſoule, and forget not all his benefits: which forgiueth all thy ſinne, and healeth all thine infirmities: which ſaueth thy life from deſtruction, and crowneth thee with mercy and louing kindneſſe: which ſatisfieth thy mouth with good things, making thee young and luſty as an Eagle.</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19782:9"/> Let vs praiſe God our ſelues, and exhort others to doe the like, for it is good and godly ſo to doe: And therefore the Prophet ſaid:<note place="margin">147.</note> 
               <hi>O praiſe the Lord: for it is a good thing to ſing praiſes vnto our God; yea, a ioyfull and pleaſant thing it is to bee thankefull.</hi> Thus much concerning the perſon meant by the rich man, to wit, God. <hi>Now of his Steward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The iudgement of ancient Writers concerning this Steward (who he ſhould be, &amp; what ſhould be his name?) haue been diuers, euery man hauing a ſeuerall opinion, and ſpeaking as he thought, <hi>quothomines, tot capita, tot ſententiae:</hi> Look how many men, ſo many heads, ſo many opinions: which thing is to be deplored, that ſo many learned men, and famous in other matters, ſhould in this point bee ſo much deceiued,<note place="margin">Rom. 15.7.</note> as to reſtrict this parcell of Scripture writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten for all our learning, to one particular Man, People, or Nation, it being alſo parabolically ſpoken. Whereas it deepely concernes vs all, and is to bee applyed particularly to euery ſeuerall man of vs. Some haue thought that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was this Steward.<note place="margin">Act. 9.4.</note> For he was a bad one, vntill he was called of Ieſus Chriſt: and of this iudgement was <hi>Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antiochia.</hi> Some affirmed that the Iewes were this Steward, and the Gentiles theſe Debtors. Of this opinion was <hi>Tertullian, lib. de fuga, cap.</hi> 13. <hi>Gaudentius</hi> writing to <hi>Germinius,</hi> ſuppoſeth that this Steward was the Diuell, miſ-implying all his gifts, his wit and power to tempt men to their deſtruction. Many others haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſly and ſtrangely ſet downe their opinions, which I thinke more fit to omit, then to fill my paper with friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous matters. Let vs harken to them who come neerer to the ſcope of the place. In this number I place <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in his Commentaries,<note place="margin">Aug. in quaeſt. Euang.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his Euangelicall queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: <hi>Theophilact,</hi> &amp; others, who affirme that this Steward is all mankind, &amp; further ſay, that the word, OIKONOMOS, a Steward, doth ſignifie not only <hi>Villicum,</hi> a Bayly of Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry; but one to whom all manner of goods and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions in a Farme, are concredited &amp; committed to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19782:9"/> to wit, a generall Steward, beſt expreſſed by the word <hi>(diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſator)</hi> which ſignifieth an Officer laying out money for an houſhold vnder another man. And therefore theſe reade the words following, <hi>(Render account of thy Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, for thou mayeſt be no longer Steward.)</hi> Thus: <hi>Redde ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem diſpenſationis tuae: non enim poteris amplius diſpenſare.</hi> So then this Steward is all mankinde. For euery man hath receiued of God, the proper owner of all, one good gift or another in truſt, which he ought to diſpoſe and employ, not as he liſteth, but as God the proper owner of al would haue him, and muſt yeeld an account to him, euen as the earthly Steward doth to his earthly Maſter. For this cauſe euery man muſt needs be a Steward, and a diſpoſer of ſome good gift of God. Kings then are Stewards to the higheſt of all, &amp; acknowledge their aduancements to come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord; and therefore in their ſtiles of Dignity, vſe theſe words <hi>(by the grace of God.)</hi> Miniſters are Stewards of the Lords Houſe, which is the Church, and ought to breake the Bread of Life to their Flockes, to preach the Word in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, and muſt render an account.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.7.</note> All Magiſtrates are Stewards of the common houſe, which is the weale publique, and ought to conſider that they are ſet ouer the people, for the puniſhment of euill doers,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.14.</note> and for the praiſe of them that doe well. Maſters are Stewards of their owne Houſhold, and ought not onely to diſpoſe all things in order, but eſpecially to make this reſolution, that they and their houſholds will ſerue the Lord.<note place="margin">Ioſu. 24.15.</note> All men are Stewards of their owne bodies, and of the priuy cloſet of their own conſcience, as <hi>Pontan</hi> hath. There is none ſo mighty that is greater, or ſo meane and baſe, that is leſſe then a Steward to the King of Kings, to the Higheſt of all; and what goods or goodnes he vſeth, hee hath receiued them all of the Father of Lights.<note place="margin">Iam. 1.17. 1. Cor. 4.7.</note> For what haſt thou, that thou haſt not receiued? He it is that deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to his Seruants his Talents to ſome more and to ſome leſſe. Which doctrine confuteth the <hi>Pelagians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 2.5.</note> and all
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19782:10"/> ſuch as aſcribe all that they haue to their owne induſtry. Whereas all that is good, commeth from God, as being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely rich in goodneſſe and mercy towards all,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.12.</note> and yet hath neuer the leſſe himſelfe: for his riches and treaſures are inexhauſtable. All we therefore are Baylifes, Stewards, and Diſpoſers vnder God, and ſhould Miniſter the gifts which we receiue ſpirituall or temporall,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 4.10.</note> as good Stewards and diſpoſers of the manifold graces of God. And then a man proueth himſelfe to bee a faithfull Diſpoſer;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.2.</note> vvhich whoſoeuer doth, is bleſſed of God, a moſt happy man, and if he doth not diſcharge his office of Stewardſhip and ſeruice well, of all men moſt vnhappy. <hi>The Lord ſaith, Who is a faithfull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 12.42, 43, 44, 45, 46.</note> 
               <hi>and wiſe, whom the Maſter ſhall make Ruler ouer his houſhold, to giue them their portion of meat in due ſeaſon? Bleſſed is that Seruant whom his Maſter when hee commeth, ſhall finde ſo doing. Of a truth, I ſay vnto you, that hee will make him Ruler ouer all that he hath. But if that Seruant ſay in his heart, My Maſter doth defer his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, and ſhall begin to ſmite his Seruants, and Maidens, and to eat and drinke, &amp; to be drunke, the Maſter of that Seruant will come in a day when he thinketh not, and at an houre when he is not ware of, and will cut him off, and giue him his portion with the vnbeleeuers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Euery Chriſtian man and woman, bee they neuer ſo high, or neuer ſo low; neuer ſo rich, or ſo poore; haue a threefold Farme committed vnto them, the fruits of which they ought to diſpoſe wiſely, and faithfully: and therefore good Stewards are called faithfull and wiſe, of our Sauiour before, <hi>Luke</hi> 12 42. It behooueth vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to take heed what we doe, that we may make a good reckoning of our Stewardſhip, bee found true, and not falſe in gouerning theſe Farme-places, Mannors, and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor-houſes, which are theſe three, as the Learned haue ſet them downe.<note place="margin">Ludolphus de Saxonia, Iodocus Rad.</note> 
               <hi>Prima villa eſt mundus iſte; ſecunda proprium Corpus, tertia anima.</hi> The firſt Farme-Houſe is the world: the ſecond, a mans owne body: the third, his ſoule.</p>
            <p>Now in being a Steward in the firſt Farme, the world:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19782:10"/> man muſt take heed that hee become not ſo great a friend vnto it, and be not ſo much in loue with it, that he become an enemy vnto God, an vntrue &amp; falſe Steward vnto his Maſter: for he that will be a friend of this world,<note place="margin">Iam 8. Mat. 6.27.</note> is made an enemy to God. For no man can ſerue two Maſters. He may not looke to flowe in the treaaſures and pleaſures of the world, and raigne with Chriſt. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>Nemo poteſt gaudere cum mundo, &amp; regnare cum Chriſto:</hi> that is, no man can reioyce with the world, and raigne with Chriſt. And againe, he ſaith: <hi>Difficile, imo impoſsibile eſt, vt praeſentibus &amp; futuris quis fruatur bonis, vt hic ventrem, illic mentem impleat, vt à delicijs, ad delicias tranſeat, vt in vtro<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> faeculo primus ſit, vt in terra, &amp; in coelo, appareat glorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus:</hi> that is, it is an hard thing, yea, impoſsible, that any man ſhould enioy the goods of this preſent world, and alſo of the world to come: that heere hee ſhould fill his belly, and there his ſoule: that hee ſhould bee chiefe in both worlds; that he ſhould be glorious in the earth, and in heauen. And this made <hi>Iohn</hi> ſo earneſtly to diſſwade vs from the one, the world,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.15, 16, 17.</note> and ſo louingly perſwade and exhort vnto the loue of the other, the world to come. <hi>Loue not the world, neither the things that are in the world: If any man loue the world, the loue of the Father is not in him. For all that is in the world, (as the luſt of the Fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life) is not of the Father, but of the world: and the world paſſeth away, and the luſt thereof: but he that fulfilleth the will of God, abideth for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The riches, treaſures, and ſtocke of this Farme, are all goods Temporall, which being concredited to vs of this rich perſon, God, the true owner of them, we muſt take heed that we play not the bad Stewards with them: and that is done foure wayes. Firſt, in getting them wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. Secondly, in ſetting our hearts on them idolatrouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Thirdly, in keeping them to our ſelues baſely. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in ſpending them vnlawfully, and ſinfully. Of theſe foure in order,</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:19782:11"/>
            <p>Firſt, wee placed of our great and good Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Stewards in this Farme, the world, may not gaine goods through other mens hurts, building our houſes, as the moth, in other mens cloth, &amp; feeding our ſelues fat by hurting, biting, and ſpoiling others, as the moth is fatted by ſpoiling the cloth where ſhe liueth. Such men are very like to the filthy worme in a ſheepe, which is made fat by eating and conſuming the poore ſeely ſheepe, and like Lice and Fleas, which fatte themſelues by ſucking mens bloud.<note place="margin">Iam. 2.6.</note> Such bad Stewards are the wicked couetous bad rich men, who are made full by deuouring the poore, and oppreſsing them by tyrannie. Good Chriſtians are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to Trees, which doe bring forth good fruit in due ſeaſon,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.3.</note> and help euery way: For a good Tree will bring forth fruit to quench hunger and thirſt, and it will put off the iniury and violence of the ſtormy weather; but a bad tree, a Bryer, when the poore Sheepe flye vnto it for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, ſcrapeth and ſcratcheth all the wooll from their backs, and pilleth them bare. Such trees are the mercileſſe Stewards, the Tyrants of the world: which, when the poore fly vnto them for ſuccour, they tye them, and wrap them in Bonds, like as the Bryer doth the ſheepe, and then vnmercifully ſpoile them.<note place="margin">1. King. 21.</note> The rich Steward <hi>Ahab</hi> could not reſt, vnleſſe he had poore <hi>Naboth</hi> his Vineyard, and he and his curſed wife <hi>Iezabel</hi> cared not how wrongfully and cruelly they came by it.<note place="margin">Greg. decret. l. <hi>5.</hi> tit. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gregory</hi> reporteth, that ſuch cruell and bad Stewards were denyed <hi>Chriſtianorum Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulturam:</hi> Chriſtian mans buriall. And <hi>Glanuill</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Glanuil. l.</hi> 7.16.</note> writing of the Lawes and Cuſtomes of England, ſaith, that by the moſt ancient Lawes of England, the goods of an iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and defamed oppreſſour, dying without reſtitution, were eſcheated to the King, and all his Lands to the Lord of the Towne. And what becomes of himſelfe? His fleſh is giuen to the wormes, a right <hi>Cadauer.</hi> Looke to the ſillables of that word, and let <hi>ca,</hi> ſtand for <hi>caro, da,</hi> for <hi>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> and <hi>ver</hi> for <hi>vermibus.</hi> It ſheweth That mans fleſh is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19782:11"/> to wormes: and his ſoule to the Diuels, to bee tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented world without end. And therefore the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, <hi>Si haberes ſapientiam</hi> Salomonis, <hi>ſi pulchritudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem</hi> Abſalonis, <hi>ſi fortitudinem</hi> Samſonis,<note place="margin">Aug. ſuper Mat. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſi longaeuitatem</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch, <hi>ſi diuitias</hi> Croeſi, <hi>ſi foelicitatem</hi> Octauiani, <hi>quid pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt haec cùm tandem caro datur vermibus, &amp; anima daemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, cum diuete ſinc fine crucianda?</hi> That is to ſay, If thou haddeſt the wiſedome of <hi>Salomon,</hi> the beauty of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom,</hi> the ſtrength of <hi>Samſon,</hi> the long life of <hi>Enoch,</hi> the riches of <hi>Croeſus,</hi> the felicity of <hi>Octauian,</hi> what doe theſe profit thee, when at the laſt, thy fleſh is giuen to the wormes, and thy ſoule to the Diuels, with the rich man to be tormented world without end? For what will it auaile a man to winne all the world, and to loſe his owne ſoule? or what ranſome ſhall a man giue for his ſoule?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Men placed Stewards in this world, &amp; hauing the ſtock of the ſame at their diſpoſition, play the bad Stewards, in ſetting their hearts vpon them idolatrouſly. From this vice and hainous ſinne, <hi>Dauid</hi> dehorteth, when he ſaid,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.10. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>If ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches increaſe, ſet not your heart theron.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> commands them that be rich in this world, <hi>that they be not high-min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, neither put their truſt in vncertaine riches, but in the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God.</hi> In which place, hee yeeldeth a great reaſon to moue men not to truſt to riches, adding a fit Epithite to ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, calling them vncertaine. For they ebbe, they flowe, they come, they goe, they are neuer certaine. Therefore the Wiſe man gaue good counſell, when as hee ſaid: <hi>Truſt not in vncertaine riches. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alerius</hi> ſaid well to this purpoſe, <hi>Diuitiae iſtae in quibus ſummam foelicitatem conſiſtere putant, ſunt caducae, momentancae, crepundijs ſimillimae, affluunt ſubitò, ſubitò dilabuntur, nullo in loco, nullo in homine, nullo tempore ſunt certae, ſed incertiſsimo flatu fortunae huc illuc actae, quos in ſublime ſuſtulerunt ſubito caſu deijciunt.</hi> That is to ſay, Thoſe riches wherein men place their chiefe felicitie, are caduke, momentany, moſt like to gugawes, they come ſuddenly, and ſuddenly ſlide away: they are certain in no
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19782:12"/> place, in no man, at no time, but toſſed hither and thither by fortunes inſtabilitie, whom they haue exalted highly, they throw downe ſuddenly. This was one of the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers reaſons, why riches ſhould not bee felicitie: <hi>quia fluunt, &amp; refluunt,</hi> that is, they come ſpeedily to a man, and haſtily runne away, like the tyde of the Sea. So long as <hi>Troy</hi> flouriſhed, it was ſaid of King <hi>Priamus (quo no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> foelicior alter)</hi> neuer was any more happy: but when it was deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſo vncertaine was his ſtate, and ſo vaine his former truſt in riches <hi>(infoelix Priamus)</hi> ſo that this ſaying <hi>(Pria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi calamitates)</hi> became a common prouerbe ſpoken of all diſtreſſed perſons. What a fooliſh thing it is for men to truſt in riches, may appeare by the example of that rich Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, who conſidering his great in-comes and friuts that were to come in, reaſoned with himſelfe, ſaying, What ſhall I doe, becauſe I haue no roome where I may lay vp my fruits? And he ſaid, This will I doe, I will pull downe my Barnes, and build greater, and therein will I gather in all my fruits, and my goods: and I will ſay to my ſoule, Soule, thou haſt much goods laid vp for many yeeres, liue at eaſe, eate, drinke, and take thy paſtime. But God ſaid vnto him: <hi>O foole, this night will they fetch away thy Soule from thee, then whoſe ſhall thoſe things bee which thou haſt prouided?</hi> So is he that gathereth riches to himſelfe, and is not rich towards God, which truſteth to vncertaine ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and conſidereth not how deadly they ſting in the end. For as the Bee carrieth Hony in his mouth, and a ſharpe ſting in his tayle; euen ſo the couetous and cruell man truſting to his riches, hath pleaſure in his life, but pain at his death: Like to the example of the rich Glutton, whoſe pleaſant life you may ſee whiles hee liued, and his dolefull ſorrows after death: from the 19. Verſe to the end of this Chapter.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, men play the bad Stewards in this Farme, this world, by keeping their goods to themſelues baſely, and miſerably, of which goods, the Lord is the true owner,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19782:12"/> and not themſelues, but Stewards and Diſpoſers of them; and therefore, O man, thou ſhouldeſt diſpoſe them, and doe with them, as he would haue thee; for ſo ought euery one to doe that is a Steward and Bayliffe vnder another. Therefore be rich in good workes, glad to diſtribute. For this is the true vſe of riches in good men that vſe them wel, to whom they are Gods bleſsings, and the ornaments of vertue. But to the wicked that imploy them not to help others, but rather do hurt, they are <hi>ſentina malorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſt.</note> a ſinke of euils. Keepe not that to thy ſelfe baſely, which God the true owner bids thee layout cheerefully to help others. For if thou doeſt, thou art falſe to God in thy dealing. If a rich man that hath a Bayliffe, a ſeruant vnder him, ſhould ſay vnto him, Here is twenty ſhillings, pay this to ſuch and ſuch perſons, and it is as good as if thou payedſt it vnto me. If this ſeruant ſhould keepe this twenty ſhillings vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to himſelfe, and not lay it out as his Maſter bids him, nor reſtore it, you will ſay with mee, that this were a bad ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, a falſe Steward. God of his gracious goodnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth all that thou haſt vpon thee, and bids thee giue vnto the poore, feede the hungry, cloath the naked,<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> viſit the ſicke, and imploy it to other good vſes, and then thou giueſt it to him. If thou ſhouldeſt not doe this, thou art a falſe Steward, thou doeſt not repay that which thou haſt receiued. Thou a rich man carrieſt as it were the poore mans ſtocke; and therefore let them haue part with thee. <hi>Stips pauperum, theſaurus diuitum:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tiberius Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</note> the rich treaſure is the poore mans ſtocke, as ſaid the good Emperour. God will haue no Begger in Iſrael. Nature ſuffereth nothing empty, and the Raine when it falleth downe, and runneth, filleth euery chinker and hole as it runneth, and leaueth ſtill ſome moiſture behinde it, to doe good, where need is. So doe you, ye rich Stewards of the weale publique: Lay out ſome goods for the maintenance of the Goſpell, ſome for thy poore neighbours: that is done to Chriſt, that is a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in Heauen ſurely kept for thee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 18.</note> and hath a finall bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19782:13"/> 
               <hi>Math.</hi> 25. for the works of the godly follow them, to defend them, and reioyce them in the world to come. But if thou art a falſe Steward, getteſt thy goods by pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, polling, grinding the faces of the poore, and ſelling them for hoſe and ſhooes, and keepeſt them baſely to thy ſelfe, and thinkeſt at thy death to leaue them to thy wife and children: thou ſhalt vndoubtedly leaue behind thee for all thine, not a bleſſing, but a plague, and a curſe, and ſo vtterly vndoe all thy poſteritie.</p>
            <q>De malè quaeſitis vix gaudet tertius haeres.</q>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note>
               <hi>God doth viſit the ſinnes of the fathers vpon the children, vnto the third and fourth generation of them that hate him.</hi> And the Lord commaunded the cruell ſeruant himſelfe, his wife and children, and all that hee had to be ſold, <hi>Math.</hi> 18. inflicting the puniſhment not onely vpon himſelfe, but alſo vpon his wife and children. Therefore let men be not vniuſt and cruell, but true and mercifull: for as the holy father hath:<note place="margin">Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>Sola miſericordia eſt comes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>functorum.</hi> Onely mercy accompanieth the dead: That a man ſhall carry away with him, and God in his mercy will reward mercy.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, men play the bad Stewards, when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Lords goods, and lay them, not out according to his will: but ſpend them vnlawfully, wilfully, and waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully: for which they are culpable and accuſable, as this bad Steward was. The idolatrous perſon layeth out his riches vpon ſuperſtitious workes, as <hi>Ahab,</hi> and <hi>Iezabel.</hi> The quarrelſome man layeth out his goods vpon vnneceſſary ſuites of law, hindering himſelfe and his neighbours, as the <hi>Corinthians</hi> did. The vncleane perſon in chambering and wantonneſſe, as <hi>Sardanapalus</hi> and <hi>Abſalon,</hi> liuing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together in carnalitie. The Epicure and belly God, in faring deliciouſly euery day, as the rich Glutton. Gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ters, in gaming, as <hi>Octauius Auguſtus.</hi> To conclude, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19782:13"/> one which layeth out his goods in idle ſuperfluous and vngodly courſes of life, playeth the parts of an vnthrifty and vnfaithfull ſeruant, as the prodigall ſonne. And if a Preacher, Magiſtrate, or other Officer rebuke any of theſe for their vnfaithfull dealing, and prodigall ſwagge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: they will ſay, What haue they to doe with vs? we waſt and ſpend but our owne money and goods: building vpon a baſe ground: for no man is Lord and proper owner of his wealth, but onely a Steward for a time to the high Lord of all. And as a great mans Bayliffe and Steward on earth, ought to lay out the goods of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter as he commandeth, and muſt render an account how he doth it: euen ſo muſt euery man being made a Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in this farme the world, employ the talents and gifts which he receiueth, as the Lord of Lords, the high Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of all commandeth, and ſhall render an account, as hereafter followeth.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Farme or Mannor-houſe, wherein man, a Steward vnder this rich man God, is to be employed, and which he ought carefully to looke vnto, is his owne body; the goods whereof, as health, power, and ſtrength, are to be employed to the honour of God, to ſupply our owne neceſſary occaſions,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.</note> and to helpe our neighbour in all godly and honeſt affaires. This Farme ought to be well and cleanly kept, that it may be a fit dwelling Place and Temple of the holy Ghoſt: for if wee will adorne our houſes, decke them, ſweepe them, and euery way (as much as in vs lyeth) make them hanſome and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for a great earthly perſon: much more ſhould wee haue a care to preſerue from pollution, and keepe cleane our owne bodies; becauſe they are the houſes of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt; and further, to giue our members inſtruments of righteouſneſſe vnto God,<note place="margin">Rom. 6.13.</note> and to offer vp our bodies a quicke ſacrifice, holy &amp; acceptable vnto God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.1. This Farme a good Steward ſhould carefully looke vnto, leſt death ſhould enter through the ports and gates there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19782:14"/> to the ſoule, and worke the deſtruction thereof: which ports and gates I will ſet open vnto you, making as much haſte, as the Porter doth, when his Maſter waiteth for him at the gate. The ports and gates of the body are theſe fiue: Hearing, Seeing, Talking, Taſting and Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: Which gates ſhould be heedfully watched, that nothing goe in or out, but that which pleaſeth the Lord: for as a great earthly man hath a Porter to keepe his gates, that no lewd, filthy nor contagious perſon ſhould enter in to pollute his houſe, or infect his people, and ſo procure danger or death vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or otherwiſe diſorder himſelfe: Euen ſo euery Chriſtian man ſhould looke to the gates and doores of his body, leſt ſinne enter in by them, and death follow to the ſubuerſion of body and ſoule.</p>
            <p>The firſt port and gate of the body is the care, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per organ and inſtrument of hearing, it is the mouth of the ſoule which giues it nouriſhment, and ſendeth downe foode into it, and which makes it liuely and fructifie in all the reſt of mans members. Mans eares ſhould be open to heare good things,<note place="margin">Reuel. 2. Math. 13.</note> as the Word, as our Sauiour would haue vs, and the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> verſe 3. exhorteth vs ſo to doe, ſhewing the vtilitie thereof, ſaying: <hi>Incline your cares and draw neere: Heare and your ſoule ſhall liue.</hi> This word is the ſincere milke, whereby our ſoules are nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and receiue their ſpirituall growths: it is a lanterne to carry light,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.2.</note> and to direct: it is a medicine to heale, a guide to conduct, a bit to reſtraine, a ſword to defend, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to waſh, fire to inflame, ſalt to ſeaſon, wine to reioyce, raine to refreſh, a treaſure to inrich, a key to vnlocke hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen gates vnto vs, and by the merits of Chriſt Ieſus to let vs into an inheritance immortall, and vndefiled, and that fadeth not away. Now, beloued, ſeeing that mans eares are the inſtruments, &amp; veſſels to receiue this Word, let vs ſtudy to keepe them cleane, and open to receiue the Word:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. <hi>Moenan:</hi>
               </note> but ſhut this gate againſt al blaſphemous ſpeeches, ſlanderous and filthy talking: for euill words corrupt good manners.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:19782:14"/>
            <p>The ſecond port of the body is the eye, which muſt not let in bad ſights, it muſt not couetouſly looke on his neighbours goods, lands or liuings,<note place="margin">1. King. 21.</note> as <hi>Ahab</hi> did on poore <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard, nor wantonly looke on his neighbours wife, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did vpon the wife of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 11.</note> This cauſed Ieſus the ſonne of <hi>Sirach</hi> in his ninth chapter, verſe eight, to ſay, <hi>Turne away thy eyes from a beautifull woman, &amp; looke not vpon others beauty; for many haue periſhed by the beauty of women: for through it loue is kindled as a fire.</hi> What harmes enter in by this gate, it may appeare by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Putiphar</hi> his Lady and wife,<note place="margin">Gen. 39.</note> who ſteadily behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the beauty of <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> after many dayes, at the laſt ſaid, Come, lye with mee. Let vs therefore take heed of wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton looking, ſinfull luſting, and vngodly committing of ſinne and wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>The third port and gate which letteth in ſinne and death to the ſoule, is talking out of the mouth, executed by the tongue: This ſhould not be filthy, nor fooliſh,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.4. Col. 3 8. Epheſ. 4.29.</note> but good to edifie withall, that it may miniſter grace to the hearers. The tongue is the beſt member that a man hath, (if it be in tune, in good order;) but the worſt member, if it is out of order. And therefore <hi>Anacharſis</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded what was the beſt member of a man? and what the worſt? The people looking for a double anſwere, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a double queſtion: He ſpake in one word and ſaid, The tongue for the former reaſons. Therefore the Poet ſaid: <hi>Eſt vitae, pariter ac ianua lingua necis.</hi> The tongue is the gate of life and alſo of death. Therewith bleſſe we God,<note place="margin">Iam. 3.9.</note> euen the Father, and therewith curſe we men, which are made after the ſimilitude of God. But let vs looke to the true vſe of the tongue, and haue it ſtill in our hearts and minds, which is firſt to glorifie God, and then to exhort our neighbour to goodneſſe. This made <hi>Dauid</hi> to pray thus: <hi>O Lord, open thou my lippes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and my mouth ſhall ſhew forth thy praiſe:</hi> and it made the Authour to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> to giue this good counſell: <hi>Exhort one another daily, while it is called the day.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:19782:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Lactantius</hi> writing of the tongue of man, ſetteth down theſe things to be conſidered, the Finall cauſe, the Materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all cauſe, the Formall, the circumſtances, and the manner how it is, wet and moiſtened.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Finall cauſe: which although it is laſt in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, yet is firſt in intention: and that is (as the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher hath) to expreſſe the conceptions of the minde. But the Scriptures tell vs,<note place="margin">Heb. 13.15. &amp; 3.13.</note> that the tongue was giuen to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God, and to inſtruct one another.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The matter of the tongue: it is made of fleſh and not of bones, that thou ſhouldeſt not bee ſtubborne and ſtiffe in thy ſpeech, but gentle and courteous, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The forme of the tongue: it is more long then broad: open aboue, and ſhut below. This ſhewes that it ought to be ſtretched out, and to reach on high to ſound out the praiſes of God, but it ought not to be delighted to talke of things below.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The circumſtances: <hi>Labia et dentes,</hi> the lippes, and the teeth. The lippes muſt ſpeake to the glory of God, and the edification of our neighbour, and the words (as hee ſaith) muſt bee examined <hi>dentibus examinationis,</hi> with ſtrict examination, and due conſideration, before we ſpeake.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The tongue is wet from the head: ſo our ſpeech ought to be of Chriſt our head: it is wet alſo with our owne ſpittle: ſo our talke ſhould be of our owne filthines, of our owne ſinnes, that wee may be aſhamed of them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and amend, that we may be forgiuen.</p>
            <p>The fourth gate of this Farme (the body) which let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in ſinne into it, and hurts the ſoule alſo, is our taſting, our eating and drinking, which ſhould be moderate to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice nature, and not to make the fleſh proud and rebellious againſt the ſpirit, which a little will doe as the Philoſopher thought. The Apoſtle would haue vs to walke honeſtly, as in the day, not in eating and drinking, meaning exceſſe of eating and drinking, like to the ſonnes of <hi>Eli, Iob, Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tazar,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:19782:15"/> and the rich glutton:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.3.</note> and thus the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Peter</hi> vnderſtandeth it. And our Sauiour giues vs a good caueat to beware of this exceſſe in eating and drinking. <hi>Take heed to your ſelues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 21.34.</note> 
               <hi>leſt at any time your hearts be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with ſurfetting and drunkenneſſe.</hi> Exceſſiue banquet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with coſtly meate and drinke, makes a man procline and prone to luſt: <hi>Hierom. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enter mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aeſtuans, ſpumat in libidinem.</hi> Let vs therefore follow both the counſel and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Paul.</hi> His counſell is,<note place="margin">Col. 3.5.</note> that wee ſhould mortifie our fleſh, our earthly members. His example is laid down, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. where he ſaith, <hi>I tame my body, or I beate downe my body,</hi> that is, <hi>I bring it into ſeruitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt gate of this Farme, whereof wee are made Stewards, and which letteth in ſinne and death to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule, is Touching; the obiect whereof muſt be no vncleane thing, as the Apoſtle doth teach, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.17.</note> In which place the Apoſtle bringeth in an exhortation ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of <hi>Eſay</hi> 52.11. where the Prophet ſaith: <hi>Depart ye, depart ye, goe out from them, and touch no vncleane thing, &amp;c.</hi> Which exhortation the Apoſtle bringeth in there to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and all Chriſtians,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.19.</note> that for as much as they were the Temples of the holy Ghoſt, they ſhould leaue the Temples of Idols, the prophanations of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylonians, and their filthy coinquinations: for that which the Prophet ſpeaketh of the peoples going out of <hi>Babylon</hi> into the Land of the Iewes,<note place="margin">Eſay 52.11.</note> the ſame he transferreth from the type, to the thing ſignified, to wit, that all they which haue giuen their names to God, ſhould forſake the wicked prophanations of the Gentiles, their haynous ſinnes,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.11.</note> their filthy kind of life, Haue no fellowſhip with the vnfruitfull workes of darkenes: yea, &amp; they ſhould be ſo farſtrangers from an vncleane life, that they ſhould not ſo much as touch any vncleane thing, leſt they ſhould be defiled: for he that toucheth pitch, ſhall be defiled.<note place="margin">Eſay 52.11. 1. Cor. 6.17. Act. 2.40.</note> Which places may well be vnderſtood of both ill company-keeping, and of vncleane liuing: from both of theſe we are forbidden.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19782:16"/> But to ſpeake a little of the former: Wee ſee by dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experience, that one mangie horſe will infect another: &amp; therefore when wee ſee in a cloſe or ſtable ſuch a one, wee will ſay, Wee will not put our horſes there, leſt they ſhould be infected: In like manner wee our ſelues will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine the company of ſuch as haue any contagious and and dangerous diſeaſes, as the Leproſie, or the plague; and we will deſire the ſocieties of ſuch as are ſound and heal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy: And why doe we not refraine the companies of the wicked, whoſe vile and lewd examples in ſpeeches and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſoone depraue vs, and confirme vs in naughtineſſe? And againe, Why do we not delight in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of the godly, knowing that of them we may learne goodneſſe? for with the holy thou ſhalt be holy, and with the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thou ſhalt learne frowardneſſe. Let vs therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, abhorre, and flee from naughtineſſe, and wicked mens companies, as from the ſting of a Serpent, and poyſon of a Baſiliske, (vnleſſe it be in hope to conuert them) and let vs touch no vncleane thing, but practiſe holineſſe of life and conuerſation.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.3, 4, 5.</note> For this is the will of God, euen our ſanctification, and that we ſhould abſtaine from forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, that euery one of vs ſhould know how to poſſeſſe his veſſell in holineſſe and honour, and not in the luſt of concupiſcence, euen as the Gentiles which knowe not God: and God hath called vs not to vncleanneſſe, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to holineſſe.<note place="margin">7. verſe.</note>
            </p>
            <p>O deare Chriſtians, Chriſt hath made vs Prieſts vnto God,<note place="margin">Reuel. 1.6.</note> and St. <hi>Peter Ep.</hi> 2.5. ſaith, <hi>That we are an holy Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, to offer vp ſpirituall ſacrifices, acceptable to God by Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt and</hi> Paul beſeecheth vs to <hi>giue vp our bodies a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſacrifice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuel. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>holy, and acceptable vnto God.</hi> O let vs doe ſo, let vs doe ſo; let vs ſleepe no longer in ſinne, rocked and lulled in the cradle of ſecuritie. And thus much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſecond Farme place, and the ports and gates of the ſame, which a carefull Steward ſhould circumſpectly and warily looke vnto.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:19782:16"/>
            <p>The third farme, is the ſoule of man, which although it is created pure of God, as the Angels are, yet being in the body, a foule and filthy priſon, and yet part of man, (for man doth conſiſt of a body and a ſoule) is polluted by this participation with the body, is tainted now with originall ſinne, and performes not many times good parts and offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Now to ſpeake ſomewhat more plainely to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: Whereas there are two parts of mans ſoule, the Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and the Will: The office of the intellect is, to diſcerne among obiects what is good to be allowed, or meet to de diſalolwed: It is the office of the Will to chuſe and follow that good which the intellect ſhall appoint, and to deſpiſe and refuſe that which the vnderſtanding ſhall diſallow. If the former, (the intellect) faileth in diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and iudgement: then the Will faileth alſo in chuſing and following: for the intellect is as it were the ſoules guide and gouernour, the Will euer expecteth iudgement from the intellect, and is ſtill at his becke. Now whereas man faileth many times in iudgement and vnderſtanding; and the Will not onely couets, but chuſeth that which is euill; it commeth to paſſe that the ſoule is polluted, and in mans members performes wicked actions. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore man muſt craue the conduction of Gods holy Spirit, to be led by him, and the Word of God, which muſt be a lanterne to his feet, &amp; a light to his pathes, and then he ſhall goe well. This ſoule of man ſhould not be polluted with impure and vncleane thoughts, and bad choyces, and all the vertues and powers of it ought to be directed princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally to the knowledge, loue, and honour of God.</p>
            <p>The ſoule of man performeth diuers offices in man, and according to her ſeuerall performances takes diuers names, as <hi>Iſiodorus</hi> writeth: <hi>Anima dum viuificat corpus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Secundo eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>molog.</note> 
               <hi>anima est: dum vult, animus eſt: dum ſcit, mens: dum recolit, memoria: dum rectum iudicat, ratio eſt: dum ſpirat, ſpiritus eſt: dum aliquid ſentit, ſenſus eſt.</hi> This is a point fit for the learned, and therefore I leaue the Engliſhing of it to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19782:17"/> them that can vnderſtand it. And ſo much of the third and laſt Farme-houſe, which Man, a Steward vnder God, muſt looke vnto, and haue an eſpeciall care of: for it is immortall.</p>
            <p>By this which I haue ſpoken, it may appeare what a great burthen and charge lyeth vpon euery mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to looke vnto his wayes and pathes, his conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, ſtudies, and all his labours, and workes. For Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, who by his Word and great power made all things, in his infinite wiſedome created nothing vaine and idle. The glorious Angels are miniſtring ſpirits, <hi>Seruentes</hi> vnto God, his Meſſengers to do his wil, &amp; ſent for the good of the Church, to bring glad tidings, to comfort and help: which the word AGGELOS teacheth Which thing the Author to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> hath well obſerued,<note place="margin">Chap. 1.14.</note> ſaying, that they are ſent from God to Miniſter for their ſakes, which ſhall be heires of ſaluation. And therefore <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, <hi>Angeli ad miniſterium pro noſtra ſalute ſemper mittuntur:</hi> that is, the Angels are alwayes ſent to ſerue for our ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The coruſcant and glorious Sunne doth goe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh his courſes (as God hath appointed) by motions and operations. <hi>Adam</hi> the firſt and principalleſt man, as ſoone as he was created, was placed in the Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> to dreſſe, trim, and keepe it, in a decent and good order, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.15. And yet this being before the fall, and before any weedes and trumperies that there might grow, there was no need to labour; yet God appointing him to this worke, hereby doth ſhew how much he abhorred idlenes. <hi>Adam</hi> then was, as it were, the Lords labourer as well as his owne, euen before the fall, in the time of his integritie. But after the fall, labour was a puniſhment laid vpon <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and all his poſterity. <hi>In the ſweat of thy browes, or face, thou ſhalt get thy liuing.</hi> Now labour is paine: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when we ſpeak of a laborious man, we ſay, ſuch a one taketh great paine, whether it be in Mechanicall crafts and occupations, or altogether in contemplation. All men are
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19782:17"/> Stewards, and muſt labour, the Word of God exempteth none, and God hath no reſpect of perſons. Our Sauiour <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. will ſuffer none at any time to be idle, but ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them to labour in his Vineyard.</p>
            <p>Miniſters are the Lords Stewards, and muſt labour,<note place="margin">Math. 9.37. 2. Cor. 6.1.</note> and therefore are called Labourers: they are called workmen, and workers together, and ſhould ſhew themſelues to bee cunning workemen, rightly diuiding the Word of God.</p>
            <p>They are the Lords Seruants, and receiue Talents:<note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.15.</note> and therefore ſhould make good vſe of them.</p>
            <p>His Shepheards:<note place="margin">Ezec. 34.</note> therefore muſt feede and ouerſee his flockes.</p>
            <p>His Cryers: therefore muſt cry alowd and ſpare not:<note place="margin">Eſay 58.1.</note> 
               <hi>Tell the people their tranſgreſsions, and the Houſe of</hi> Iacob <hi>their ſinnes:</hi> they may not be dumbe.</p>
            <p>His Builders: therefore ſhould goe on in their worke.</p>
            <p>Fiſhers: therefore ought to let ſlip their Nets, to take and winne ſoules, but caſt their Angle to take money, as <hi>Peter</hi> did.</p>
            <p>Embaſſadours of the Lord:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.20.</note> Therefore they ought to haue tongues, and ſufficiency to doe the Lords meſſage.</p>
            <p>Feeders: therefore ought to haue meat, and to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute it.</p>
            <p>Sowers: therefore ought to ſcatter the Seed of the Word into mens hearts.</p>
            <p>His Leaders: therefore they ſhould conduct their flockes in the way of the Lord.</p>
            <p>His eſpeciall Fighters againſt Sinne, the World, the Fleſh, the Diuell, Heretikes, and all the enemies of Gods Truth, as <hi>Paul</hi> was, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7.</p>
            <p>By theſe, and many other like Appellations and Names we ſee, and may learne, that God vouchſafeth the helpe of Miniſters, to execute his will, and vſeth them as meanes to ſaue his Sheepe from periſhing; yea, they are the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to conuert the people. The Lord ſaued the Arke, but by <hi>Noah:</hi> He conuerted the Niniuites, but by <hi>Ionas;</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:19782:18"/> inſtructed the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> but by <hi>Philip:</hi> perſwaded <hi>Corneli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> but by <hi>Peter:</hi> called <hi>Paul,</hi> but by <hi>Ananias. Paul</hi> muſt plant, <hi>Apollo</hi> water, and God giueth the increaſe. Albeit Chriſt is the light, yet Miniſters beare witneſſe of the light: though he be the fountaine of liuing water, yet Miniſters are the conduits to conuey them to the people: though he be the Phyſician, yet Miniſters are the Apothecaries, to make the confection: though he be the cauſe efficient, yet Miniſters are the inſtrument, euen helpers: though hee be King, yet Miniſters are his Embaſſadours; yea, which is more, if more can bee, <hi>Paul</hi> telleth <hi>Timothy,</hi> that if hee take heede to himſelfe, and vnto doctrine, and continue therein, he ſhall ſaue both himſelfe, and them that heare him: and ſo <hi>Timothy</hi> ſhould not onely be an Helper, but a Sauer in ſort. Miniſters then muſt bee good Stewards, carefull, and painefull. <hi>Cura curarum regimen animarum:</hi> The gouernment of ſoules, is the care of all cares.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding this office of the Miniſtery truely ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, bringeth honour: yea, it is worthy double ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. For the Elders that rule well, are worthy double honour, ſpecially they that labour in the Word and Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. Many loue to rule, but they rule not well, neither labour in the Word and Doctrine: and therefore are not worthy double honour: for there is none due, but to the painefull, Steward; the labouring Miniſter, as Father <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timer</hi> well ſaid in his fourth Sermon before King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6.</p>
            <p>Noblemen, Knights, and Gentlemen of great valour and worth are Stewards, and ought to employ ſome houres in the ſeruice of God, to pleaſe him; as <hi>Iehoſophat, Aſa, Ioſias,</hi> and <hi>Ezechias</hi> did. They ought alſo to do good to the Commonwealth, not neglecting a reaſonable and neceſſary care of their owne followers, and Families. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Chronicles teſtifie, that <hi>Alphred</hi> King of England, and Founder of the Vniuerſitie of <hi>Oxon,</hi> diuided the day and night into three parts: eight houres he ſpent in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19782:18"/> ſeruice of God, eight houres vpon his Country, and eight houres vpon his body, and the maintenance of his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, letting no time to paſſe away vnprofitably, alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring, that whileſt he had time, he ſhould doe good. <hi>Erneſtus Luneburgenſis</hi> ſpent himſelfe in doing good; and therefore was repreſented by a golden Candleſticke, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a Torch in it, wherein were ingrauen theſe Letters in gold, ſhewing his good and charitable minde, &amp; deeds of charitie, proceeding from him. <hi>A. S. m. i. c.</hi> A ſtood for <hi>Alijs, S.</hi> for <hi>ſeruiens, m.</hi> for <hi>me, i.</hi> for <hi>ipſum,</hi> and <hi>c.</hi> for <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumo.</hi> Set all together, the ſentence will be, <hi>Alijs ſeruiens, meipſum conſumo:</hi> I conſume my ſelfe, by ſeruing other mens turnes. It is a common ſpeech among worldly men, when they are exhorted to help the poore beeing in diſtreſſe, to ſay, We will doe what we can for our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, not hurting our ſelues; but wee will looke to our ſelues firſt. O beloued, theſe men are louers of themſelues, more then louers of God, or of their neighbours. The old commandement giuen of God, was, and is:<note place="margin">Ioh. 13.34. &amp; 15.12.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe:</hi> and who doth ſo now? And yet our Sauiour in the New Teſtament preſſeth vs more nearely, teaching vs to loue one another, as hee loued vs: now Chriſt loued vs better then himſelf: for if he had not, hee would haue harkened to <hi>Peter,</hi> diſſwading him from his ſuffrings for vs, and perſwading him to pity &amp; fauour, himſelfe: but hee would not follow his wicked counſell, but knowing it not to bee of God, ſaid to him,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> 
               <hi>Get thee behinde, Satan, for thou art an offence vnto me, &amp;c.</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians take their names of Chriſt, and ſhould be of Chriſts minde, and reckon euery one an enemie vnto them, that diſſwadeth them from doing good to their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, when they may, although it be to their owne loſſe, hurt, and hazzard not onely of goods, but alſo of life. There is a great hatred betweene the Dragon, and the Pel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican: the Dragon, when hee knoweth that the Pellican hath yong Birds, watcheth her when ſhe goeth from her
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19782:19"/> neſt, and then commeth and poiſoneth the yong ones. The Pellican returning, and finding her younglings dead, bewaileth the loſſe of their liues, ſending our moſt dolefull and lamentable cryes and ſqueakings, and at the laſt, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting al care of her ſelfe, and burning with a feruent loue towards them, ſhe pecketh her owne breſt, letteth out her owne bloud, which ſtreaming out on them, reuiueth them. In like manner, there was a great hoſtility betweene the great Red Dragon, the old Serpent, (I meane Satan) and all mankinde. He in <hi>Adam</hi> poyſoned and killed vs all with ſinne.<note place="margin">Rom. 5.12. Math 26.28.</note> Our Sauiour Chriſt pittying our miſerable caſe, and willing to help vs, ſhed his owne bloud for vs, and made vs aliue againe.<note place="margin">Ioh. 11.25.</note> Such a loue ſhould be in vs, when we ſee our Chriſtian brethren in extremitie,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.16.</note> and can help. We ought to lay downe our liues for them, much more we ſhould impart our goods, and beſtow any labour and paine to doe them good. I write theſe things to you (you Honourable, Worſhipfull, and rich men of the world) to moue you (if it pleaſe God that I may,) to be liberall, and rich in good workes,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 6.18.</note> and to lay vp treaſures in heauen for your ſelues, by ſhewing workes of mercy. Which thing moſt of you are able to doe, and may doe without danger of life. O then be willing to make performance, and God will heere on earth increaſe your basket and your ſtore, as he did the Loaues and Fiſhes in the Diſciples hands,<note place="margin">Math. 14.</note> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributing them, and hee will lengthen that which you haue, as hee did the Meale and the Oyle of the poore Widdow of Sarephath:<note place="margin">1. King. 17.</note> you ſhall receiue mercy at the Lords hands in earth, and in Heauen at the laſt Day, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting bleſſing.<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> Therefore flatter not your ſelues, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of your high Places of Honour and Worſhip. For God priuiledgeth not you more then the poore, to be idle Stewards. There muſt bee no ciphers in Gods. Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, no mutes in his Grammar, no blankes in his Kalender, no Drones in his Bee-hiue, no loyterers in his Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place, and Vineyard, no idle Stewards in his Farmes. And
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19782:19"/> ſo, my good Lords, and you Worſhipfull Gentlemen, with all reſpectiue duties, I humbly take my leaue of you.</p>
            <p>Lawiers are Stewards, and diligently and faithfully ſhould examine their Clients cauſes, deale plainely and iuſtly with them; and not for gaine ſake tell them a lye, and confirme them in errours, and make them pay for all, ſowing the ſeeds of Sedition, which come vp euery Terme, when as louely compoſitions and agreements at home might better ſerue: and whereas their Clients are poore already, they in the end make them poorer.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>5.</hi> de guber.</note> 
               <hi>Siluia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hac lege tueri pauperes videntur, vt ſpolient, hac le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge defendunt miſeros, vt miſeriores faciant, defendendo:</hi> that is to ſay, With this Law they ſeeme to defend the poore, that they may ſpoile them. With this ſame Law they defend poore wretches, to make them more miſerable by their defending. And yet for all this, who better rewarded then the Lawyer? A Preacher that ſpeaketh the truth from God, and vſeth the meanes to win mens ſoules to God, hath many times for his paines, reproaches: but Lawiers ſometimes for pleading vniuſt cauſes, haue large fees: and when their Client is ouerthrowne, his cauſe loſt, and his money ſpent, they blame the Client, &amp; ſay, He told me the beſt, but not the worſt, we lacked good information But now what becomes of this poore man ouerthrowne? He perhaps hath maintained the ſuite with borrowed mony, and is become indebted vnto many, and new ſuites by his Creditors come vpon him, Baylifes (who liue &amp; reioyce at poore mens fals) ſwarm about him like Caterpillers, and the Flies of <hi>Egypt,</hi> they take him, and prey vpon him. Thus the vnmercifull feed vpon him when hee is downe, as Wolues, Dogs, Kites, Crowes, and ſuch like doe vpon a Sheepe that lyes in a Ditch, and is not able to riſe. But this dangerous and hurtfull ſore is commonly bred and maintained by the inferiour ſort of Lawiers, who wring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out matter from poore ſilly men, bring it vp out of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19782:20"/> the countrey, to the better ſort of Lawyers, and worke them to vndertake buſineſſes, concealing the truth many times from them, which theſe good Lawyers, whereof (God be thanked) we haue great ſtore, learned and godly, skilfull in our Lawes, would neuer vndertake, if the truth at the firſt were deliuered vnto them. O God, giue them knowledge of the truth and righteous cauſes, and make them maintainers and followers of the ſame. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Husbandmen, Artificers, Trades-men, and all other workemen of occupation, and labourers whatſoeuer are Stewards, and ought truſtily, and not deceitfully; diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not idly labour and take paine early and late, leſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty come vpon them, as one that trauelleth, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity like an armed man, <hi>Prou.</hi> 6.11.<note place="margin">Prou. 6.</note> He that will not worke in Harueſt, ſhall want at Chriſtmas. The very Bees and Emmets, by the inſtinct of nature, labor diligently in Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.8.</note> to prouide for Winter. So ſhould poore labourers do to prouide for them, and theirs, that they may not proue worſe then Infidels. A ſlothfull hand, ſaith <hi>Salomon,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth poore;<note place="margin">Prou. 10.4.</note> but the hand of the diligent, maketh rich. He that gathereth in Summer, is a wiſe ſonne; but hee that ſleepeth in Harueſt, is the ſonne of confuſion. Let euery man therefore in his place ſhew himſelfe a good Steward, that he may eate the labours of his hands:<note place="margin">Pſal. 128.</note> which is a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thing, and then hee may eate with a good conſcience. <hi>Salomon</hi> gaue good counſell,<note place="margin">Prou. 5.15.</note> when he ſaid, <hi>Drinke the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of thine owne ciſterne, and of the Riuers out of the mids of thine owne Well.</hi> Get thee goods with thine own honeſt labours, and then eate with thanksgiuing; but if thou art idle,<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.11, 12.</note> and laboureſt not: the Apoſtle thinketh thee vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to eate. The Heathens did hold, that no good thing could be had without labour and paines taking; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſpake of vertue and knowledge, thus:
<q>
                  <l>Virtutem poſuere dij ſudore parandam.</l>
                  <l>Non iacet in molli venerandae ſcientia lecto</l>
                  <l>Ipſa, ſed aſſiduo parta labore venit.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19782:20"/> Man muſt depend vpon God; yet vſe the meanes, and he will giue a bleſſing. Our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus could haue giuen fiſh vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> without caſting out his net, but he would not; to teach him and the Church, that is to ſay, all the faithfull, by his example,<note place="margin">Luk. 5.</note> to labour and to vſe the meanes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> This doctrine teacheth vs, that all men of what Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Trade or occupation ſoeuer they are of, are Stewards vnder the high God, are ſeruants, or at leaſt-wiſe ought to be ſo vnto God, and therefore muſt needes ſerue, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and not loyter, and then they ſhall better auoide the baites and ſnares of Satan: for the Diuell hath neuer ſo fit opportunitie to ſow Tares among the Wheat,<note place="margin">Math. 13.</note> as when men are aſleepe, careleſſe and idle: for then hee hatcheth and breedeth many vices in vs: for like as in a ſtanding water wormes are ingendred and bred, and not in a ſweet and ſwift current: So likewiſe in an idle, (and not in a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring body) many idle and euill thoughts are bred, and foſtered. In which lamentable eſtate, as long as man lyeth in, he is in the Diuels ſeruice, he is the Diuels labourer, as <hi>Bernard</hi> writeth vpon the <hi>Canticles,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Qui in labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re hominum honeſto non ſunt, in labore profectó daemonum erunt:</hi> that is in effect, as if he ſhould ſay: <hi>Men that are loyterers, are the Diuels labourers:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6.</note> 
               <hi>and what is the wages and pay of the Diuell? Death and deſtruction, the wages of all ſinne.</hi> The Crab-fiſh (as <hi>Plinie</hi> ſaith) when he ſeeth the Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter lye gaping againſt the Sunne-beames, priuily ſtealeth vpon him, and putteth a pibble into the mouth of the Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and ſo getteth out the fiſh, and leaueth nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him but the ſhell, good for nothing: So likewiſe when we lie idle, rocked and lulled in the cradle of ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the Diuell ſtealeth into vs, getteth away our hearts, and deſtroyeth our ſoules, and leaues nothing but a body ſubiect to ſinne, which he alſo will haue at the laſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A man that laboureth, ſhall thereby the better be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble with a good conſcience to prouide for himſelfe and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19782:21"/> his family, without making falſe reckonings to deceiue his Maſter, as this falſe ſteward did.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A painfull man ſhall the better be able to relieue and helpe others, and this is a Chriſtian mans duty: for as <hi>Plato de legibus</hi> hath, <hi>Non ſolùm nobis ſumus nati, ſed partem patria, partem parentes, partem amici vendicant,</hi> that is to ſay, We are borne onely for our ſelues, but our Countrey claimes part for her own, our parents part, and our friends part. We muſt doe good to all, but chiefely to the houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of faith: Wee muſt doe good to all, I ſay: yea, euen to our enemies that hate vs, following the example of our heauenly Father, who letteth his Sunne to ſhine, and the raine to fall vpon the good mans ground and the bad. And this muſt a man doe with his true gotten goods: for the gift that is giuen, being truly gotten, maketh the almes more pleaſing to God.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This ſheweth the true end wherefore God maketh men rich Stewards, and deliuereth them his goods: not that they ſhould lay them vp, and doe no good with them, nor put their truſt in them, nor keepe them baſely, nor ſpend them waſtfully &amp; ſinfully; but that they ſhould glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtribute them, according to the good pleaſure of the chiefe Owner, God; to the benefiting of the Church, Gods faithfull people: for as a ſheepe beareth a fleece of wooll, not for himſelfe, but for the neceſſitie and benefit of men: Euen ſo the gifts of God which he giueth, either ſpirituall, or temporall, we are not to keepe onely for our ſelues, but to ſupply the neceſſities and wants of others: for ſo the Apoſtle teacheth vs,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.10.</note> ſaying, <hi>As euery man hath receiued the gift, let him miniſter the ſame one to another, at good diſpoſers of the manifold graces of God.</hi> Wee as feeling members one of another, ought to relieue and ſupport one another: for as the Stagges when they ſwimme ouer a great riuer to feed in ſome meddow, ſwimme all on a row, and lay their heads one ouer anothers backe, carrying the waight of one anothers hornes, and when the firſt is wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19782:21"/> another takes his roome, and ſo doe it by courſe: Euen ſo muſt we doe, beare one anothers burthen, helping and doing good one to another, til we haue paſſed the trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome waues of this world, and are come to the hauen of eternall ſaluation. Then ſhall we approue our ſelues good Stewards, good ſeruants to our high Maſter the Lord God Almighty, we ſhall be found faithfull in our places, and ſhall haue the fruit thereof, an eternall bleſſing, as our Sauiour doth teach, ſaying,<note place="margin">Mat. 24.45, 46.</note> 
               <hi>Who is a faithfull Steward and wiſe, whom the Master ſhall make ruler ouer his houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, to giue them their portion of meate in ſeaſon?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.42, 43, 44.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed is that ſeruant whom his Maſter when hee commeth ſhall find ſo doing: Of a truth! ſay vnto you, that he will make him ruler ouer all that he hath, that is, hee will make him an heire of eternall life: Hee ſhall inherit the Kingdome prepared from the beginning of the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25.34.</note> 
               <hi>Hee ſhall walke with the Lord in white garments,</hi> that is, <hi>hee ſhall be glorified,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and haue life euerlaſting, and the glorious company of Chriſt: He ſhall be in</hi> Abrahams <hi>boſome, as</hi> Lazarus <hi>was,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 16.</note> 
               <hi>and eate of the tree of Life in the middeſt of the heauenly Paradiſe of God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>Hee ſhall haue the Crowne of glory: Hee ſhall be a pillar in the Temple of God,</hi> that is, <hi>hee ſhall be firme and ſtable in glory, as a pillar irremoueable, &amp;c. Eye hath not ſeene,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 3.12.</note> 
               <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eare heard; neither euer did enter into the heart of man, what good things the Lord hath prepared for them that loue him, and ſerue him in holineſſe and righteouſneſſe all the daies of their life. Illud verum et ſummum gaudium eſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi> in a Sermon, that is the true and greateſt ioy: and therefore as it were rauiſhed with a great loue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, cryed out, <hi>O beata regio Paradiſt! ó beata regio delicia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum!</hi> O bleſſed region of Paradiſe! O bleſſed region of delights! And therefore hee exhorteth vs to bee out of loue with this world whiles we bee heere, and to haſten thither, ſaying thus, <hi>Feſtinemus ad locum tutiorem, ad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grum vberiorem, ad paſtum ſaniorem, vt habitemus ſinè me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu, abundemus ſinè defectu, epulemur ſinè fastidio,</hi> that is
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19782:22"/> to ſay: Let vs haſten to a more ſafe place, to a more fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile ground, to a more ſound feeding, where wee may inhabit without feare, abound without defect, banquet without diſdaine. Here is the hauen, the bleſſed port of reſt, and the liberall portion of the good and faithfull Steward. But the ſlothfull, waſtfull, cruell and vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Steward ſhall be cut off, or cut into pieces, and haue his portion with hypocrites, there ſhall bee weeping and gnaſhing of teeth, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.51. Wherefore ſeeing that we all rather deſire to be reputed, (yea, &amp; be indeed) good Stewards then bad, to enioy a good place and portion, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a bad: let vs depart out of the Kingdome of ſinne and Satan, and come to the Kingdome of light, let vs ſhew and approue our ſelues good Stewards, keeping our Farme places, the world, the body, and the ſoule well, and let vs not get our goods in the firſt mannor houſe, the world, wrongfully, nor put our truſt in them idolatrouſly, nor keepe them to our ſelues baſely, nor ſpend them waſtfully and vngodly, but lay them out for the maintenance of the Goſpell, and helpe of the poore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digent members of Chriſt Ieſus liberally.</p>
            <p>Againe, let vs looke to our ſecond Farme place, and mannor houſe, (our bodie) that it be cleane, and fit for the chiefe Lord and Maſter of all, and his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, and the holy Ghoſt to come into. Let vs dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently watch the ports and gates of the ſame, our Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, Seeing, Talking, Taſting, and Touching, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing goe in, nor come out, that may defile the body. Laſtly, let vs haue an eſpeciall care of our principall part, the ſoule, the laſt mannor houſe. Let repentance ſweepe it cleane from impure thoughts, and wicked co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations, let a good conſcience be his bedding, let faith be euer looking to Chriſt Ieſus, and cleanſing, and let the graces and vertues of the holy Ghoſt be the orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his lodging. And in all things, and in all our places and charges, let vs proue our ſelues good, wiſe, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19782:22"/> faithfull Stewards, that it may be ſaid vnto vs, &amp; to euery one of vs, <hi>It is well done, good ſeruant, thou haſt beene faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in little, I will make thee Ruler ouer much: enter in into thy Maſters ioy.</hi> This approbation and allowance of our Stewardſhip, and vnſpeakeable reward, giue and grant vs (O heauenly Father) not for our worthineſſe (for we haue no merits) but for thy mercies and graces in Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The end of the firſt Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <head>
               <hi>THE SECOND SERMON.</hi> And the ſame was accuſed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S all men are Stewards vnder God, &amp; what good Talents &amp; gifts ſo euer they haue, they receiue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him the fountaine of all graces: Euen ſo they ought to occupy &amp; imploy the ſame, according to the good pleaſure of him the Collator and Donator, as it is plaine in the Parable of the Talents, <hi>Math</hi> 25. And as S. <hi>Peter</hi> teacheth, 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 4. ſaying, As euery one hath receiued the gift, euen ſo miniſter the ſame, as good Stewards of the manifold graces of God: Whoſoeuer doth this, is commended and rewarded of his high Lord and Maſter, with theſe words of grace to his comfort: <hi>O well done, thou good &amp; faithfull Seruant, thou haſt been faithfull ouer few things, I will make thee Ruler ouer many things: enter thou into the ioy of thy Lord,</hi> Mat. 25.21.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19782:23"/> But if a ſeruant haue much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>credited vnto him, if it be but of an earthly Maſter, and imploy it ill, ſpend it waſtfully, eating and drinking with the Drunkards, participating with the Adulterers, and intreating his fellow-ſeruants hardly, and yet thinketh that his euill carriage and outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſhall not be knowne, but that he ſhall eſcape with impunitie: O how this man deceiueth himſelfe: For the fellow-ſeruants will relate the treacheries, bad vſages, and cruelties of their fellowes to their Lord. As thoſe ſeruants did which ſaw their fellow-ſeruant ſo cruelly handled, <hi>Math.</hi> 18. And heere the bad Steward is accuſed to his Lord. Now if wee ſee by dayly experiences, that bad Stewards to earthly Maſters eſcape not alwayes free with their falſe dealings, and other euill behauiours, but one or other will eſpy them, and diſcloſe them, and giue their Maſter intelligence, and then he reckoneth and accounteth with them, and diſplaceth them: then we may much more aſſure our ſelues, that no cloud of darknes, no maske nor veile can be caſt before the Lords eyes:<note place="margin">Pſal. 79.9.</note> 
               <hi>For hee that planted the eare, ſhall be not heare? Or he that made the eye, ſhall hee not ſee?</hi> God knoweth, noteth, ſeeth, ouerſeeth al things; yea, the very ſecrets of the heart: and yet if he were not ſo quicke of capacitie, of hearing, and ſeeing: Yet there are many tell-tales, and pick-thankes in the Familie, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late all our miſdemeanours, and accuſe vs vnto him, as in my Text; the falſe Steward is ſaid to be accuſed. And here beginneth a lamentable diſcourſe, &amp; a Tragicall Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the miſerable eſtate of a bad Steward, laid down in my Text, in theſe points: Firſt, <hi>He is defamed, or accuſed,</hi> in theſe words: <hi>and the ſame was accuſed.</hi> Secondly, <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: (and he called him.)</hi> Thirdly, reprehended, in theſe words, <hi>(How commeth it to paſſe that I heare this of thee?)</hi> Fourthly, he yeeldeth an account: <hi>Come render an account of thy Stewardſh.</hi> Fiftly, he is put out of his Office, in theſe words: <hi>For thou mayeſt be no longer Steward.</hi> Of theſe in order: and firſt of his accuſation. Wherein we are to note,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19782:23"/> firſt, his Accuſers: Secondly, the capitall and hainous crimes whereof he is accuſed.</p>
            <p>The Accuſers or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainants are theſe:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Satan.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Angels.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Saints.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>His owne Conſcience.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Sinnes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>Creatures of God.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The hainous crimes wherof the euill Steward is accuſed of, are theſe fiue:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfaithfulneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Cruelty.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Slothfulneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Ill company-keeping.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Waſtfulneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, the euill, vnfaithfull, and vngracious Steward is accuſed of the Diuell. For which cauſe hee is called,<note place="margin">Reu. 12.</note> The accuſer of the Brethren, which accuſeth them before God day and night. Hee accuſeth our workes, words, and thoughts, as <hi>Gregory</hi> noteth, ſaying thus:<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> moral.</note> 
               <hi>Diabolus prima opera noſtra, deinde verba, &amp; tandem cogitationes accuſat.</hi> He defameth man, accuſeth him of wickedneſſes, reporteth them before God, calleth for vengeance and ſpeedy death, leſt the thred of mans life ſhould be drawne out along, and he ſhould repent and obtaine eternall life.<note place="margin">Iob 1.</note> If Satan was ſo impudent, that he bluſhed not to defame and accuſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God holy <hi>Iob,</hi> a man to whom there was none com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable in his time on the earth, a perfect and iuſt man, one that feared God, and eſchewed euill: What is it that he will not alledge againſt a ſinfull Nation, a people laden with iniquitie, a ſeed of the wicked, corrupt children, in whom, from the ſole of the foote, vnto the head, there is nothing ſound in them, but they draw wickedneſſe with cords of vanity, and ſinne as it were with a cart-rope?</p>
            <p>Secondly, an vniuſt Steward is defamed and accuſed of Angels, <hi>Iob</hi> 20.27. <hi>Reuelant coeli iniquitatem improbi.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 1.</note> The
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19782:24"/> Heauens reueale the iniquitie of a wicked man. <hi>Per coelos, Angelos, qui in coelis ſunt, accipe,</hi> ſaith the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: In <hi>Math.</hi> 18. The fellow-ſeruant told to the Lord the cruelty of his ſeruant. Now the Angels are our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-ſeruants, as we may probably gather out of <hi>Iohn, Reu.</hi> 22. where he fell downe to worſhip the Angell, who ſaid vnto him, <hi>See thou doe it not: for I am thy fellow-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, and the fellow-ſeruant of thy Brethren the Prophets, which keepe the ſayings of this Booke: Worſhip thou God.</hi> Loe, the Angell ſaid to <hi>Iohn,</hi> that he was his fellow-ſeruant, and not onely his, but of his Brethren the Prophets, which kept the ſayings of Gods Booke. The Angels then tell God our faults as here. Our prayers, holineſſe, and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, as in <hi>Tobie</hi> 12. Let vs therefore that liue in the preſence of God, and his Angels, carry our ſelues godly, and honeſtly, knowing that moſt pure eyes doe looke vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, a bad Steward is blamed and accuſed of Saints both triumphant which are in Heauen, and militant which liue on earth. Of Saints triumphant, whoſe bloud was ſhed on earth by cruell Tyrants and perſecutors, for the Word of God, and teſtimonie which they had. For theſe being in the bleſſed port of Heauen cry out againſt them that imbrued their hands in their bloud,<note place="margin">Reu. 6.</note> ſaying, <hi>How long tarrieſt thou, O Lord, which art holy, and true, to iudge and auenge our bloud on them that dwell on earth!</hi> And that an vngracious Steward is accuſed before God of Saints, that are liuing in this mortall life, it is alſo moſt manifeſt. <hi>Ieremy</hi> blamed and accuſed the Iewes vnto God, yea, and craued reuengement againſt them in theſe words: <hi>O Lord of hoſts, thou righteous iudge,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 11.</note> 
               <hi>thou that tryeſt the reines, and the hearts, let me be auenged of them. For vnto thee haue I committed my cauſe.</hi> When <hi>Antiochus</hi> oppreſſed the Church of God with great tyrannie, <hi>Dauid</hi> accuſed him vnto God in theſe words;<note place="margin">Pſal. 74.10, 18.</note> 
               <hi>Remember this, O Lord, how the enemy hath rebuked, and the fooliſh people hath blaſphemed thy Name. Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remy</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:19782:24"/> in like manner accuſed and blamed his perſecutors vnto GOD, and craued him to reuenge him, ſaying,<note place="margin">Ier. 15.15.</note> 
               <hi>O Lord, thou knoweſt, remember me, and viſit me, and reuenge mee of my perſecuters.</hi> If the poore is oppreſſed of the rich, and make his mone vnto the Lord, accuſing him and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for reuengement: The Lord reſpecting the deepe ſighing of the poore, will awake as one out of ſleepe, and as a Gyant refreſhed with Wine,<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.</note> and will ſmite their enemies in the hinder parts, and put them to a perpetuall ſhame. True it is, and memorable, which <hi>Siracides</hi> hath, chapter 35. where he ſaith; <hi>God hath no reſpect of perſons againſt the poore, but doth heare the prayer of him that is wronged, hee will not neglect the prayer of the fatherleſſe, nor the widdow, if ſhe complaine. Doe not the widdowes teares goe downe her cheekes? and they cry out to God on high in Heauen, againſt him that hath cauſed the ſame?</hi> Now, beloued bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and ſiſters, if wee ſhould wrong an innocent and harmeleſſe man in a righteous cauſe vpon earth, we would be vnwilling,; yea, we would tremble and quake to haue a complaint (we knowing our ſelues guilty) to bee made vnto a mighty Iudge or Potentate that can puniſh vs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely. How much more then ſhould it grieue vs, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſh vs, and cauſe vs to make recompence, and ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the parties whom we haue wronged, when wee know that the complaints and cryes of them that are iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, doe ſound in the eares of the Lord, that an accuſation is made againſt vs, that an account muſt be giuen to the high Iudge, and iuſtice without partialitie miniſtred?</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> the bad Steward is accuſed of his owne thoughts, and teſtified againſt of his owne conſcience: and this is as forcible to conuict a man, as a thouſand wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes: and hereupon grew the prouerbe,<note place="margin">Socrates.</note> 
               <hi>Conſcientia mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le teſtes.</hi> When a mans Conſcience is wronged, hee liueth as merry, as a Bird in a pitfall.<note place="margin">Lib. de moribus.</note> For <hi>Conſcientia laeſa eſt nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecura,</hi> as <hi>Seneca</hi> writeth. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> writing vpon the 50. Pſalme, ſaith, <hi>Conſcientia peccati, formidinis mater:</hi> that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19782:25"/> is to ſay, The Conſcience or knowledge of ſin, is the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of feare. If a man feare any creature, Man, Beaſt, or Worme, he may auoid them; but hee can neuer flee from his Conſcience: ſhe is a bird which hee alwayes carrieth in his boſome, pleaſant as the Nightingale, if ſhee bee not violated; but being wronged, ſhee is like a Waspe, or Snake vnder a mans cloathes, or rather like the Bots in a Horſe belly, which neuer ſuffereth him to be quiet, but are ſtill eating, and gnawing.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sat.</hi> 12.</note> And therefore <hi>Inuenal</hi> ſaid, that this is the greateſt puniſhment, (and we muſt needs all yeeld vnto it.) <hi>Nocte dieque ſuum geſtare in pectore teſtem.</hi> This griefe of Conſcience is an inward tormenting of the ſoule,<note place="margin">Vpon 1. Cor. 11.</note> void of Faith, Hope, and Charitie, which <hi>Melanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thon</hi> calleth <hi>Erinnys Conſcientiae,</hi> that is to ſay, an helliſh Hagge, or infernall Fury of the Conſcience. A wronged Conſcience is neuer quiet, neuer at reſt, but makes her poſſeſſour to flee hither and thither, and ſeeke to depart from her,<note place="margin">Tom. 8. fol. 286.</note> but he cannot. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his enarration of Pſalme 45. ſaith, that he which hath a violated conſcience, will flee, <hi>ab agro, ad cinitatem, à publico, ad domum, à domo, in cubiculum:</hi> that is, he will flee out of field, into the City, out of the Citie, into his houſe, out of his houſe, into his Chamber: and what there? <hi>Ecce hoſtem inuenit, quò fugitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus eſt, nempe ſeipſum:</hi> and there he finds the enemy that he would flee from, to wit, himſelfe. Theſe torments are the moſt grieuous torments.<note place="margin">Ariſtides.</note> And therefore <hi>Lucan</hi> truely (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though mournefully) ſaid of an afflicted conſcience:
<q>Heu quantum miſero poenae mens conſcia donat!</q>
            </p>
            <p>Alas what puniſhment the filly wretch endureth by reaſon of his guilty conſcience!<note place="margin">Eſay 57.21. Act. 24.16.</note> Such a one hath no peace. Let vs therefore with <hi>Paul</hi> endeuour, yea, exerciſe our ſelues to haue alwayes a cleere conſcience towards God, and towards men. Let vs take the counſell that <hi>Paul</hi> gaue to <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1.</note> Fight, that is, earneſtly ſtriue, that we may
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19782:25"/> haue Faith &amp; a good conſcience. For <hi>quaenam ſummae boni? Mens quae ſibi conſcia recti.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 15.15.</note> A good Conſcience is a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall feaſt, the cheere, ioy in the Holy Ghoſt, and the Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke ſuch a peace with God, our neighbours, and our ſelues, as paſſeth all vnderſtanding, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, the very ſinnes which a man committeth, are ſaid in the Booke of God to accuſe, reproue, and condemne him. <hi>Ieremy</hi> in his ſecond Chapter ſaid vnto the Iewes, <hi>Thine owne wickedneſſe ſhall reproue thee, and thy turning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſhall condemne thee.</hi> For as the workes of the godly do follow them, <hi>ad defendendum, &amp; exhilarandum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 14.13.</note> to defend and cheere them: ſo the workes of the wicked do follow them, <hi>ad accuſandum &amp; contriſtandum,</hi> to accuſe, &amp; make them ſad. Among the ſinnes that cry vnto God againſt man, and moſt grieuouſly accuſe him, there are foure dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable ſinnes, as ſome will, but I reduce them to two.<note place="margin">The firſt cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinne.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt is the ſhedding of innocent bloud, the greateſt wrong that can be wrought to humane nature, euen worſe then the taking away of a mans goods; for they may bee reſtored, but mortall life neuer. Beſides this, as much as in the murtherer lyeth, he taketh away from the party killed, all time to diſpoſe and ſet things in order, and alſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, that the man may obtaine remiſsion of his ſinnes. This is not a dormient and ſilent, but a crying ſinne. This ſinne was in <hi>Cain</hi> that bloudy butcher, killing his godly and innocent brother <hi>Abel;</hi> vnto whom God ſaid, <hi>Behold, the voice of thy Brothers bloud cryeth vnto mee out of the ground.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">The ſecond crying ſinne.</note> the oppreſsion of the poore lifting vp their voices vnto God their reuenger, who heareth &amp; helpeth them. As in the 12. Pſalme, ver 5. <hi>At the crying of the poore, I will vp, ſaith the LORD. Siracides</hi> 30. <hi>God hath no reſpect of perſons againſt the poore, but doth heare the prayer of him that is wronged, hee will not neglect the prayer of the fatherleſſe, nor the widdow, if ſhe complaine. Doe not the widdowes teares goe down her cheekes? but they cry out to God
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19782:26"/> on high into Heauen, againſt him that hath cauſed the ſame.</hi> And ſuch a ſinne as this was that ſinne of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action,<note place="margin">Exod. 5.</note> impoſition, and cruell oppreſsion of the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> And very aptly to this purpoſe, may be applyed the crying of hirelings defrauded of their hire by the rich, whereof <hi>Iames</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Chap. 5.7.</note> ſaying, <hi>Behold, the hire of Labourers which haue reaped your fields (which is of you kept back by fraud) cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and the cryes of them which haue reaped, are entred into the eares of the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> And of this ſort, was the cry againſt <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha,</hi> whereof God ſpeaketh, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.21. O beloued, beware of theſe hainous ſinnes, and aſſure your ſelues, that neither theſe, nor other the leaſt ſinnes that we commit, ſhall goe vnpuniſhed, without vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fained repentance, and quicke apprehenſion of the merits of Chriſt Ieſus by a true and liuely faith. And ſo much of the two crying ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, the creatures abuſed not onely the ſenſible crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, groaning and trauelling in paine, till it be deliuered from the bondage of corruption and vanity,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> which againſt it will, it ſuffereth vnder the wicked; but euen the very ſenſeleſſe creature.<note place="margin">Habuc. 2.11. Iam. 5.2.</note> The ſtone crying out of the wall, and the beame out of the timber anſwering it. The moth of the garment, and the ruſt of the cankred gold, witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing againſt the couetous worldlings; yea, the dead letter of the Bible cryeth and accuſeth, as Chriſt ſheweth in the Goſpell.<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.45.</note> 
               <hi>Doe not thinke</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that I will accuſe you to my Father: there is one that accuſeth you, euen</hi> Moſes <hi>in whom yee truſt:</hi> that is, The law or writings of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhall accuſe you, for playing the bad Stewards. To conclude, the heauens ſhall declare his wickedneſſe, and the earch ſhall take part againſt him, as <hi>Zophar</hi> ſaid, <hi>Iob</hi> 20.27. Let vs therefore not deceiue our ſelues, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that our abuſes in our Stewardſhip will not be known to the Lord: for although he knoweth all things already, yet the Scriptures ſpeaking after the manner of men, tell vs that many criminations, and accuſations one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19782:26"/> will come out againſt vs, and be brought before the Lord, ſtirring him to reuengement: And yet alas, how careleſſe man is in this point. He without any care or feare of God, abuſeth his creatures; euen ſenſible and liuing things, that are ſubiect to vanitie, and the touching and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes of him. Man, when hee hurteth any liuing creature, will laugh and reioyce at ſuch times as he is willing to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilarate himſelfe withall, when the creature it ſelfe (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubiect to vanitie, the touching and abuſes of the wicked) doth grone for ſorrow; and man at his pleaſure will kill the ſame. But yet hee conſidereth not, that for theſe his abuſes, and other his wickedneſſes, (if he repent not) hee ſhall himſelfe die eternally. O ſinfull impietie, mercileſſe cruelty, and careleſſe ſecuritie! from the which God deliuer vs. So much concerning the accuſers of the bad Steward.</p>
            <p>The capitall and deadly faults, and haynous crimes, whereof the euill Steward is, and ſhall bee accuſed, are theſe 5.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Infidelitie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Crueltie.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Slothfulneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Ill company-keeping.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. <hi>Waſtfulneſſe.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, vnfaithfulneſſe and falſehood: for whereas faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe is required in the Lords diſpoſers, and they ſhould ſo carry themſelues in their offices, that they may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led faithfull and wiſe:<note place="margin">Math. 24.</note> and ſhould ſo imploy and miniſter the gifts of God, as becommeth good Stewards of the manifold graces of God: To bee briefe, ſhould get their goods truly, and beſtow them in godly affaires,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.</note> and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters bountifully: may not he worthily be accuſed of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie and falſehood, which maketh waſte of his Maſters goods when he is in office and ſeruice: and when he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that he ſhall out, will not ſtudy amendment, nor craue mercy, nor fauour, nor forgiuenes of his faults, but will perſeuer in his naughtineſſe, and ſtudy further to deceiue at the laſt, as this falſe Steward did; which being accuſed,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19782:27"/> and knowing that hee ſhould goe out of his Office, to make vp the full meaſure of deceit, he compareth and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorreth with his Maſters debters and abateth their ſums, to this end, that they might maintaine him when he was put out of his Office?<note place="margin">Valer. Max. l. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Occultum &amp; inſidioſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> malum, eſt haec perfidia,</hi> this treachery is a ſecret and deceitfull euill. Such fellowes ſhew themſelues to be no true members of the Church:<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.2.</note> for euery one that is ſuch, walketh vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and doth the thing that is right, and ſpeaketh the truth from his heart. Such a wicked Steward commeth by ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, but not righteouſly, in the middeſt of his life muſt be leaue them behind him,<note place="margin">Ier. 17.11. Luke 12.</note> and at the laſt be found a very foole: Such a one was the rich man. Nothing croſſeth the Lords loue more then this: <hi>for the righteous Lord lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth righteouſneſſe, his countenance doth behold the iuſt, Pſal.</hi> 11.7.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the euill and naughty Steward is accuſed of crueltie,<note place="margin">Math. 24.49.</note> becauſe hee beateth his fellow-ſeruants, that is, dealeth rigorouſly,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.</note> cruelly, and iniuriouſly with them, as the other ſeruant did to his fellow that ought him an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred pence, and was not able to pay him; and therefore fell down &amp; be ſought him, ſaying: Refraine thine anger towards me, and I wil pay thee all: but the creditor would ſhew no mercy vpon him, but hauing caught him by the throat, ready to thrattle him, caſt him into priſon. O cruell pranke, rather agreeable to the nature of a beaſt (who wil huntch his fellow that is vnder him) the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the humane quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that ſhould be in a man, who ſhould ſuccour &amp; relieue the poore that are next him: and not to be curriſh vnto them like churliſh <hi>Nabal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 25. 1. King. 21.</note> nor cruell like <hi>Ahab,</hi> not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them to haue any thing neere them, nor any way to proſper; but (the more is the pitty) as the high trees drop vpon the low, and hinder their growth: and as the mountaine Radiſh being planted neere the Vine, cauſeth it to ſtarue, and wither away: So the great wicked ones of this world, being too neere the poore godly, make them
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19782:27"/> to decay, and fall away to nothing: for where the hedge is loweſt, the beaſts will breake ouer, and it is vſually ſeene that the great fiſh wil eate vp the ſmall. In the holy Booke of God we find that <hi>Eliah</hi> was fed by Rauens,<note place="margin">1. King. 17. Dan 6.</note> 
               <hi>Daniel</hi> not hurt among hungry Lions, and man indued with reaſon: and who ſhould be led by Gods holy Spirit and his word (a aſſe for pitty) is many times neither charitable, nor mercifull to the poore, but moſt cruell and vnmercifull. So true is that ſaying of <hi>Cyprian</hi> lamenting this caſe:<note place="margin">Serm. de erat. dominic.</note> 
               <hi>O de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtandam humanae malitiae crudelitatem! aues paſcunt, ferae parcunt, homines ſaeuiunt:</hi> that is to ſay, O deteſtable cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, proceeding from the malice of man! birds doe feed men, wild beaſts ſpare men, but men doe rage one vpon another. But what becomes of the wicked, cruell, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly Steward? They conſume ſuddenly, periſh, and come to a fearful end, although for a time they beare neuer ſo faire a ſhew in this world: for as fire made of thornes burneth fiercely for a time, and keepeth a great noiſe and crackling, but yet is ſpeedily burnt out and conſumed: So the attempts of the wicked are for a time violent, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, but God in his good time doth with ſpeed extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh and quench them. This <hi>Dauid</hi> doth proue by his owne experience, who ſpeaking of his cruell aduerſaries,<note place="margin">Pſal. 118.12. Pſal. 68.2.</note> ſaith; <hi>They came about me like Bees, and are extinct, euen as the fire among the Thornes: For in the Name of the Lord I will deſtroy them. And therefore as the ſmoke vaniſheth, and commeth to nothing: ſo the wicked and vngodly periſh at the preſence of God.</hi> So that they hurt themſelues moſt, and therfore are little better then mad men. For as mad men &amp; franticke, are wont to rent and teare themſelues: So wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vngodly men inflict vpon themſelues moſt dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and incurable wounds: yea, they are moſt wilfull mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers of their owne ſoules and bodies, and when they hurt a poore man a little, they moſt wrong themſelues. And ſo the rich Glutton in this Chapter, by his vnmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes &amp; cruelty towards poore <hi>Lazarus,</hi> did hurt himſelfe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19782:28"/> more then he did the poore man: For the poore man went preſently to Heauen, and he to Hell. The cruelty of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> towards the Iſraelites,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> hurt himſelfe and the Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans more then the Iſraelites, as their fearefull end moſt plainely ſhewed, when the Waters ouerwhelmed them in the Red Sea, ſo ſodainly ouertaking and couering them, that no ſignes of true repentance could appeare. The griefe and torments of <hi>Cain</hi> his conſcience,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> his feare and trembling, perfecting his miſeries, with death of the body here, euen an end vnnaturall, and euerlaſting torments af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, muſt needs bee worſe, then the onely vntimely death of the body to <hi>Abel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.19. Heb. 9.27.</note> death being euer certaine, a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery incident to all fleſh. <hi>Adonibezec</hi> was a moſt vile and cruell Tyrant to many: For he cut off the great Toes and Thumbes of ſeuenty Kings,<note place="margin">Iudg. 1.</note> and made them to gather bread vnder his Table: but at the laſt the iudgements of God laid on him were ſuch, that hee was taken, and his owne were cut off, and his owne conſcience made him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his owne worthineſſe of that puniſhment, and to ſay:<note place="margin">Verſe 7.</note> Seuenty Kings hauing the Thumbs of their hands, and of their feet cut off, gathered bread vnder my Table: as I haue done, ſo GOD hath rewarded mee. So they brought him to Ieruſalem, and there he dyed.</p>
            <p>O beloued Chriſtians, ſeeing that cruelty is a thing ſo hurtfull to your ſelues, and others; let me beſeech you that are men of valour, might, and power, euen great and mighty Stewards, to lay aſide the ſame, and all wrath, the cauſe of the ſame,<note place="margin">Lib. de morib.</note> as <hi>Seneca</hi> counſelleth, ſaying: <hi>Eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabis crudelitatem, &amp; miniſtram crudelitatis iram:</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>Auoid cruelty, and anger a ſeruant of cruelty.</hi> And againe, <hi>Reijce crudelitatem, &amp; matrem crudelitatis iram:</hi> that is, <hi>Reiect cruelty, and anger the mother of cruelty. Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiodorus</hi> thinketh that Ambition, Pride, and deſire of Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches make moſt men to be cruell vnto the poore; and hee would haue great men of the world not to bee rigorous vnto the poore. His reaſons are two: Firſt, becauſe poore
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19782:28"/> men haue miſerie and ſorrow inough of themſelues alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. Secondly, rich men reape, by hurting poore men, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther glory nor aboundance of riches.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the euill Steward is accuſed of ſlouthfulneſſe, and long continuance in the ſame, which made him vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing and vnable now to labour: for he plainely ſaid,<note place="margin">Verſe 3.</note> 
               <hi>I cannot digge.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> Such an idle ſeruant was hee that had a talent deliuered vnto him, and neuer made any good vſe of it, but hid it in the ground. Of this vice, all idle perſons that haue good gifts, and vſe them not, are guiltie, and ſo are all they that haue ſtore of worldly riches, and imploy them not to the maintenance of the truth, the aduancement of Gods glory, the good of the Church, Gods faithfull peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and their owne competent maintenance, and their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. Beloued Chriſtians, high and low, rich and poore, young and old, all, one with another, and euery one by himſelfe, giue your ſelues to honeſt and godly exerciſes: for hereof commeth fruit and goodneſſe. <hi>Aurelius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nullus fructus otij, imo magis diſpendium:</hi> There comes no fruit of idleneſſe, but rather loſſe. His example is: <hi>Otioſus</hi> Eſau <hi>amiſit primatus benedictionem, quia maluit cibu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accipere quàm quaerere,</hi> that is, Idle <hi>Eſau</hi> loſt his primary bleſſing, becauſe he had rather receiue meat, then get it by labour. The Diuell hath neuer ſo fit time to ſow the ſeedes of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and miſchiefe, as when men are idle, as appeareth by the Parable, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. where it is ſhewed, that whiles men ſlept, that is, were idle, the Diuell came and ſowed tares among the wheat. The counſell therefore of Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> touching this matter, is very good:<note place="margin">Ad Demet.</note> 
               <hi>Aliquid ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris facito, vt te Diabolus inueniat occupatum. Non enim fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilè capitur à Diabolo, qui bono vacat exercitio:</hi> that is, Doe ſome good worke, that the Diuell may finde thee buſied: for he is not eaſily taken of the Diuell, which is employed in good exerciſe. The Bees teach vs to labour: for no creature is more painfull then they: and if any become drones, and will not labour for hony and maintenance,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19782:29"/> they will draw him out of the hiue, that he may periſh. Beloued, it ſeemeth that theſe ſmall irrationall creatures haue a greater care to puniſh this vice, then many Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, Officers, maſters, and parents. For innumerable loyterers are ſuffered to ſwagger, ſpend, and waſte, they care not how much almoſt in euery towne, yea one ſuch will ſpend more then two or three men of good gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and yet theſe idle drones are ſuffered in many places without controlment of any, to liue euen how they liſt, hatching and breeding by their idleneſſe and ſecure life, many inconueniences, and grieuous ſinnes. For as by the pumpe of a ſhip, water doth oftentimes ſecretly get in and increaſeth, ſo that through the negligence of the Mariner the ſhip is drowned: ſo by ſlouthfulneſſe and a ſecure life, wicked thoughts and concupiſcences are multiplied in our hearts, till at length our ſoules are in great danger.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the euill Steward is accuſed of ill company-keeping, for he eateth and drinketh with the drunken, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.49. If a man were honeſt before, yet the ſociety and fellowſhip of ſuch as are wicked, will hazard his repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and conuerſation, and change his manners from good to euill. For as the Camelion is ſometimes blacke, and ſometimes greene, ſometimes pale, and ſometimes blue, (for he euer taketh his colour of what thing is ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him:) So men of all degrees are wont very much to imitate the nature, diſpoſition, and maners of thoſe, whoſe company they frequent, and whoſe counſell they follow, and whoſe familiaritie they vſe: for with the holy thou ſhalt be holy, and with the froward thou ſhalt learne fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe. Keepe company therefore with the godly, and refraine the ſinfull delectations of the wicked.<note place="margin">Act. 2.</note> Saue your ſelues from this froward generation. Come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them:<note place="margin">Eſa. 52.11.</note> depart ye, depart ye, goe out from them, and touch no vncleane thing, for if ye do, ye will be infected, For if one ſhabed and ſcabbed ſheepe will infect a whole flocke, then what will daily feeding and folding with
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19782:29"/> many doe? Take the good counſell of <hi>Salomon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 4.14, 15, 16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Enter not into the way of the wicked, and walke not in the way of euill men: Auoid it, and goe not by it: turne from it, and paſſe by. For they cannot ſleepe, except they haue done euill, and their ſleepe departeth, except they cauſe ſome to fall. For they eate the bread of wickedneſſe, and drinke the wine of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</hi> Goe not therefore the broad way with the wicked which leadeth to deſtruction: Faſhion not your ſelues like to the world, the wicked ones of the world, for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell is their Prince, and tyrannically ruleth them: Hee is their god and Maſter, and badly payeth them their wages. Death and deſtruction is their paiment, which in the end of their ſeruice they receiue from him. O keepe not company then with the wicked (vnleſſe your deſires and endeuours are to conuert them) but as occaſion and opportunitie ſhall ſerue, delight the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the godly. And this Saint <hi>Peter</hi> would haue vs to doe, ſaying; <hi>Loue brotherly fellowſhip:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Epiſt. 2, 17. Heb. 10.25.</note> And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> agreeth hereunto, exhorting vs not to forſake the fellowſhip that wee haue among our ſelues. For to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the company of the good, is hurtfull, as it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the example of <hi>Iudas,</hi> who forſooke the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Apoſtles and periſhed: and of <hi>Thomas,</hi> who was not with the other ten Apoſtles, when Chriſt appeared to them after his Reſurrection: and therefore ſeeing him not with the reſt, doubted.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point: As a Bird leauing her neſt and Egges, neuer hatcheth her yong ones: but the Eggs rot, and the fruit muſt needs periſh: Euen ſo, euery one which forſaketh his firſt loue, leaueth the way of truth, departeth from the ſocietie of the good, remaineth not in the vnity of the Church, but goeth in the way of <hi>Cain:</hi> euen this man with the froward, becommeth froward, is corrupted in the errour of <hi>Balaam,</hi> becommeth abominable in his ſtudies, and periſheth in the gaine-ſaying of <hi>Corah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Laſt of all, the bad Steward is accuſed of waſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19782:30"/> 
               <hi>quòd diſſiparet bona ipſius.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Helm.</note> A Learned man wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon this place, hath theſe words: <hi>Diſsipare, hoc loco eſt, non ad honorem Dei &amp; vtilitatem ſuam, &amp; proximorum, vti rebus conceſsis, ſed ad profanos, malos, &amp; odibiles vſus eas detorquere.</hi> To waſte or to ſcatter abroad (for ſo the word doth properly ſignifie) is not to vſe things granted to the honour of God, to a mans owne profit, and his neighbours: but to wreſt them to prophane, euill, and deteſtable vſes.<note place="margin">Luke 15.</note> The Prodigall Sonne was ſuch a Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: for he craued his portion of goods which belonged to him, and got it of his Father: and not many dayes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when he had gathered all that he could together, hee tooke his iourney into a farre Country, &amp; there he waſted his goods with ryotous liuing. Euery man that hath good gifts giuen him of God, and doth miſ-imploy them, is guilty of this ſinne of waſtefulneſſe. And ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the hainous crimes whereof the bad Steward is accuſed.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the ſecond Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:19782:30"/>
            <head>THE THIRD SERMON.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow next, of his calling, in theſe words: <hi>And he called him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God may bee ſaid to call a man many wayes.</p>
            <p>Sometimes he louingly inuiteth, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticeth, and calleth vs vnto him by his benefits, ſhewing himſelfe very boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull vnto vs, and patient; to draw vs hereby, (as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth his Child, with an Apple,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note> or ſome pleaſing thing) to repentance. And thus kindely God dealt with the Iewes:<note place="margin">Ier. 5.</note> but all the Lords louing kindneſſes towards them were loſt, the people were ſo vnthankefull. Againe, the Iſraelites were thus called, and inuited. For they had <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> to declare the Law of God vnto them, to guide them, and which by prayers put away all hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things from them, and by the ſame obtained all neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie things for them, euen Manna from Heauen: but they like wanton and vndutifull children, abuſed the goodneſſe and lenitie of God towards them. And thus the Lord cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth and inuiteth vs. For what ſingular bleſſings hath the Lord beſtowed vpon vs, not onely common and generall to all his people: as our Election, Redemption, Vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Iuſtification, and other ſpirituall and perfect good
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19782:31"/> things; but priuate alſo, which other Nations want. For wee haue a moſt gracious, learned, godly, and vertuous King, peace and all other good things vnder him, which other Nations doe lacke. For which the Lord make vs thankefull.</p>
            <p>God calleth man by caſtigations, and the Rod of correction,<note place="margin">Reu. 3.19. &amp; Heb. 12.</note> which are arguments of Gods loue to his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and proceed from it. The Lord ſaith, <hi>Whom I loue, I correct.</hi> And againe, <hi>My ſonne, deſpiſe not thou the chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Lord, neither faint when thou art rebuked of him. For whom the Lord loueth he chaſtneth, and he ſcourgeth euery ſonne that he receiueth.</hi> Afflictions are the rod which our louing Father taketh in his hand, and wherewith he whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his children round, to make them repent, and obey his calling: and this may be a great comfort to Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that their heauineſſe and afflictions are but ſhort, they haue a proſperous iſſue, a ſpeedy deliuerance: for heauineſſe endureth for a night, and ioy commeth in the morning. As after ſtormes and tempeſts comes ſunne-ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning weather: and after a bloudy and red euen, a faire bright morning: Euen ſo, after momentanie afflictions pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently endured, the Children of God ſhall haue a farre more excellent and an eternall waight of glory.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.17.</note> Hereby the Children of God are bettered in this life. For as iron is more bright, when the ruſt is ſcowred from it: Wheat more pure, when the Chaffe is blowne from it, and the Weeds ſifted out: and Gold when it is tryed in the fire is more precious; So are the Children of God when they are tryed in the fiery furnace of afflictions, and found faithfull. This makes them to repent, to ſeeke vnto God, to pray vnto him, to hope for deliuerance from him: and to end, as it were in a word, is the plaine high way to Heauen.<note place="margin">Act. 14.22.</note> For through many tribulations wee muſt enter into the Kingdome of Heauen. Wherefore (all yee that ſuffer in a good cauſe) take the comfortable exhortation of Saint <hi>Iames:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 1.2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>My brethren, count it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19782:31"/> ioy, when yee fall into diuers tentations: knowing, that the trying of your Faith, bringeth forth patience; and let patience haue her perfect worke, that yee may bee perfect, and entire, lacking nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God calleth man by his Word: and this calling is two-fold:
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Generall.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Speciall.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>The Generall calling, is an inuitation and bidding of all good and bad, tagge and ragge, to come from the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Satan, ſinne and darkneſſe, to the Kingdome of Chriſt, of grace, and light, executed by the outward prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and reading of the Word. For God which is rich in mercy, and would haue all men to be ſaued,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.4.</note> and to come to the knowledge of his Truth, vouchſafeth his meanes to all, would haue his Goſpel to be preached to all,<note place="margin">Math. 28.</note> that all might beleeue, yeeld their obedience, and bee ſaued: or elſe, wilfully contemning their calling, be left inexcuſable. This we may ſee to be true, by his bountifull feaſt, and the liberall inuitation which he made, and appointed, <hi>Luk</hi> 14. This is, and hath been euen from the beginning the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Lords Kingdome. Thus God called <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> ſaying; <hi>Adam, Where art thou?</hi> Thus hee called the people in <hi>Noah</hi> his time, by <hi>Noah</hi> himſelfe: and ſo the people in the Prophets time, by the Prophets themſelues. So he called them in the New Teſtament by <hi>Iohn Baptiſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3. Math. 11.</note> Yea, Chriſt himſelfe ſo called, ſaying: <hi>Come vnto me, all ye that trauell, and are heauy laden, &amp;c.</hi> And hee commanded the Apoſtles ſo to doe, giuing them their meſſage, ſaying: <hi>Goe ye, and teach all Nations, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 28.19, 20. Mar. 16.</note> And now Miniſters doe it, yea, and ſhall doe it in Chriſts ſtead, to the end of the world.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.20.</note> Now then (ſaith the Apoſtle) are wee Meſſengers for Chriſt; euen as though God did beſeech you through vs; ſo pray we you in Chriſts ſtead, that yee be reconciled vnto God.</p>
            <p>But (alas) this generall Calling, this bountifull offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19782:32"/> of Grace, takes no place among the wicked, moues their hearts nothing at all. For although their ſoules are almoſt famiſhed, and they are euen ſicke vnto death: yet they refuſe all Phyſicke, and reliefe: and therefore are left inexcuſable,<note place="margin">Muſc.</note> and worthily periſh. <hi>Meritò perit aegrotus, qui medicum non ſolùm, non vocat, ſed vltrò venientem recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſat,</hi> that is, the ſicke man worthily periſheth, which not onely refuſeth to call a Phyſician, but when hee is come, repelleth him. Some being called, ſay, as the rebellious Iewes ſaid:<note place="margin">Ier. 44.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>The word that thou haſt ſpoken vnto vs in the Name of the Lord, we will not heare it of thee: But wee will doe whatſoeuer thing goeth out of our owne mouth, as to burne incenſe to the Queene of Heauen, &amp;c.</hi> Others are perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of them that call them: as they that were bidden to the great wedding, who tooke the Kings ſeruants, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated them ſharpely,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.6.</note> and ſlue them. Such a one was <hi>Herod</hi> to <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 14.</note> who could not abide him, calling him from his filthy inceſtuous ſinne with <hi>Herodias</hi> his brother <hi>Philips</hi> Wife:<note place="margin">Mark. 6.</note> but as ſoone as he was reprooued, tooke a light occaſion, inſtigated by the curtizan, to put him to death. But now (God be thanked) the Lawes are ſo well eſtabliſhed, and executed, that no man dareth to lay violent hands vpon his Miniſter; but yet the wicked will hurt him with their ſlanderous tongue many times, and keepe his dues from him, ſometimes priuily, that hee ſhall not know it: And if hee doth know it, then many times they will plead a cuſtome, their cuſtome to deceiue: yea, they will ſay, Our cuſtome is an ancient cuſtome. Whereas, <hi>Mala conſuetudo eſt erroris vetuſtas:</hi> that is, <hi>An euill cuſtome is the antiquity of an errour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some when they are called, are ſomewhat more For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall, Morall, and mannerly, then the former were. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they are meere Worldlings, and preferre earthly things, before heauenly; yet they couer their affections, and make comely excuſes, and reaſonable, as they thinke, and will ſay, when they are abſent from a Sermon, Wee
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19782:32"/> were hindred by ſuch and ſuch meanes that wee could not be at it; very like to them that were bidden to the great Supper, and made ſeuerall excuſes: One ſaid,<note place="margin">Luke 14.</note> I haue bought a Farme, and I goe to ſee it: Another ſaid, I haue bought fiue yoke of Oxen, and I goe to proue them: and the third ſaid, I haue married a Wife, and therefore I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not come. But none of theſe excuſes pleaſed the Lord, the maker of the Feaſt. For hee being angry with theſe, ſaid, None of theſe ſhall taſte of my Supper, of my ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and heauenly diſh-meates, and of my coſtly banquet. What greater ingratitude and churliſhneſſe could any ſhew? Nay, what greater ſottiſhneſſe can the whole world bewray, then to preferre Chaffe, before pure Wheat; ruſt, before Iron; Lead, before Siluer, Copper, before pure Gold; earthly and fraile things, before heauenly, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall good things? And yet ſo fooliſh are we, and ignorant; yea, ſo void of diſcretion, and piety, that we will ſtill pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and alledge one cauſe or another to hinder our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, when we are called, thinking that we thereby help our ſelues, when we moſt of all hurt our owne ſoules. We pretend lets, as that man did, who when our Sauiour cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him, ſaid: <hi>Suffer me firſt to goe and bury my Father:</hi> and we are worſe then hee that would goe and bid them that were of his houſhold, <hi>Farewell,</hi> and then reſolued to come. For many neuer reſolue to obey their calling at any time, but ſtand backe with wily ſhifts, good for nothing but to beguile themſelues. So truely ſpake Chriſt. <hi>No man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to me</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>vnleſſe the Father draw him.</hi> Marke the word, <hi>(draw)</hi> as though a man were holden backe of ſome Tyrant (as of Satan:) or were of himſelfe ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to come, that he muſt be drawne and haled along. Let vs make excuſes no longer, but pray vnto God to giue vs both to will, and power to performe:<note place="margin">Phil. 2.</note> for in him it is to performe both.</p>
            <p>The ſpeciall and effectuall calling (a benefit proper to Gods Children,) hath euer election going before it (for
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19782:33"/> it is the firſt fruit of it, and comes next from it) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Paul</hi> ſets our falling next to predeſtination.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.30.</note> This ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and effectuall calling takes place onely in them that are elect, when as God doth by the preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, call vs out of the kingdome of Satan and ſinne, and (as it were) out of this world of wickedneſſes, to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt, of grace, and of light, to be of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his children, to be ſheepe of his fold. And here we are to note, that God doth not call vs all at one time, but at ſundry times, as it ſhall pleaſe him to diſpenſe his grace vnto vs, as we may ſee by his ſending of labourers at ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall houres into his Vineyard.<note place="margin">Mat. 20.</note> Some are ſanctified in their mothers wombe, and ſpeedily called and ſent to their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.</note> as <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> in his youth, <hi>Peter</hi> when hee was of ripe age, <hi>Paul</hi> ſomewhat late, and the theefe when he was readie to be crucified. Before the time of their calling they wander in the vaſt ſolitude and wilderneſſe of this world, nothing differing from other men in outward ſhape, but in qualities and maners, and they being Chriſts ſheepe are ſo ſaued and guided by him, that they cannot bee taken from him,<note place="margin">Ioh. 10.</note> neither runne into the pit of deſtruction. This effectuall calling is wrought by the preaching of the Word, and by theſe three meanes:</p>
            <p>Firſt, God openeth and prepareth the eares, which are the mouthes of the ſoule: the bodie hath but one mouth to receiue corporall nutriment, to ſuſtaine it, but the ſoule being the better part of man, hath two mouths, (I meane, his two eares) to receiue in food for it, which God ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to that purpoſe: as <hi>Dauid</hi> doth teach vs by his owne example,<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.</note> ſaying, <hi>Sacrifice and offerings thou didſt not deſire, for mine eares haſt thou prepared.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, attendance is giuen to that which is prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and taught: for he that hath cares to heare, is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to heare.<note place="margin">Mat. 13. Reuel 2. Eſa. 55.3.</note> And the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> craueth and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth for this attendance, ſaying, <hi>Encline your eares, and draw neere, heare, and your ſoules ſhall liue.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:19782:33"/>
            <p>Thirdly, there followeth this preaching, eares ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and good attendance giuen, a wonderfull compun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and pricking of the heart, as it may appeare by the example of thoſe people that heard the Sermon of <hi>Peter,</hi> who ſaid vnto <hi>Peter</hi> and the other Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Act. 2.37.</note> 
               <hi>Men and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, What ſhall we doe?</hi> Well, <hi>Peter</hi> followed them ſo earneſtly (when he ſaw them comming) with good do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine and exhortation, that he did win them, and there was added to the Church about three thouſand ſoules. But (beloued) note this, that there is euer much adoe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that the Law, compared to an hammer, can breake the knottie affections of the heart, and ſo currie and make the ground of mans heart fit to receiue the ſeede of the Goſpel, and there plant faith that may purifie it.<note place="margin">Acts 15.9.</note> But here (perhaps) ſome may deſire to know, by what characters, markes, and ſignes a man may aſſure his ſoule, that hee is predeſtinated to eternall life, that he may take comfort by this doctrine. For reſolution, marke this, which I haue penned for thy good. If thou ſeeſt thy ſinnes, and percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt Gods wrath and anger ready to fall on thee for them, diſlikeſt them, art grieued for them, bewaileſt them, and heartily craueſt pardon for them, and beginneſt to become a new man, continueſt with increaſe in the faith of Ieſus Chriſt, and doeſt ſeeke after the kingdome of God, then no doubt thou art elected, and effectually called. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer, if thou art readie, as it were, with an Eccho, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to euery thing that the Spirit of God ſhall endite, and the Preacher ſhall ſpeake truly out of Gods Booke, then thou art effectually called. Looke to <hi>Dauids</hi> exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 40.<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.</note> In the volume (or rolle) of thy booke, it is written of me, that I ſhould doe thy will, O my God: I am content to doe it, or, I am delighted with it, yea thy Law is in my heart. Againe, God ſaid to <hi>Dauid, Seeke ye my face: Dauids</hi> ſpirit, heart and ſoule did anſwere, <hi>Thy face, Lord, will I ſeeke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many goe to the Church to auoide the danger of the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19782:34"/> Lawes, that they may not be preſented to the ſpirituall courts, or come into the danger of the temporall Lawes, or be noted of their neighbours to be houſe-lurdins at home: but not moued with religion, pietie, or any good deuotion, to pray, or any godly preparation to receiue the holy Communion. O careleſſe ſecuritie, and blind impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie! from the which the Lord deliuer vs. I feare much, that there are many temporizers, that goe to the Church to free themſelues from the danger of the Lawes, or for company ſake. Theſe men are ſo farre from their effectuall calling, as the Eaſt is from the Weſt. For euery one that is but in the way to this, carrieth this reſolution, that whatſoeuer he heareth truly taught out of Gods Booke, he will follow.<note place="margin">Iam. 1.</note> He will not be an idle hearer, but a doer of the Word. He will walke after the Lord, keepe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, as much as in him lieth, and his Statutes with all his heart, as the people conſented to do, that heard <hi>Ioſias</hi> the king reade the Lawe vnto them.<note place="margin">2. Kings 23. 2. Chron. 34.</note> This good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution did the people make, which when <hi>Moſes</hi> had told them all the words of the Lord, ſaid: <hi>All the things which the Lord hath ſaid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 14.</note> 
               <hi>will we doe.</hi> And ſo ought euery man and woman be reſolued: In which good reſolution, O God, ſettle vs all for thy mercies ſake. But here it may be (O Chriſtian Reader) that you deſire to know, what maner of calling this Steward had, which was ſo grieuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accuſed to his Maſter. To this I anſwere: His calling was neither of the former, but fearefull, and very diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate, a ſudden, and vnexpected calling to reckoning after manifeſt crimes, and falſe dealings againſt his Maſter; and vpon the ſame an account taken, and he found faultie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion, and finall departure from his office for euer fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. This Stewards Maſter dealt with him after the order and faſhion of great men in this world, which when they find their ſeruants vniuſt, will preſently call them to account, and ſet them packing. This is a great loſſe to poore ſeruants, that haue nothing but their ſeruice to truſt
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19782:34"/> vnto. But this Stewards loſſe went beyond all common ſeruants loſſes: for it was of ſeruice, goods, life preſent, and the life to come: from all which wicked men depart, as the rich man, <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. and the rich Glutton, <hi>Luk</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>Thus much of his calling. Next, of his reprehenſion or increpation, in theſe words:
<q>How commeth it to paſſe, that I heare this of thee?</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words giue ſingular inſtructions to all ſorts of people, taken
<list>
                  <item>literally and plainely, or</item>
                  <item>Allegorically.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>If you take them plainely, as the words are, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand by the rich man, any Magiſtrate whatſoeuer: and by the Steward or ſeruant, the ſubiect: Or by the rich man, any great Maſter; and by the ſeruant, them that ſerue in his houſe. They giue foure inſtructions and informations to theſe great men of authoritie.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that they may not couer ſinnes and enormious offences, but ought to reproue and correct them, neither ſpare the rod, and ſword, and deale too gently, like old <hi>Eli,</hi> when faults are committed.<note place="margin">1. Kings 2. Rom. 13. 1. Pet. 2.14.</note> For Magiſtrates are ſet ouer the people, for the puniſhment of euill doers, and for the praiſe of them that doe well.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they ought to enquire out the truth of the ſame, and examine the matter diligently. Which thing we are taught by the example of the beſt, euen God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, concerning the cry, and exceeding grieuous ſinne of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha:</hi> for thus the Lord ſaid,<note place="margin">Gen. 18.21.</note> 
               <hi>I will go down now, and ſee whether they haue done altogether according to that cry which is come vnto me; and if not, that I may know.</hi> This <hi>Iob</hi> reported that he did:<note place="margin">Iob 29.16.</note> 
               <hi>I was a father</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the poore, and when I knew not the cauſe, I ſought it out di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the accuſers of the true bringers of the newes,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19782:35"/> (when the truth is knowne) are not alwaies to be diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and vttered to them that are accuſed, for feare of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention and debate. For here he ſaith not: This man or that man told me: but he ſpake indefinitely, ſaying, <hi>How commeth it to paſſe, that I heare this of thee?</hi> He would not ſet the fellow ſeruants together by the eares, but would maintaine charitie, the bond of all perfection, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.14.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, he diſcloſeth not openly to others, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall point whereof the Steward was accuſed, to cauſe murmuring, but calleth him, vnto him priuily, and telleth him priuately of the euill report that went of him, ſaying, <hi>How commeth it to paſſe that I heare this of thee?</hi> following the ſweet, charitable, and wholeſome counſel and aduice of our Sauiour,<note place="margin">Mat. 18.15.</note> teaching vs thus: <hi>If thy brother treſpaſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee, goe and tell him his fault betweene thee and him alone: if he heare thee, thou haſt wonne thy brother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How commeth it to paſſe that I heare this of thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words (as I ſaid before) being taken allegorical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, containing <hi>aliud verbis, aliud ſenſu,</hi> ſpeaking of a rich man, and yet meaning God; and ſpeaking of a rich mans Steward, and yet vnderſtanding all mankind, a large col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectiue or Nowne of multitude, doe giue vs to note two things worthy all godly mens conſiderations:</p>
            <p>Firſt, that our faults are not hid from the Lord.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the Lord is diſpleaſed with them.</p>
            <p>Mans faults are not hid from the Lord: but although man worketh them neuer ſo ſecretly and cloſely, which wicked men ſtill affect, (for which cauſe their workes are called the workes of darkneſſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> becauſe they proceed from the darkneſſe of mans vnderſtanding, are done in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and leade men to extreme darkeneſſe) yet all are knowne of the omniſcient God, the all-ſeeing God, the ſearcher of the heart and reines, who is <hi>totus animi, totus animae,</hi> knowing, ſeeing, and foreſeeing all things. Which
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19782:35"/> thing who will be ſo mad as to deny? ſeeing that the Pſalmograph truly and reuerendly telleth God ſo, ſaying, <hi>O Lord, thou haſt ſearched me out and knowne me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 139.</note> 
               <hi>thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt my downe-ſitting and mine vpriſing, thou vnderſtandeſt my thoughts long before,</hi> and that is moſt of all. He holdeth on in his ſpeech, and ſpeaketh further, ſaying, <hi>Thou art about my path, and about my bed, and ſpéeſt out all my wayes.</hi> He ſeeth euery thing that is done on the face of the earth: For his eyes are like a flame of fire,<note place="margin">Reuel. 1. Pſal. 121. Pſal. 142.</note> they are moſt cleare and bright, and neuer ſleepe. <hi>Hee looketh downe vpon the children of men, to ſee if there were any that would vnderſtand and ſeeke after God.</hi> He ſeeth both good and euill: for as <hi>Dauid</hi> hath, <hi>The eyes of the Lord are ouer the righteous, and his eares are open vnto their prayers.</hi> Againe,<note place="margin">Pſal. 34.15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>The face of the Lord is againſt them that doe euill, to cut off their remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance from off the earth.</hi> And this we may perſwade our ſelues to be true, becauſe he is the onely true Vbiquitarie, preſent euery where with his Spirit, and from whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence no man can flie. And therefore the Pſalmiſt by way of interrogation ſpeaketh thus vnto God:<note place="margin">Pſal. 139.</note> 
               <hi>Whither ſhall I goe then from thy Spirit? or whither ſhall I goe then from thy preſence? If I climbe vp into heauen, thou art there; if I goe downe to hell, thou art there alſo: If I take the wings of the morning, and remaine in the vttermoſt parts of the ſea, euen there alſo ſhall thine hand leade me, and thy right hand ſhall hold me. If I ſay, peraduenture the darkneſſe ſhall couer mee, then ſhall my night be turned to day, yea the darkeneſſe is no darkneſſe with thee, but the night is as cleare as the day; the darkneſſe and light to thee are both alike.</hi> No man then can hide himſelfe from the Lord, no place is fit:<note place="margin">Amos 2.</note> 
               <hi>For though they digge downe to hell, ſaith the Lord, thence ſhall my hand take them; though they climbe vp to the heauens, thence will I bring them downe; though they hide themſelues in the top of Carmel, I will ſearch them, and take them out thence; though they be hid from my ſight in the bottome of the ſea, thence will I command the ſerpent, and he ſhall bite them.</hi> The wicked
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19782:36"/> Steward cannot then flee from the Lord, his cauſe muſt come to the hearing of his Maſter, he muſt endure ſharpe reprehenſion, ſtrict examination, and come to an account, as after. If the vniuſt Steward, the euill man, the theefe, adulterer, and ſuch like offenders, were perſwaded that God did heare of their miſdemeanors, and euill carriages, or that he did looke vpon them, when they perpetrated their wickedneſſes, me thinkes it ſhould be a great terrour and ſhame vnto them. If an earthly Prince, a Noble man, a Maſter, or a Magiſtrate ſhould looke vpon a man, and ſee him deale falſely and vniuſtly, or otherwiſe to play the filthy adulterer, would it not make man to tremble, feare, and to be aſhamed? How much more then to conſider, that the King of kings, and Lord of lords, the high Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Magiſtrate and Iudge of all doth heare of his ſinnes, and looke vpon his ſinfull and filthie facts. Let vs all bee aſhamed to commit ſinne,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 16.</note> and not be like <hi>Abſolom,</hi> who ſhamed not to lie with his fathers concubines in the open Sunne, in the top of the houſe, euen in the ſight of all Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael: for the Lord heareth, ſeeth, and knoweth all the ſins of man. This wicked Steward before he was accuſed, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and reprehended, and brought to account, was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the Lord had not intelligence of his falſhood: but how much was he deceiued? For here the Lord ſaith, <hi>How commeth it to paſſe that I heare this of thee?</hi> There are three fooliſh and vaine conceits ſuggeſted of Satan, which embolden a wicked man in the perpetration of his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſes:
<list>
                  <item>1. They thinke that the Lord neither ſeeth, nor knoweth their wickedneſſes.</item>
                  <item>2. Hee puniſheth not ſtraight, but either delayeth long, or puniſheth not at all.</item>
                  <item>3. If the Lord knoweth mans faults, yet he concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them, &amp;c.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt vaine conceit, concerning the Lords not ſeeing, and not knowing their ſinnes, how fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19782:36"/> and impious it is, this place doth proue: for here the Lord ſaith, <hi>How commeth it to paſſe that I heare this of thee?</hi> The Maſter therefore heard it, and had notice of all. Although (I hope) that I haue ſpoken ſufficiently of this point, yet I beſeech you hearken to two examples, to ground you throughly in this point. The firſt is, of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> which committed adulterie and murther,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 11.</note> and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Lord ſaw it, knew it, and it was euill in his ſight, and ſent <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet to reproue him,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.</note> who boldly layd his great ſinnes to his charge. The ſecond example, of <hi>Ahab</hi> that vile king of Iſrael, and <hi>Iezabel</hi> his queene,<note place="margin">1. Kings 21.</note> worſe then himſelfe, an inſtigatrix of his euils: (as <hi>Eua</hi> was to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi>) when they had wrought poore <hi>Naboths</hi> death, the Lord knew it, and ſent <hi>Elias</hi> to rebuke him. To end this point in a word:<note place="margin">Apoc. 2. &amp; 3. chapt.</note> The Lord did bid <hi>Iohn</hi> write to the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, that is to ſay, the Miniſters of the ſeuen Churches: <hi>I know thy workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond vaine conceit ſuggeſted of Satan, is, The Lord puniſheth not ſtraight, nor preſently, but ſuffereth the vngodly Steward to flouriſh. To which I anſwere: That the pleaſures of the wicked beeing taken with euill conſciences, neither are, nor can be durable; they flouriſh but for a time, and in the middeſt of them are taken away. <hi>Dauid,</hi> a man after Gods owne heart,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.</note> ſaw that by his owne experience, and therefore ſaid, <hi>I my ſelfe haue ſeene the vngodly in great proſperity, and flouriſhing like a greene bay tree, and I went by, and loe, he was gone, I ſought him, and his place could no where be found. Therefore fret not thy ſelfe becauſe of the vngodly, neither be thou enuious againſt the euil doers: for he ſhall ſoone be cut downe like the greene graſſe, and be withered like the greene herbe. For the Lord doth ſet them in ſlippery places, and at laſt caſteth them downe to deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, ſuddenly doe they conſume, periſh, and come to a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full end.</hi> What plainer example, to this purpoſe,<note place="margin">Luke 12.</note> can bee produced, then that of the rich man, who in the middeſt of his proſperitie and worldly pleaſures, heard this dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19782:37"/> voice: <hi>Thou foole, this night will they fetch away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee thy ſoule: then whoſe ſhall thoſe things be which thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided?</hi> So that, whereas they haue been fed fat in the great and large greene paſtures of pleaſures, waſting their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters goods, as this bad Steward did, yet all endeth in ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, euen as the fat Oxe, after his pleaſant feeding, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to the ſlaughter; and the end of theſe is confuſion. For euen as a Snayle by little and a little, creepeth vp from the root of an Hearbe, vnto the top, and as ſhe goeth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumeth the Leaues, and leaueth her nothing but foule and filthy ſlimy ſteps: ſo likewiſe luſt and pleaſure, if wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto them, will creepe into our ſoules, and will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue them of all ornaments of vertue, and will leaue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde nothing, but a foule filthy conſcience, &amp; reproach, to vs and our poſteritie.</p>
            <p>The third vaine conceit, ſuggeſted of Satan, is the Lords taciturnitie. For although he knoweth euery ſinne, when the world doth not; yet for a time hee holdeth his peace, and it commeth not out to the eyes of the world. The impure perſon ſinneth, and ſo doth the Theefe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offenders; the Lord heareth of it, and ſeeth it, and yet for a time (it may be) neither ſpeaketh, nor puniſheth. But this ſilence is temporarie. And therefore the Pſalmiſt true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid, <hi>Our Lord will come, and will not keep ſilence.</hi> And the time alſo will come, that euery mans worke ſhall be made manifeſt.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3. 1. Cor. 4. 1. Tim. 3.</note> And the Lord will lighten the hidden things of darkneſſe, and open the counſels of the heart, and then the madnes of the wicked ſhall be manifeſted to all men. This doctrine teacheth vs, that the time will come, when all things ſhall be made knowne: although Satan, in the meane time, worke neuer ſo cunningly, to deceiue men; and ſets counterfet colours, and falſe ſhewes vpon euery ſinfull action of man, being more skilfull herein, then any Dyer is, in ſetting colours vpon his cloth. For wee haue but few Dyers that can ſet any Dye or colour vpon a cloth, and pleaſe the owner in the colour that he hath moſt
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19782:37"/> minde vnto: the Diuell can doe it in ſuggeſting ſinne to a wicked man. Firſt, he plu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, ſoundeth, &amp; findeth mans nature, vnto what ſinne he is moſt inclined, and offereth the ſame ſinne vnto man, and then he ſets another colour vpon the ſame ſinne. As for example, if a man is inclined to adultery and vncleanneſſe, hee calleth the ſame, touches and prankes incident to youth; and couetouſneſſe, he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth honeſt prouiſion for a mans ſelfe and his. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, <hi>Diabolus, quando decipere quenquam quaerit, priùs na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam vniuſcuiuſque intendit, &amp; inde applicat, vnde aptum hominem ad peccandum inſpexerit:</hi> that is, <hi>When the Diuell goeth about to deceiue any man, firſt he findeth out his nature, and then miniſtreth vnto him that ſinne, whereunto he findes him moſt inclined.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3.5, 6.</note> When the Diuell went about to deceiue our firſt Parents, he told them that they ſhould be as gods, knowing but good and euill, pretending friendſhip vnto them, and offering a pleaſant fruit withall.<note place="margin">2. Sam. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued with his pleaſing ſinne, wantonneſſe: <hi>Ahab</hi> vvith couetouſneſſe: <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his heart hee hardened with lying words: The Heathens with vniuerſalities, and antiquities. To conclude, no ſhifts, no crafts, no deceits, but they are knowne vnto him, and put in practice by him, and in the cunningeſt faſhion that may be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How commeth it to paſſe that I heare this of thee?</hi> Theſe words, as I ſaid, doe alſo teach that the Lord is diſpleaſed with the ſinnes of a bad Steward, a wicked and ſinfull man. For they ſecretly, and openly doe include and carry a kinde of reprehenſion, and increpation, as though hee ſhould ſay, Why haſt thou dealt falſely in thy Steward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and gotten thee ſo ill a report? Thou are worthy to be blamed for thy perfidiouſneſſe and treacherie. The conſideration whereof, ſhould make vs to flee from ſinne and wickednes, as from the ſting and poiſon of a Serpent. For who would perpetrate &amp; commit thoſe things which diſpleaſe his Lord and Maſter: The Pſalmograph ſaith, <hi>The Lord doth abhorre both the bloud-thirsty and deceitfull
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19782:38"/> man.</hi> Againe hee ſaith: <hi>I hate the ſinnes of vnfaithfulneſſe, there ſhall no ſuch cleaue vnto me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe foure things may perſwade vs that God moſt perfectly hateth ſinne, and all manner of naughti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Comminations and threatnings in the Scriptures.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Sinne breaketh friendſhip between God and Man.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>God neuer made ſinne, hee neuer procured it, he deſireth it not, nor alloweth it.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>The Lords puniſhments inflicted vpon ſinners.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>As touching the firſt, the Lords threatnings and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations: wee may eaſily perſwade our ſelues that God deteſteth ſinne; becauſe he ſo horribly, and fearfully thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth out moſt dreadfull ſentences againſt ſinners, ſuch as theſe.<note place="margin">Mat. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>Now alſo is the Axe put to the roote of the Trees:</hi> therefore <hi>Euery Tree which bringeth not forth good fruit, is hewne downe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 8.4.</note> 
               <hi>and caſt into the fire:</hi> Againe, <hi>The ſoule that ſinneth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom 6. Rom. 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall dye the death.</hi> And that ſaying of <hi>Paul. The reward of ſinne, is death. Tribulation and anguiſh ſhall bee vpon the ſoule of euery one that doth euill.</hi> All which, and many other ſuch terrible ſayings are true, and in force, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all impenitent faithleſſe perſons.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſinne breaketh friendſhip betweene God and Man: and therefore muſt needs be moſt diſpleaſing vnto God. If two are deare friends, and loue one another en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely, and are loth to liue at variance: If theſe fall at vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, then we make no doubt but that, that which break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth friendſhip, is moſt diſpleaſing vnto him, which forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his old friend. Now God is moſt louing, kinde, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, and mercifull vnto man, till ſinne doth domineere and raigne in his body, and then man breaking, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherouſly dealing, ſinning, and offending his God, there is a preſent ſeparation,<note place="margin">Eſai. 59.1, 2, 3.</note> as <hi>Eſay</hi> doth teſtifie. <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19782:38"/> he, <hi>the hand of the Lord is not ſo ſhortned, but that it can ſaue, nor his eare ſo dull, but that it can heare: But your iniquities doe make a ſeparation betweene you and your God; and your ſinnes doe make him to hide his face from you, and not heare; for your hands are defiled with bloud, and your fingers with cruelty; your lips do ſpeake that which is falſe, and your tongue doth ſpeake frowardneſſe.</hi> Note, I beſeech you, the cauſe of the breach of friendſhip, and falling out betweene God and the people: <hi>Their ſinnes, their iniquities.</hi> This is alſo proued by thoſe ſpeeches that <hi>Samuel</hi> vſed to <hi>Saul.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.23.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>caſt away the words of the Lord: therefore the Lord hath caſt away thee.</hi> Where it is proued, that the cauſe of <hi>Sauls</hi> abiection, was his owne wilfull reiection of God and his Word firſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God neuer made ſinne: For he ſaw all things that he had made, &amp; loe they were very good.<note place="margin">Gen. 1.31.</note> He appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it not, nor alloweth the perpetration of it, but threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth deſtruction to the Lyer and Doer of wickednes: For his heart abhorreth ſuch, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 5.4, 5, 6. where the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſpeaketh vnto God, thus: <hi>Thou art not a God that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth wickedneſſe: neither ſhall euill dwell with thee. The foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſhall not ſtand in thy ſight: for thou hateſt all them that worke iniquity. Thou ſhalt deſtroy them that ſpeake lyes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 92.15.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord will abhorre the bloudy man and deceitfull.</hi> As hee is righteous, and void of iniquitie: So hee alloweth righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and hateth ſinne in euery place and perſon.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the iuſt iudgements and puniſhments which GOD inflicteth vpon the wicked for ſinne, manifeſtly proue that he is diſpleaſed with the ſame. Hee ſpared not <hi>Dauid</hi> a King and a Prophet for Adultery and Murther; neither the Sichemites and Beniamites, for rauiſhing <hi>Dina</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Iacob,</hi> nor <hi>Abſalom</hi> for treaſon, nor <hi>Saul</hi> for tyrannie, nor <hi>Rehoboam, Iereboam, Sennacherib</hi> for cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty: <hi>Herod, Nebuchadnezzar, Lucifer</hi> for pride: <hi>Pharaoh</hi> for incredulitie and hardneſſe of his heart. Hee pardoned not <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eua</hi> for eating a forbidden fruit, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19782:39"/> by the ſame all mankinde ſinners by tainture, but caſt them out of Paradiſe: he ſpared not the poore wretch for gathering ſtickes on the Sabbath day: Hee ſpared not <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> for lying and with-holding part of their owne goods from the Apoſtles: He ſpared not Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, no nor the very Angels that ſinned, but caſt them downe, and deliuered them into chaines of darkneſſe, to bee kept vnto iudgement. To conclude, hee ſpared not Chriſt Ieſus his deare Sonne, but our ſinnes beeing impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him, he laid the puniſhment alſo vpon him, both in his body, and alſo his ſoule, whoſe bloudy wounds and paines were ſufficient to ſaue all, but efficient, and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all onely, to redeeme all the ſoules and bodies of his elect and faithfull. Therefore ſeeing that we know that he left no ſinne vnpuniſhed in the vnrepentant in all former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: but ſeeing, hearing, and knowing them all, as wel the offenders, as their offences, ſtraightwayes armed himſelfe with iuſtice and iudgement, and puniſhed them moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerely. We may aſſure our ſelues, that he hauing perfect knowledge and notice of all our miſdemeanours, and manifold tranſgreſſions, perpetrated againſt his diuine Maieſtie, will not ſpare vs, but will reprehend vs, and ſay vnto euery vnrepentant and bad Steward: <hi>How commeth it to paſſe that I heare this of thee?</hi> and preſently will call vs to account. Which is the fourth point, wherein the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable eſtate of a bad Steward, a wicked man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth.</p>
            <trailer>The end of the third Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="sermon">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:19782:39"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE FOVRTH SERMON.</hi> Come render account, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the benefits which our good GOD be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweth vpon the good Stewards, are in number infinite, in dignity excellent, and in meaſure incomprehenſible: and as the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Father hath,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> 
               <hi>Beneficia Dei omnibus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris conſideranda.</hi> For who is able to expreſſe to the full, the happy ſtate of that Steward, to whom it is ſaid of him that neuer diſſembleth, nor deludeth? <hi>O well done, thou good and faithfull ſeruant, thou haſt beene faithfull in little, I will make thee Ruler ouer much: enter into thy Maſters ioy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> So on the contrary, no man can expreſſe to the full, the lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eſtate of an euill Steward, and vnprofitable ſeruant, to whom it will be ſaid of the true Iudge: <hi>Caſt that vnprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſeruant into vtter darkneſſe: there ſhall bee weeping and gnaſhing of teeth:</hi> two bad diſhes to come in at the laſt; where the firſt diſh is weeping, and the ſecond gnaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of teeth. And to this paſſe is this bad Steward come: before him is <hi>praecipitium,</hi> a place to fall downe forward: behinde him is, <hi>occipitium,</hi> a place to fall downe back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: on the one ſide, <hi>Scilla;</hi> on the other ſide, <hi>Charyb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> ſo that he can flee no way without great danger. He
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19782:40"/> muſt needs ſtand ſtill, and indure all hazzards and perils, and come to his account, to the true audit. For now hee muſt take his <hi>vltimum vale,</hi> his laſt farewell, and ſing his dolefull and euerlaſting euen ſong. Such a great and horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble day is come,<note place="margin">Ioel 2. Mal. 4.</note> as the Prophet ſpeaketh of: <hi>Yea the day ſhall burne like an Ouen.</hi> But firſt the account ſhall be taken: For as a Prince and Nobleman, when he taketh a diſlike of his Steward, firſt reckoneth with him, and then putteth him out of his Office. So this Rich man is here ſaid to deale with his Steward, and Chriſt with all, at the laſt day, yea, his account ſhall bee more exactly and accurately taken, then of any other in this world. For he is God the Searcher of the heart, and according to the ſame hee will iudge righteouſly, hauing no reſpect nor regard to any mans perſon. For before him the King and the Begger is all one, when he ſhall come to take an account, and iudge, then Scepters and Shepheards ſhall be all one; Princes and Peſants; noble, and ignoble; yea, the very King and the Begger ſhall be fellowes: no better regarded ſhall bee the higheſt then the loweſt: but as when men put gold and ſiluer into a bagge, many pieces are ſhuffled together and yet the beſt may be the loweſt: So will it bee at this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall audit. If the greateſt men of this world are the worſt in faith, and godly life, and conuerſation, there will be no partiality vſed by the Iudge, but they ſhall be tumbled to the bottome of the pit, as ſoone as the pooreſt delinquent in the world. For when our Lord ſhall come with his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Angels, to take an account, and iudge the world, all are alike. For if great men and meane perſons are in the ſame ſinne, they ſhall be bound together, and caſt as a fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got into hell-fire. The glorious Angels at the great Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt ſhall firſt gather the Tares, ſeparating them from the Wheat:<note place="margin">Mat 25.32.</note> which is, <hi>poena damni,</hi> that is, the puniſhment of that a man loſeth, a plaine priuation of God, and all that is good, Angels, Saints, Friends; and then they ſhall binde them in Sheaues to be burnt: which is, <hi>poena ſenſus:</hi> the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19782:40"/> ſenſe of puniſhment, as it were a poſſeſsion of Hell, and all that is euill. <hi>Ludolphus</hi> thinketh that they ſhall not bee bound all in one, but in many Faggots. An Adulterer with an Adultereſſe ſhall make one Faggot, a Drunkard with a Drunkard another faggot, &amp;c. Hee thinketh that they ſhall not bee bound together that haue commited di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and ſeuerall ſinnes, neither according to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their Perſons, as King and King together, rich and rich, baſe and baſe. But as there are ſeuerall ſinnes, ſo ſeuerall Sheaues: and all this ſhall bee done without reſpect of perſon. This account ſhall bee taken not onely of externall things, but alſo of internall: that is to ſay, both of bodies and ſoules. No man can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe himſelfe, or vſe any cunning to deceiue, as before an earthly Iudge; but euery man ſhall appeare rightly as he is. For Chriſt (to whom the Father hath giuen all iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) will reſpect no man for his purſe ſake, nor friends.<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.</note> Therefore let vs deale ſincerely towards God and Man, knowing that we ſhall be called to account moſt ſtrictly, and accurately, for euery idle word, much more for euery wicked deed: and becauſe a good conſcience is a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and beſt <hi>ſuperſedeas</hi> in this point: let vs follow the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaid,<note place="margin">Act. 24.16.</note> that in this hee exerciſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that he might haue a good conſcience towards God and men.</p>
            <p>Tremble and quake (O ſinner) at the cogitation of theſe things. Repent, reuert, and turne vnto the Lord. For what art thou to ſtand in the preſence of this Iudge; being fraile, vaine, weake, naked miſerable, filthy, and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible? A man that hath imperfections in his eyes, cannot looke on the brightneſſe of the Sunne. And how canſt thou be perſwaded, that thou being an Infidell, fraile, and full of blemiſhes, ſhalt looke vpon the Sunne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Chriſt Ieſus? Repent, and beleeue, and thou ſhalt look vpon him, otherwiſe thou ſhalt be reiected. For as the Eagle, when ſhe hath yong ones, taketh them out of the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19782:41"/> neſt, and ſuch as can looke on the Sunne, them ſhe kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth; and ſuch as cannot, ſhe caſteth away; Euen ſo, they that with the eyes of their Faith, looke on Ieſus Chriſt, ſhall bee preſerued at this generall and great Aſsize, and they that cannot, ſhall bee tumbled downe to the pit of perdition.</p>
            <p>But becauſe ſecure and careleſſe men, Epicures and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, deny this great and ſtrict account that ſhall bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at the laſt Day,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.3, 4.</note> according to Saint <hi>Peters</hi> prediction, which telleth vs, that in the laſt dayes, there ſhall come mockers of Chriſts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to Iudgement to take this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; And theſe are the laſt dayes, in which wee ſee by many workes of the wicked, liuing in Atheiſme and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curiſme, that they are ſo perſwaded, and differ nothing (as appeareth) from the wicked iudgement of <hi>Paulus Terti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> the Pope, who when there was a ſpeech made vnto him of this account at the laſt Iudgement, ſaid vnto Cardinall <hi>Bembus: O Bembe, Bembe, quantum nobis profuit fabula de Chriſto!</hi> making this doctrine a fabulous thing. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (the more is the pitty) the queſtion <hi>(An ſit?)</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there is any laſt iudgement, is moſt neceſſary to bee diſcuſſed, and ſpoken of. Which whiles I endeuour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmatiuely to proue, I beſeech you without partialitie, lend mee your yeelding reſolutions vnto the truth, as it ſhall be proued. And
<q>
                  <l>—<hi>Si tu quid rectius iſtis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Candidus imperti, ſi non, his vtere mecum.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If better then theſe, thou haſt in ſtore,</l>
                  <l>Let vs haue part, and ſay no more:</l>
                  <l>But if thine owne doe thee not pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Vſe that I haue, and reſt at eaſe.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 100.</note>The firſt proofe is the Word of God, an eternall an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible truth, as our Sauiour doth witneſſe, ſpeaking thus to his Father a maintainer of it:<note place="margin">Ioh. 17.17.</note> 
               <hi>Sermo tuus eſt veritas,</hi> thy
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19782:41"/> Word is the Truth. <hi>Enoch</hi> the ſeuenth from <hi>Adam</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied, propheſied of this day of the Lords comming to take an account, ſaying, <hi>Behold,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude 14.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord commeth with thouſands of Saints, to giue iudgement againſt all men, and to rebuke all that are vngodly among them, of all their wicked deeds, which they haue vngodlily committed: and of all their cruell ſpeakings, which vngodly ſinners haue ſpoken againſt him.</hi> In which place, the Lords comming to iudgement is plainely foretold: and becauſe it is a thing certaine and ſure to be, therefore hee ſpeaketh in the preſent Tenſe, and ſaid: <hi>Behold, the Lord commeth.</hi> And ſo the high Iudge himſelfe ſpeaketh, ſaying, <hi>Behold, I come as a Theefe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 16.</note> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the preſent Tenſe (as before) and not in the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Tenſe, ſaying, <hi>I will come.</hi> And <hi>Peter</hi> reporteth,<note place="margin">Act. 10.</note> that the high Iudge, our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, commanded him, and the other Apoſtles, to preach vnto the people, and to teſtifie, that it is he, that is ordained of God, a Iudge of quicke and dead. And <hi>Paul</hi> prepareth men by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance againſt that Day, ſaying:<note place="margin">Act. 17.30, 31.</note> Now hee admoniſheth all men euery where to repent; becauſe hee hath appointed a day, in the which he will iudge the world in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp;c. The ſame <hi>Paul</hi> aſſureth vs, that wee all muſt appeare before the Iudgement ſeat of Chriſt,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> that euery man may receiue the things which are done in his body, according to that he hath done, whether it bee good or euill. The ſame Apoſtle moſt plainely ſetteth downe the order and manner of the Lords deſcenſion from Heauen to doe this weighty buſineſſe, when as he ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.16, 17</note> 
               <hi>The Lord himſelfe ſhall deſcend from Heauen with a ſhout, and with the voice of the Archangell, and with the Trumpet of God: And the dead in Chriſt ſhal riſe firſt: then we which liue &amp; remaine, ſhall bee caught vp with them alſo in the clouds, to meet the Lord in the Aire: and ſo ſhall we euer be with the Lord.</hi> This comming of our Sauiour to iudge, and to take this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, was foretold of the Angels, who ſtanding by him when hee aſcended into Heauen, and ſeeing the men of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19782:42"/> Galilee gazing after him, ſaid, This Ieſus which is taken vp from you, ſhall ſo come, as ye haue ſeene him goe into heauen. And how can we doubt hereof, ſeeing that our Sauiour himſelfe, euen the high Iudge, foreſheweth the ſame?<note place="margin">Mat. 27. &amp; 25.</note> And Saint <hi>Mathew</hi> ſetteth downe the order and maner of this Iudgement ſo plainely, that no man, led by the Spirit of God, can once mutter againſt his doctrine.</p>
            <p>The ſecond proofe is taken from the end vnto which mankind was made of God. God neceſſarily obtaineth his end. And this was the end for which he made man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that he might be his Image, and his eternall Temple wherein he might and ſhould be celebrated: to whom he might communicate himſelfe, his chiefe wiſedome, goodneſſe, righteouſneſſe, and felicitie; which felicitie is part of the Image of God, but this is deſtroyed and defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of the Deuill: Therefore God, which is ſtronger then the Deuill, will reſtore it. And although the end for which man was made, is hindred diuers wayes in this life, yet the Lord once will attaine vnto it. Wherefore there muſt of neceſſitie once be a change, and an adiudging vnto the ſame end. And here it is admirable to conſider, how like a Diuine the learned Philoſopher aymed and leuelled at this marke and matter: For thus hee ſaid, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eriſimile eſt hominem ad has miſerias non eſſe conditum, ſed &amp; longè ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſsimum eſt, praeſtantiſsimam creaturam omnium, ad melio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem finem conditam eſſe:</hi> That is to ſay, It is like to be true, that man was not made to endure theſe miſeries, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is farre moſt true, that the moſt excellent creature of all was made to a better end.</p>
            <p>The third proofe is taken from the righteouſneſſe of God, his goodneſſe and diuine truth, which require that the godly ſhould be perfectly well, and the wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly euill, and this falleth not out ſo many times in this life. For here we ſee the wicked many times flouriſh with all worldly proſperitie,<note place="margin">Pſal 37.35. luke 16.</note> according to <hi>Dauids</hi> report, and the example of the rich Glutton. Therefore there muſt
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19782:42"/> be another life, wherein this iuſtice of God may appeare, that both bodies and ſoules, as they haue beene ioynt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of good actions and bad, may haue either ioy and comfort, or paine, terrour, and diſcomforts; the wicked may haue tribulation, the godly, reſt. And the inchoation of this, ſhall be at this day and time: as <hi>Paul</hi> prooueth, where he comforteth the Church of the Theſſalonians, ſhewing, that their perſecuters ſhall be afflicted, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly puniſhed at this day and time, and the godly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded. The words are theſe:<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 1.6, 7, 8, 9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>It is a righteous thing with God, to recompence tribulation to them that trouble you, and to you which are troubled, reſt with vs, when the Lord Ieſus ſhall ſhew himſelfe from heauen, with his mighty Angels, in fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire, rendring vengeance to them that doe not know God, and which obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which ſhall be puniſhed with euerlaſting perdition, from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power, when he ſhall come to be glorified in his Saints, and to be made marueilous in all them that beleeue. Abraham,</hi> in his conference which hee had with the rich Glutton tormented in hell, ſpeaketh to this purpoſe when he ſaid: <hi>Remember that thou in thy life time receiuedſt thy pleaſures, and likewiſe</hi> Lazarus <hi>paines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 16 25.</note> 
               <hi>now therefore is he comforted, and thou art tormented.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth reaſon ſtanding for a proofe, may be drawne from Chriſts glory: that as he was diſhonoured at his firſt comming in the fleſh, wonderfully abaſed, diſgraced, and humbled: ſo at his ſecond comming, hee ſhall appeare in glorie, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.31.</p>
            <p>The fift reaſon which the ancient Father ſetteth down in ſtead of a proofe, is probable; and it is taken from the Rainbow: in which are two colours, <hi>ceruleus, ſeu aqueus color; &amp; purpureus, ſeu igneus color,</hi> The gray and watrie colour, and the purple or fiery colour. <hi>Ceruleus ſeu aqueus color, indicat mundum aquis diluvij perijſſe; &amp; eo modo nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam deinceps deleturum iri.</hi> That is, the gray or watry colour doth ſhew, that the world periſhed with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19782:43"/> of the Flood, and neuer after ſhall be deſtroyed after that manner. That is proued, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. where it is ſaid, That God ſet the Rainbow in the skie, as a true externall ſigne, that the earth ſhall neuer be ouerflowne againe with the waters of a Floud. Now the other colour, <hi>purpureus ſeu igneus color ſignificat mundum deinceps in extremo iudicio igne tranſiturum:</hi> That is to ſay, The purple or fierie colour doth ſhew vnto vs, that the world hereafter in the laſt Iudgement ſhall paſſe away, and be purged with fire. And this is proued, and will fall out true, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7.</p>
            <p>The ſixt, is the horrible promulgation of the Law in mount Sinai, in thundring, lightning, and flames of fire, threatning moſt horrible puniſhment to the offendours, and inforce withall the maledictions and tortures denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in the ſame, againſt all impenitent perſons and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels: which doth proue, that there is a day of Iudgement and account. For whereas theſe wicked ones rather flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh here, then receiue puniſhment: there muſt needes bee a iudgement and account taken of theſe delinquents, and another life, that thoſe things that God hath ſpoken, may take true effect, that the fulfillers of the Law (which are the faithfull in Chriſt) may haue life, and the impenitent tranſgreſſours, death eternall. For the Lord knoweth how to deliuer the godly out of temptation,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.9.</note> and to reſerue the vniuſt vnto the day of iudgement for to bee puniſhed. And according to this, a mans conſcience doth miniſter many times feare, or hope vnto him, according as his deedes haue beene.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Ouid. Faſt. pri.</note>Conſcia mens vt cuiquè ſua eſt, ita concipit intra</l>
               <l>Pectora, pro meritis ſpem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> metum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſuis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Laſtly, diuers ſignes and tokens of the laſt Iudgement, which were foretold of the Prophets, of Chriſt, and the Apoſtles, that ſhould goe before this Day, and time of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, are accompliſhed. And therefore there is a day of Iudgement and an account,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.7. Mat. 24.33.</note> and it is at hand. Theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions and foreſignes are moſt ſet downe, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19782:43"/> where it is ſhewed, that there ſhall be many falſe Chriſts, and falſe prophets, many hereſies, errours and ſects. Which we ſee to be true, not onely among the Romaniſts and Rhemiſts, but euen (the more is the pitie) many ſecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and factious perſons ariſe among our ſelues. Againe, we haue had warres and rumours of warres. Moreouer, there haue beene famines, peſtilences, and earthquakes, and that within our times that are now liuing; wee need not ſeeke for further proofes nor examples; for if wee would, we might haue many. To ſpeake of ſignes in the Sunne, Moone, or Starres, coldneſſe of charitie, and the reſt, would make me too tedious: therefore I will leaue them, and many other foretellings, as apparent truthes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready fulfilled, and yeelded vnto of all them that are true and ſettled Chriſtians. Onely let me begge of you that are Readers of this Treatiſe, to hearken to the vſe of my do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, wherein I will be ſo briefe, that my beginning and end ſhall almoſt be knit together.</p>
            <p>Firſt, this doctrine auaileth to confute Epicures, and Atheiſts, and mockers of this doctrine of Chriſtes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Iudgement to take this accompt, who ſay, as the Apoſtle hath, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. <hi>Where is the promiſe of his comming?</hi> For ſince the Fathers died, all things continue alike from the beginning of the Creation.<note place="margin">2. Epiſt. 3.</note> Theſe the Apoſtle ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throweth by two reaſons; Firſt, in that the falſe mockers ſay, that all things continue alike ſince the Creation: hee proueth it to be falſe by the Floud in the daies of <hi>Noah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 5.</note> For this they know not (ſaith he) and that wilfully, how that the heauens were of old, and the earth conſiſting of the water, and by the water, by the Word of God: by the which thing the world that then was periſhed, being then ouerrunne with water.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he ſheweth the manner of the purging of the world in the day of Iudgement by fire, ſaying, But the heauens and the earth which are now, be kept by his Word in ſtore, and reſerued vnto fire againſt the day of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19782:44"/> iudgement, and perdition of vngodly men. Therefore all things haue not, neither will continue alwaies alike, and yet theſe wicked Atheiſts, as heretofore, ſo ſtill perſeuere in their wicked courſe of life, and incourage one another to ſecuritie and pleaſures,<note place="margin">Eſa. 56.12.</note> they ſay, <hi>Come, let vs take wine, and we will fill our ſelues with ſtrong drinke, and to morrow ſhal be as this day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Wiſdom. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and much more abundant.</hi> They ſay, <hi>Come, and let vs enioy the pleaſures that are preſent, and let vs cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vſe the creatures as in youth; let vs fill our ſelues with coſtly wine and oyntments, and let not the flower of life paſſe by vs. Let vs crowne our ſelues with Roſe-buds before they be withered: Let vs be partakers of our wantonneſſe, let vs leaue ſome tokens of our pleaſures in euery place: for that is our por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and this is our lot.</hi> Theſe men liue rocked and lulled in the cradle of ſecuritie, as though there were no death certaine, no account to bee made, no hell at all. Which thing the Poet lamented, when he ſaid euen mournfully,
<q>
                  <l>Eheu ſic viuunt homines tanquam mors nulla ſequatur,</l>
                  <l>Et veluti infernus fabula vana foret.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9.27.28.</note>But let theſe men conſider, that (as it is in holy Writ) it is appointed to all men to die once; and after death com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth iudgement: and that the careleſſe and bad Steward muſt come to reckoning. And as the Wiſe man hath, God will call man to account for all theſe things; for all theſe fooleries and ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this doctrine auaileth to comfort the godly afflicted: <hi>Erit olim viciſcitudo,</hi> there wil once be a change: Their ſorrow will once bee turned into ioy eternall. All teares once ſhall be wiped from their eyes. When we are in extremity, let vs conſider, yea and comfort our ſelues with that conſolation which the Lord gaue to the Church of Philadelphia,<note place="margin">Reuel. 3.11, 12.</note> ſaying, <hi>Behold, I come ſhortly:</hi> and ſo hee comforted the other Churches. And the like ioy and conſolation may we all conceiue in all our tribulations and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19782:44"/> miſeries. Let vs euer conſider, that the Lord will come quickly, and that he that endureth temptation is bleſſed, and ſhall at the laſt receiue the crowne of glorie,<note place="margin">Iames 1.12.</note> which the Lord hath promiſed to them that loue him.</p>
            <p>The third vſe. We ſhould, by the knowledge and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of this day, keepe vs in the feare of God, and care to doe our duties.<note place="margin">1. Epiſt. 4.7, 8.</note> And this Saint <hi>Peter</hi> teacheth vs to doe, ſaying: <hi>The end of all things is at hand, be ye therefore ſober, and watching in prayer. But aboue all things, haue fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent loue among you: for loue couereth the multitude of ſinnes.</hi> The ſame Apoſtle declaring the fearefulnelſſe of this day,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.</note> to wit, how it ſhall come as a theefe in the night; and that the heauens ſhall paſſe away with a noyſe, and the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhall melt with heate, and the earth with the works that are therein ſhall be burnt vp, maketh this vſe, thus concluding of his former doctrines. Seeing therefore,<note place="margin">Verſe 11.</note> that all theſe things muſt be diſſolued, what manner per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ought ye to be in holy conuerſation and godlines, &amp;c? As though he ſhould ſay, You ought to be moſt religious, moſt godly, of a moſt pure life and conuerſation.<note place="margin">Verſe 14.</note> And me thinkes we ſhould haue a care to be moſt holy without ſpot and vndefiled, euen blameleſſe; becauſe wee ſhall, at that day, ſtand before the righteous and vncorrupt Iudge, and ſhall ſtand openly in the ſight of the holy Angels. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writing vpon theſe words,<note place="margin">Reu. 20.12.</note> 
               <hi>(And I ſaw the dead both ſmall and great ſtand before God, &amp;c.)</hi> hath theſe words; <hi>Rogo vos (fratres) vt quotidiè cogitemus, quales eſſe debemus in die iudicij, puriſsimis Angelorum conſpectibus of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferendi, &amp; aeterno Iudici rationem de libris conſcientiae reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turi:</hi> that is, O brethren, I beſeech you, let vs conſider what maner of perſons we ought to be in the laſt day of iudgement, that ſhall be preſented to the moſt pure ſight of Angels, and that ſhall render an account to the moſt high Iudge, of the bookes of our conſcience. It ſeemed that the good Father kept himſelfe in good order, in the feare of God, and in his Chriſtian dutie, with the daily co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitation
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19782:45"/> of this Day, and ſerious meditation how to make a good reckoning at the laſt day, and that hee exhorted o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the like vigilance and carefulneſſe. <hi>Hierom</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth,<note place="margin">Tract. 5. cap. 3.</note> that whatſoeuer he did, he alwaies bore in mind this Day, and thought that he was going to Iudgement: <hi>Siue comedam, ſiue hibam, ſiue aliquid aliud agam, ſemper videtur vox illa ſonare in auribus, Surgite mortui, &amp; venite ad iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium:</hi> that is to ſay, Whether I eate, or drinke, or doe any thing elſe, me thinkes I alwaies heare this ſpeech ring in my eares: Riſe ye dead, and come to Iudgement; and ſo by this meanes he kept himſelfe in awe, and refreinad to commit ſinne and wickedneſſe.</p>
            <p>As the Lord would haue vs to know, that there is a day of iudgement for his owne glory, our owne comfort, the confutation of Epicures and Atheiſts, and to keepe vs in our duties: ſo he hath concealed from vs the certaine time when it ſhall be, as it may be proued out of the ſacred Scriptures, theſe two wayes:
<list>
                  <item>1. By plaine ſayings and ſentences.</item>
                  <item>2. By Parables or ſimilitudes.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24.42.</note>Firſt, by plaine ſpeeches, ſuch as theſe: <hi>Watch, for yee know neither the day, nor the houre when the Sonne of man will come.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.13.</note> Againe, <hi>Watch ye therefore, for ye know not, when the Maſter of the houſe will come, at euen, or at midnight, at the cocke crowing, or in the dawning, leſt if he come ſuddenly, hee ſhould find you ſleeping: And thoſe things that I ſay vnto you, I ſay vnto all men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 13.35.</note> 
               <hi>Watch.</hi> Note the words: <hi>Watch ye there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, for ye know not the day, nor the houre, &amp;c.</hi> And to this purpoſe ſpeaketh Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 78.</note> writing to <hi>Heſychius, Tempora computare, hoc eſt,</hi> CHRONOS <hi>vt ſciamus, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſit huius ſaeculi finis, vel aduentus Domini, nihil mihi aliud videtur, quàm ſcire, velle, quod Chriſtus ait, Scire neminem.</hi> That is to ſay, To count times, that is, to know the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, when ſhall be the end of this world, or the comming of the Lord, this ſeemeth to me, that a man is willing to know no other thing, but that which Chriſt ſaith, No man ſhall know. And why ſhould a man diue into the Lords
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19782:45"/> ſecrets, which hee is not willing to reueale vnto vs,<note place="margin">Act. 1.7.</note> and which it is not expedient for vs to know. Our Sauiour ſaid vnto the Apoſtles;<note place="margin">Mark. 13.</note> 
               <hi>It is not for you to know the times or the ſeaſons, which the Father hath put in his owne power. Hee hath not reuealed this ſecret to Man, nor Angell,</hi> Math. 24.36.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this is proued by Parables, as of the ten Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins that went to meet the Bridegroome, theſe ſlept,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> and ſuddenly at midnight, when they looked not for him, there was a cry that the Bridegroome came, and theſe words were vttered; <hi>Goe out to meet him.</hi> Note the words I beſeech you: <hi>(and ſodainly at midnight, when they looked not for him.)</hi> This proueth that the Lords comming to Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall be ſudden, and that hee ſhall finde the vvicked ones ſecure and careleſſe. Againe, the Parable of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents doth admoniſh vs to be watchfull, becauſe the day and time of the Lords comming to take an account, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, and vnknowne. For as the deliuerer of the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, going into a ſtrange Countrey, gaue the receiuers of them a charge to occupy them till he came, and did not tell when he would come; but yet after a long ſeaſon came to reckon with them, and to call them to account, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them in his mercy, according to their ſeuerall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments: Euen ſo, our Sauiour beeing gone as it were into a ſtrange countrey, into Heauen, where he neuer was in body before, hath deliuered vnto ſundry and ſeuerall perſons excellent gifts, which he would haue them vſe to his glory, and the good of his Church; and hee will come after a ſeaſon, (he telleth not when, and therefore no man knoweth the time) to take a ſtrict account of all the recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of them.</p>
            <p>The ſodaineneſſe and vncertaintie of his comming,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.2. Reu. 16.15. Luk. 17.24.</note> is compared to the comming of a Thiefe which giues no warning, to lightening that giues a ſodaine flaſh, and ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teneth out of the one part vnder Heauen, and ſhineth vnto the other part vnder Heauen; to the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19782:46"/> the careleſſe people did eate and drinke,<note place="margin">Luke 17.</note> married wiues, and gaue in marriage, vnto the day that <hi>Noah</hi> went into the Arke, and the Floud came and deſtroyed them all, euen ſodainely when they neuer thought, much leſſe knew of the certaine and preſcript time. For the ſame reaſon, thoſe dayes wherein Chriſt ſhal come, are compared to the daies of <hi>Lot.</hi> Theſe ſimilitudes doe tell and teach vs, that the Lords comming to Iudgement is vnknowne, and ſhall bee ſodaine. For to this purpoſe, the Euangeliſt moſt aptly applyeth this doctrine, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.30.<note place="margin">Luke 17.30.</note> ſaying, After theſe enſamples ſhall it be in the day, when the Sonne of Man is reuealed.<note place="margin">Epiſt. 88.</note> 
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writing to <hi>Heſichius,</hi> hath an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ſaying to this purpoſe, <hi>Ego namque de Saluatoris ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentu, qui expectatur in fine, tempora dinumerare non audeo, nec aliquem propheta, de hac re numerum annorum exiſtimo praefinſſe,</hi> that is to ſay, I dare not number the times of the comming of our Sauiour, which in the end is looked for; neither do I thinke that any Prophet hath determined the number of yeeres. I therefore conclude this point, thus: Man knoweth not that day and houre, nor the Angels; Nay (which is moſt of all) not the Sonne, as touching his humanity and mediatorſhip,<note place="margin">Math. 24. Mar. 13.</note> but the Father onely and yet I ſtand aſſured, that in his Godhead hee knoweth this time.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Reaſons wherefore the Lord concealeth the times of his comming.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>It is not expedient for vs to know them.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That wee might exerciſe our faith and patience.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>To make vs more vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, it is not expedient nor meet for vs to know theſe things; I meane thoſe ſecrets which the Father hath kept in his owne power.<note place="margin">Act. 1.6.</note> The Apoſtles asked our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, whether hee at that time would reſtore the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19782:46"/> Kingdome to Iſrael, that is to ſay, to his old ancient ſtate? Hee anſwered, It is not for you to know the times and ſeaſons, which the Father hath put in his owne power: as though he ſhould ſay, it belongeth not to you to know the moments of times, and occaſions of abſtruſe, ſecret and myſticall things, not reuealed in the Word: as what houre a man ſhall dye; what houre the Lord will come to Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; when he will vtterly deſtroy the kingdome of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan; at what moment hee will bring his ſubiects into the Kingdome of his Father. There is a time when theſe things ſhall bee performed, but hid from vs, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ought to beleeue them: for they are true, and in their due times ſhall truely be performed, but wee ought not curiouſly pry into theſe ſecrets. For this (as <hi>Hugo</hi> hath) is <hi>curioſitas ſuperflua, inueſtigatio rerum ad ſe non per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentium;</hi> that is, this is ſuperfluous curioſitie, a ſearching out of matters that doe not belong to vs. This is no doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Spirit. For (as <hi>Bernard</hi> writing vpon the <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> hath) <hi>Doctrina ſpiritus non curioſitatem acuit, ſed cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem accendit:</hi> The doctrine of the Spirit doth not whet on curioſitie, but inflameth charitie. Therefore let vs learne to refraine from curious queſtions, as the Apoſtle teacheth <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus:</hi> let vs not ſearch and diue too deepe in dangerous whirlepooles, leſt we ſhould be drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. This is good for the Teacher, and profitable for the Hearer. And this good counſell <hi>Auguſtine</hi> giueth in his eightieth Epiſtle, anſwering <hi>Heſychius;</hi> and in his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine; teaching men not curiouſly to ſearch into the times and ſeaſons: but to ſtudy the Death and Reſurrection of Chriſt, that is to ſay, matters of ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Chriſt concealeth this day and houre, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe mens faith, and patience.<note place="margin">Chap. 5.</note> And to this purpoſe <hi>Iames</hi> giueth this good exhortation: <hi>Bee patient, brethren, vnto the comming of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> In which place he doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the poore, oppreſſed of the rich, warning them to wait for the Lords comming patiently, who will reuenge
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19782:47"/> the iniuries which the rich men doe to them, and giue vnto them, waiting in Faith and Hope, and yeelding pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, a proſperous iſſue and deliuerance; and in the meane time, when a man is in miſery, patience will make the griefe lighter and eaſier to bee borne. This made the Poet ſay:<note place="margin">Horace.</note> 
               <hi>Durum, ſed leuius fit patientia, quicquid corrige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re eſt nefas.</hi> It is hard, I confeſſe, that thou canſt not redreſſe, yet lighter through patience, if quietly thou beare it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Lord telleth vs not when hee will come to call vs to account, that wee aſſured of his comming, and not knowing when, ſhould at all times be vigilant, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and carefull to doe our duties, to haue all things in a godly and good order at our Lord and Maſters comming. As good domeſticall ſeruants, when their Maſter is gone from them, aſſuring themſelues that hee will come againe vnto them, and not knowing when: and that he will call them to an account, (if they haue any care) will at all times haue all things in readineſſe, and good order, that their earthly Maſter may not come vpon them vnawares, and finde them idle, and ill occupied, and all things out of right courſe: So we, ſeruants to Chriſt Ieſus our Sauiour; and knowing that hee is gone from vs into Heauen, and ſtanding aſſured that hee will come to take a reckoning of vs, of our liues and conuerſations, and not knowing when; ſhould at all times haue our accounts ſtraight, haue all things in readineſſe and good order, that our heauenly Iudge and Maſter, when he commeth to iudge the quicke and the dead, may not come vpon vs vnawares at the laſt Day, and finde vs idle, or ill occupied, and all things out of good order. And to this purpoſe tendeth that exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of our Sauiour Chriſt:<note place="margin">Luk. 12.35, 36.</note> 
               <hi>Let your loynes bee girt, and your lights burning, and yee your ſelues like vnto men, that wait for their Master when he will returne from the wedding, that when hee commeth and knocketh, they may open vnto him immediately. Bleſſed are thoſe ſeruants, whom the Lord, when
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19782:47"/> he commeth, ſhall finde waking, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> giueth the like godly exhortation: <hi>But of the times and ſeaſons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, yee haue no neede that I write vnto you: for yee your ſelues know perfectly, that the Day of the Lord ſhall come, euen as a Thiefe in the night. For when they ſhall ſay, Peace, and ſafety, then ſhall come vpon them ſodaine deſtruction, as the trauell vpon a woman with childe, and they ſhall not eſcape.</hi> But ye, brethren, are not in darkneſſe, that that day ſhould come on you, as it were a Thiefe. Yee are all the children of light, and the children of the day: wee are not of the night, neither of darkneſſe. Therefore let vs not ſleepe as doe others, but let vs watch, and bee ſober. And what plainer exhortation can there bee deliuered to this purpoſe,<note place="margin">Mar. 24.42. &amp; 44. Mar. 13.35.</note> then that which the bleſſed Euangeliſt <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> ſetteth downe, ſaying, <hi>Wake therefore: for ye know not what houre your Maſter will come.</hi> Many other exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we haue to moue, incite, and ſtirre vs to a godly life, drawne from this day of Iudgement: as that of <hi>Paul, Act.</hi> 17.30, 31. verſes, where hee preached againſt idolatry, and told the idolatrous people, that God admoniſhed all men euery where now to repent: Becauſe hee hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a day wherein hee will iudge the world in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, &amp;c. Let the recordation hereof make vs to be ſober, and watch, and haue feruent loue, as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted the faithfull, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.7, 8. ſaying, <hi>Now the end of all things is at hand: be ye therefore ſober, and watching in Prayer: But aboue all things, haue feruent loue among your ſelues.</hi> Watch therefore, beloued, and againe I ſay, Watch. Take inſtruction of the Hare, who not knowing when her enemy may come vpon her, yet fearing the worſt, ſleepeth with her eyes open, and by that meanes ſeeth the leaſt glimpſe of her enemy that may ſteale vpon her. The Nightingale fearing leſt ſhe ſhould be deuoured of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, ſetteth her breſt againſt a ſharpe Thorne, or ſome hard thing, that when ſhe, oppreſſed which ſleepe, nod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, ſhee may by and by be awaked, and then ſhee will
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19782:48"/> ſing moſt cheerefully &amp; melodiouſly. So doe you, deare brethren, ſleepe as the Hare doth, with her eyes open, that you may awake, &amp; ſodainly auoid, when your enemy, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, with his alluring temptations, would ſteale vpon you. Sleepe alſo when you are heauy and drowſie, as the Nigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingale doth, with ſome ſharp thing at your breſt (I meane ſorrow for ſin at your heart) that though againſt your wil, you nodde ſometimes with ſleepe, yet you may with the Nightingale ſpeedily awake, and ſing melodious, but yet ſpiritual ſongs;<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.19.</note> I meane Pſalmes of thankſgiuing vnto the Lord; as <hi>Dauid</hi> doth exhort vs, ſaying, <hi>Sing wee merrily vnto our Lord God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 81.</note> 
               <hi>make a cheerefull noiſe vnto the God of</hi> Iacob. O let vs be mindfull of our latter end, of death, and this laſt account; which that we may the better doe, let vs call to minde diuers domeſticall and familiar things, dayly conuerſant before our eyes, that they may put vs in minde of our latter end, and all circumſtances touching the ſame, all antecedents, coniuncts, and conſequents. Our beds may bring to our remembrances, our graues; our ſheetes that we lye in,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.</note> our winding ſheete; our ſleepe, death: (for vnto the ſame Death is compared) the very Flea that bites vs, the worme of Conſcience, that ſhall gnaw the wicked: the crowing of the Cocke that awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs out of ſleepe, and warneth vs of the paſsing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of the night, may preſage vnto vs the Trumpe of the Lord, the ſweet Bels of <hi>Aaron</hi> ſounding out and ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alowd, to call vs to the Church, the ſocietie of the faithfull, to knowledge, faith, and a godly life here in this world, yea, and our awaking out of the ſleepe of death at the laſt Day, the laſt audit and account at the time of the Reſurrection. Therefore (beloued) giue mee leaue for your good, to ſhake you out of the cradle of your ſleepe, ſecuritie and careleſneſſe: be lulled and rocked therein no longer. For then you are ſaid to bee aſleepe in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, when all the powers of the minde and ſenſes are ſo ouercome with the ſound and dead ſleepe of ſinne, that
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19782:48"/> you cannot heare when Chriſt calleth; nor ſee him when he commeth vnto you; nor feele him, when he knocketh at your hearts; nor taſte him how gracious hee is, when ye come to receiue the Sacraments, but only to your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, when ye doe not ſmell him whether hee bee a ſauour of life vnto life, or death vnto death, ſo that yee cannot know the day of your viſitation, when ſuch dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ouerſhaddoweth you, that you cannot comprehend Chriſt the light, when he commeth among his owne. On the contrary, then are we ſaid to watch, when all our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are apt to all godly exerciſes; when our eares are open to heare Chriſt our Maſter; when we continue our watch and ward, neuer putting off our armour, or betaking our ſelues to our reſt, leaſt Death, the Lords Bayliffe, ſhould ſodainly arreſt vs, or our Sauiour the high Iudge com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to Iudgement, when wee leaſt thinke of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5. 2. Pet. 3.</note> (and therefore it's compared to the comming of a Thiefe, who giues no warning) ſhould ſodainly (we vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouided, and not looking for him) ſteale vpon vs. And this is the reaſon that my Text giueth mee occaſion to preſſe you with now. The ſpeciall exerciſe that we are to vſe in our Watch and Ward, is Prayer.<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. Mat. 24.42.</note> And becauſe wee know not the certaine time of the Lords comming to take this account, we ſhould bee the more vigilant and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, hauing on our ſpirituall armour,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 6.</note> whereof <hi>Paul</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. Watch therefore (good Chriſtians) whiles it is the time of light, the time of grace, before the night of death commeth, wherein no man can worke out his ſaluation, <hi>Ezek</hi> 7. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> yeeldeth a reaſon, why man knoweth not the time of his death, nor the Day of Iudgement. His words are theſe: <hi>Magna Dei miſericordia monuit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Pſal. 34.</note> 
               <hi>vt rectè viuamus, &amp; ideo diem mortis, &amp; extremi Iudicij nobis ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcondit, ne nobis in futurum aliquid promittamus:</hi> that is, the great mercy of God hath taught vs to liue well, and for this cauſe he hath kept vs from the day of our death, and of the laſt Iudgement, that wee might not promiſe any
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19782:49"/> thing to our ſelues afterwards.<note place="margin">Auguſt. de diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plina Chriſtiana.</note> The ſame ſaith, <hi>Latet vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus dies, vt obſeruentur omnes dies:</hi> that is to ſay, the laſt day is vnknowne, that we ſhould obſerue all dayes. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I ſay, Watch, for you are not certaine to liue one houre: &amp; I wil tell you how I would haue you watch: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilate rectè credendo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Helm.</note> 
               <hi>firmiter ſperando, ſincere Deum &amp; prox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imum diligendo, mandata Dei cuſtodiendo, ſanctè, piè &amp; iuſtè viuendo, ſine intermiſsione orando, in patientia Deo in omnibus bonis operibus fructificando, quae edificationis ſunt, vbique ſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tando, in omni bonitate vſque in finem permanendo,</hi> that is to ſay, Watch, truely beleeuing, ſtedfaſtly hoping, ſincerely louing God and our neighbour, keeping the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, liuing holily, godly, and iuſtly, praying without ceaſing, in patience fructifying to GOD in all good workes, following in euery place thoſe things that tend to edification, continuing in all goodneſſe to the end. If thou doeſt theſe things, thou ſhalt neuer periſh, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this world, nor in the world to come.</p>
            <p>The doctrine of the vncertainty of the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ouerthroweth all the coniecturall and doubtfull o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of them which haue gone about to ſet downe the certaine time of Chriſts comming to Iudgement, and the purging of the world by fire. <hi>Elias,</hi> whether the Prophet, or rather ſome other <hi>Elias</hi> of the Rabbins, becauſe it is not found in the ſacred Scriptures, but in the <hi>Thalmud</hi> of the Iewes, hath ſet downe his opinion thus: <hi>Sex millia an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum mundus durabit, &amp; deinde conflagratio:</hi> that is, The world ſhall continue ſixe thouſand yeeres, and then bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning makes an end of it. And becauſe of ſinnes which ſhall be many and great, ſome yeeres ſhall be wanting. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> the Martyr was of the ſame mind: theſe are his wordes, <hi>Quot diebus factus eſt hic mundus, tot millenarijs conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur, (nam mille anni apud Dominum quaſi dies vnus) Pſal.</hi> 90. and 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. Now all things were finiſhed perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly in ſixe dayes, and the ſeuenth day was a time of reſt. Therefore the conſummation of all thoſe things ſhall be in
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19782:49"/> the ſeuen thouſandth yere the perpetuall Sabbath, the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting reſt. This is their fallible collection and conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, altogether repugnant to the Scriptures. The greateſt reaſon, or rather ſhew of reaſon, that made <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus,</hi> and their followers to erre, was, for that they vpon theſe words, <hi>(A thouſand yeeres are with the Lord as one day)</hi> doe ſay, that the world was made in ſixe dayes, and the ſeuenth day was a day of reſt: therefore the world ſhal ſtand and continue ſixe thouſand yeeres, and in the ſeuenth thouſand ſhall be the conſummation and end of all. In ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deed I muſt needs confeſſe, that theſe men were lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. But <hi>Bernardus non vidit omnia,</hi> neither theſe men: for in my opinion herein they were deceiued, in that they thought, that in eternall life, in the world to come with God, were ſpaces of times, yeeres, dayes, and houres, as well as with men in this mortall life; which is not true: for in heauen (I meane not the <hi>aereum Coelum,</hi> ayrie hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, conteining the ſpace from vs vnto the Firmament, nor <hi>coelum coelatum,</hi> the engrauen heauen; which I ſo call, becauſe it is as it were ingrauen, and enameled with glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious lights, the Sunne, the Moone, and the Starres) but the heauen which is called of the Philoſopher <hi>Empyreum,</hi> but by Diuines in Scripture, the glorious Heauen of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, or Heauen aboue the viſible heauens, wherein is our Sauiour, the Angels, and glorified Saints. In this are no ſpaces, nor ſeaſons of yeeres, dayes, moneths, houres, or other times: which thus I proue, becauſe there is no Sun, nor Moone, nor Stars, nor no vſe, need, nor neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of any of them. For the claritie and brightneſſe of the Lord ſhineth there: There is no night, no Clockes, nor Dyals, nor Watches. How then is it poſsible for a man to know the ſpaces of times there? Wherefore in the life to come, a thouſand yeeres are as one day, and one day as a thouſand yeeres. The Pſalmiſt therefore well ſaid, <hi>A thouſand yeeres in thy ſight are but as yeſterday,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 90.4.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeing that is paſt as a watch in the night.</hi> Againe, there is ſo much ioy
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19782:50"/> in heauen, that for the greatneſſe and pleaſantneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, a thouſand yeeres ſeeme to be but one day. But in no wiſe can it be hereby gathered, that, becauſe in ſixe dayes the world was made, and in the ſeuenth was reſt, that therefore the world ſhall continue ſixe thouſand yeeres, and in the ſeuenth ſhall be a perpetuall reſt, and Sabboth, and an end of all, and ſo a certaine time knowne.</p>
            <p>Beſides the maintainers of the opinion aboueſaid, there are others, which haue taken vpon them to gheſſe at the yeere when there ſhould be an end of all things. In this number are they which thought, that the end of the world ſhall be in the yeere from Chriſts birth, 1656. becauſe there were ſo many yeeres from the creation of <hi>Adam</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Flood: and the rather they haue ſo ſuppoſed, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our Sauiour and Saint <hi>Peter</hi> doe compare the times of the Floud,<note place="margin">Mat. 24. 2. Epiſt. 3.</note> and of the fire in the laſt day together. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as therefore from the Creation of <hi>Adam</hi> vnto the Deluge, were 1656. yeeres and ſixe dayes, they collect, that there ſhall be ſo many yeeres vnto the laſt Iudgement, when the World ſhall bee purged by fire. Some thought that it ſhould bee in the yeere 1588. among which number was <hi>Regiomantanus,</hi> who left to the world certain Verſes, ſhewing his too farre reaching opinion. Which Verſes are theſe following.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Post mille expletos à partu Virginis annos,</l>
               <l>Et poſt quingentos rurſus ab orbe datos,</l>
               <l>Octo geſimus octauus mirabilis annus</l>
               <l>Ingruet, is ſecum iriſtia fata trahet.</l>
               <l>Si non hoc anno totus malus occidet orbis,</l>
               <l>Si non in nihilum terra fretumque ruent:</l>
               <l>Cuncta tamen mundi ſurſum ibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t atque deorſum</l>
               <l>Imperia, &amp; luctus vndique grandis erit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>After one thouſand yeeres, full explere &amp; ended,</l>
               <l>And fiue hundred more vpon the ſame,</l>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:19782:50"/>
               <l>And eightie eight iuſt added</l>
               <l>From the Virgins birth without all ſtaine,</l>
               <l>A wonderfull yeere ſhall come vpon,</l>
               <l>And dolefull deaths ſhall follow on.</l>
               <l>If not this euill world this yeere</l>
               <l>With Land and Sea decay:</l>
               <l>Yet all the Empires euery where</l>
               <l>Aſſuredly ſhall ſway,</l>
               <l>And mourning much will follow.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Albeit (beloued Chriſtians) there was ſome ſhew of alteration that yeere, yet many that are here, liued then; and all can ſpeake by experience, that in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the laſt Iudgement, <hi>Regiomontanus</hi> was decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as vvell as others: and although there were ſome ſhew of troubles, yet GOD bee thanked, the feares were greater then the harmes, and we that liue, can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the ſame to Gods glory, who mercifully and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly protected vs, making the Seas and Windes to fight for vs, and to get the conqueſt, that all the praiſe might be the Lords.</p>
            <p>Some would haue the time to be certainely knowne, or very neerely pointed at, becauſe our Sauiour ſaith, <hi>Behold the Figge-tree and all the trees,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 21.</note> 
               <hi>when they ſhoot forth their buds, yee beholding, know of your owne ſelues, that Summer is then nie at hand: So likewiſe yee, when yee ſee theſe things come to paſſe, bee yee ſure that the Kingdome of GOD is nigh.</hi> This ſimilitude teacheth, that as when vvee ſee Trees begin to budde, then we know aſſuredly that Summer is nigh: So when wee ſee and know theſe things performed, that the Euangeliſts haue by the Spirit of GOD penned, and ſet downe, and our Sauiour foretold, and which <hi>Daniel</hi> prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied of, then wee may aſſure our ſelues, that the day and time is neere at hand: but we cannot out of theſe words gather the particular and certaine time. Againe,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19782:51"/> men ſhould conſider that our Sauiour ſpake by a ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, which illuſtrateth, but proueth not any ſet time knowne to man. In very truth, I confeſſe that the time of the laſt Iudgement may be knowne, <hi>quod ad ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> that is, that certainely it will come, but it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee knowne, <hi>quod ad ſpeciem,</hi> to wit, as touching the houre, day, moneth and certaine yeere. I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aſſure my ſelfe, and I beſeech you all bee ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that no man knoweth the certaine time, the very day nor houre of the Lords comming; no, nor the Angels in Heauen: nay, which is moſt of all, not our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt in his humanitie; but in his Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie knoweth all. And let this worke in vs all a ſerious kinde of watchfulneſſe.<note place="margin">Luk. 12.40.</note> 
               <hi>Bee yee ready</hi> (ſaith our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our) <hi>for the Sonne of Man will come at an houre when yee thinke not.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The end of the fourth Sermon.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="sermon">
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:19782:51"/>
            <head>THE FIFTH SERMON.</head>
            <p>God in his inſcrutable wiſedome, and infinite goodnes towards man, deferreth this day of iudgement for 3 reaſons.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>To ſtirre vp in vs a vigilant expectance, and a patient wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for his appearance.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>That his Church, his flocke, may be increaſed.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>To grant all men time &amp; ſpace to repent.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S touching the firſt,<note place="margin">Chap. 5.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>Iames</hi> teacheth vs to performe the ſame, by precept and pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne: by precept, in the beginning of the ſeuenth Verſe, where hee ſaith, <hi>Bee patient vnto the comming of the Lord;</hi> and hee in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect repeateth the ſame doctrine in the eighth Verſe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>Bee ye alſo patient therefore, and ſettle your hearts: for the comming of the Lord draweth neere.</hi> His example is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from Husbandmen, who patiently wait for the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous fruit of the earth, vntill they receiue the former and the latter raine. His words ſeruing for doctrine, and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, are theſe: <hi>Bee patient therefore vnto the comming of the Lord: Behold, the Husbandman waiteth for the precious fruit of the earth, and hath long patience for it, vntill he receiue the former and the latter raine. Be ye alſo patient therefore, and
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19782:52"/> ſettle your hearts: for the comming of the Lord draweth neere.</hi> He that waiteth in Faith,<note place="margin">Reu. 16.15.</note> hope, and patience for the Lords comming,<note place="margin">Luke 12.37.</note> is bleſſed: for hee ſhall appeare the ſecond time without ſinne vnto them that looke for him vnto ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as we may ſee, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. the laſt Verſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Lord deferreth his comming to Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that all the Elect may bee gathered together to his Church, may be effectually called, be of the Lords flocke, who although they are the Lords already in his eternall Decree, yet there is a time wherein they are called. The Lord would haue them heare the Word, and by the ſame to be born againe, vnto which time is required: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that they may haue time, the Lord delayeth his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming; for their ſakes the world conſiſteth, and for them all the good things on the earth are prepared. For the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly vſe them as Robbers and Theeues. The Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.3.</note> God hath prepared meates to bee receiued of the faithfull with thanksgiuing, and of ſuch as know the Truth. The like place the Apoſtle hath, ſpeaking to this purpoſe, thus: <hi>Vnto the pure all things are pure, but vnto them that are defiled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> 
               <hi>and vnbeleeuing, is nothing pure: but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the minde and conſcience of them is defiled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third reaſon why the Lord is ſo long before hee come to take this account, is very like to the former rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and it is to grant all men time and ſpace to repent, that they may bee ſaued, which the godly will not pretermit nor neglect. <hi>The Lord</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is not ſlacke, as ſome men count ſlackneſſe, but is patient to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs, for as much as he would haue no man loſt, but would receiue all men to repentance.</hi> Vnto which purpoſe hee ſpeaketh after in the 15. Verſe. <hi>Suppoſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the long ſuffering of the Lord is ſaluation.</hi> This time &amp; ſpace to repent, and prepare themſelues for this account, the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly will neuer let ſlip vnprofitably. Contrarily, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked neglect time, and therefore by the ſame are made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable, making a fuller meaſure of their ſinne, in that
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19782:52"/> they deſpiſe the goodnes and bountifulneſſe of the Lord,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note> calling them to repentance. Theſe wicked ones are afraid of this Iudgement, and therefore neuer wiſh for it: but the godly deſire it, becauſe at that time they ſhall be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from the miſeries wherein they liue in this world.<note place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> 
               <hi>O wretched man that I am</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>who ſhall deliuer me from the body of this death?</hi> In <hi>Reuelation</hi> 22. The Brideman, and Bridewoman ſay, <hi>Come, Lord Ieſu, Come:</hi> which they ſay not, that are not ready to entertaine the Lord.</p>
            <p>Hauing before proued, that there is a day of Iudgement, and that God would haue vs to know it, and the reaſons wherefore: and alſo hauing ſhewed that the certain time, the yeere, moneth, weekes, dayes, and houres are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, and the reaſons alſo of the ſame; with a confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the gaine-ſayers, and the vſe of both: And laſtly, hauing yeelded reaſons, why the Lord delayeth this Day: In the reſt, I will bee as compendious and ſhort as I may bee, ſo as I may lay downe the truth with perſpicuitie. Which that I may the better doe, obſerue with mee theſe points, which I thinke fitteſt to bee ſpoken of: And firſt, hauing before manifeſted that there is a day of Iudgement and account-taking; next, it wil be moſt profitable to ſhew,</p>
            <p>Firſt, what this Iudgement is.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the terrible ſignes, and dreadfull preparations for the wicked.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the manner and comming of the Iudge, and ſettling him in his Throne, and raiſing of the dead to come to Iudgement.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the tryall of the ſinner by Accuſers and Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, the Booke and touchſtone of the ſinners tryall at the laſt Day.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, the lamentable caſe of the ſinner condemned.</p>
            <p>Seuenthly, the ſentence giuen of both godly and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly. Firſt, what this Iudgement is.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:19782:53"/>
            <p>Firſt, it is that Iudgement which God will exerciſe in the end of the World by Chriſt, which ſhall come downe from Heauen into the Clouds viſibly, in great glory and Maieſtie, and will take this account: and by him all men ſhall bee raiſed vp, which haue beene dead from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world, euen to the end: the reſt then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aliue, ſhall be ſuddenly changed, and all ſhall ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Tribunall Seat of Chriſt, who ſhall giue ſentence of all, and will caſt the euill with the Diuels into eternall puniſhment; and will take the godly to him, that with him, and the bleſſed Angels, they may in Heauen en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy eternall felicitie. This long deſcription is taken out of the knowne Scriptures: and therefore if I ſhould labour to proue it, I ſhould hold vp a Candle to lighten the Sun. I will therefore leaue this matter as yeelded vnto, and haſten to the next point, to wit, what ſhall be done at that time, at that fearefull time of reckoning: that men war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the dangers, may be danted and diſcouraged from doing euill, and walking any longer ſecurely in the broad way that leadeth to deſtruction; and by ſerious repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance be brought to the narrow way that leadeth to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
            <p>Secondly, at this Day of Iudgement, when this ſtrict reckoning ſhall be taken, there ſhall be ſuch terrible ſignes, and dreadfull preparations for the wicked, that they ſhall bee at their wits ends; their hearts ſhall faile them for feare, and they ſhall wiſh that the Hils may couer them. For it ſhall be at midnight, when men commonly are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.16.</note> The Trumpet, the Word of the Lord, compared to a Trumpet, becauſe of the fearefull, ſhrill, and lowd ſound thereof, ſhall ſound out a moſt dreadfull <hi>taratan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tara. (Surgite mortui, &amp; venite ad Iudicium,)</hi> that is, Riſe ye dead, and come to Iudgement. At which voice, theſe dreadfull and terrible effects ſhall follow:<note place="margin">Mat. 24.29.</note> 
               <hi>The Sea and the Waters ſhall roare, the Hils ſhall moue out of their places, the Earth ſhake, the Sunne ſhall be darke, the Moone ſhall
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19782:53"/> not giue her light, the Starres ſhall fall from Heauen, the whole Element ſhiuer in pieces, the world ſhall bee in a conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fire, the Graues ſhall open, and yeeld forth the bodies lying in them, yea, and the Sea, and all other places alſo:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 20.13.</note> 
               <hi>they that then ſhall be aliue, ſhall with a ſudden mutation be renued, and all corruption wiped from their bodies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15. 1. Theſ. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and all mortalitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moued, they ſhall be made incorruptible, and immortall (which changing ſhall be inſtead of death vnto them) and all ſhal come to meete the Lord in the Aire,</hi> as thick as ſwarmes of Bees. <hi>The Angels ſhall ſeparate the good from the bad,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 13.41.</note> 
               <hi>the Tares from the Wheat, the Sheepe from the Goates, and euery one ſhal receiue according to that he hath done in this life,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.</note> 
               <hi>whether good or bad. The World,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Heauen and Earth ſhall bee diſſolued by fire:</hi> there ſhall bee a change of this preſent ſtate, and a purging of the Creatures, and not an vtter conſumption.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Iudge himſelfe, euen Chriſt Ieſus, the Sonne of God (to whom the Father hath giuen all iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) ſhall bee ſeene comming in the Clouds of Heauen,<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.22.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Math. 24.</note> in his very humane Nature; not in poore and baſe ſtate and ſort, as at his firſt comming in the fleſh, which was to good purpoſe, to giue vs an example of true humilitie, of true lowlineſſe; but in glory and great power, waited on, not with mortall and ſinfull men; but with the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and holy Angels. And then hee beeing moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, maieſticall, and powerfull,<note place="margin">Math. 25.31. The ſettling of him in his Throne.</note> and being alſo vpright and pure, will aſcend into his great white Throne, moſt beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming his Imperiall and immaculate perſon. And this <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw plainly in a viſion reuealed vnto him by Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>Re.</hi> 20.11.<note place="margin">Reu. 20.11.</note> where he thus reporteth: <hi>And I ſaw a great white Throne, &amp;c.</hi> The greatneſſe of this Throne ſheweth his might &amp; Maieſtie. For he is a King, hauing on his head a golden crown. The whitenes of it, his purity and holines.<note place="margin">Reu. 14.14. Heb. 7.26.</note> For he is a Prieſt and a Iudge, holy, innocent, vndefiled, ſeparate from ſinners, and made higher then the Heauens. When this Regall, mighty, and vncorrupt Iudge, hath ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led himſelfe in his Tribunall Seat; then at the ſhrill ſound
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19782:54"/> of the Trumpet,<note place="margin">The Reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the dead to come to Iudgement. Iob. 19.</note> all that are dead ſhall riſe, euen in the ſame ſtate and forme as they were when they dyed, couered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with the ſame skinne, and hauing the ſame fleſh, ſhall alſo behold God, not with other, but with the ſame eyes as they had when they departed out of this life: and all this ſhall come to paſſe, although a man is burnt to aſhes. For God who is Omnipotent, and made man of nothing, is much more able of aſhes to reedifie and make man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, then a ſimple man of aſhes can make a beautifull glaſſe. And if a Goldſmith, or a Pewterer, of a melted veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, can make another againe: then much more God, of a man returned to duſt, can make a man againe. He made man (I ſay) at the firſt of nothing: therefore much more is able to make him againe of ſomething, and to bring to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether all parts and pieces of him, whereſoeuer they bee ſcattered and diſperſed. An excellent example and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration whereof we haue in <hi>Ezechiel</hi> 37. where the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet foreſhewing the bringing againe of the people, being in captiuitie, telleth how the Lord ſet him downe in the middeſt of a field which was full of dry bones, and led him round about by them,<note place="margin">Ezec. 37.</note> and ſaid vnto him, <hi>Sonne of Man, can theſe bones liue? And the Prophet anſwered, O Lord God, thou knoweſt. Then the Lord proceeded further, and ſaid vnto the bones, Behold, I will cauſe breath to enter into you, and you ſhall liue, and I will lay ſinnewes vpon you, and make fleſh grow vpon you, and couer you with skinne, and put breath in you that ye may liue.</hi> And as ſoone as the Lord ſpake the word, all this was done: ſhewing plainely vnto vs our reſtauration to life at the Reſurrection in the laſt Day. All that are dead ſhall liue, ſhall riſe againe and come to be iudged: for the dead ſhall liue, they ſhall riſe againe with their body:<note place="margin">Eſay 26.19.</note> 
               <hi>Awake and ſing, ye that ſleepe in the duſt: for thy dew is as the dew of Hearbs, and the earth ſhall caſt out the dead.</hi> Let vs therefore reſolue our ſelues, that <hi>the houre ſhall come, in the which all that are in their graues, ſhall heare Chriſts voice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.28, 29.</note> 
               <hi>and they ſhall come forth that haue
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19782:54"/> done good, vnto the Reſurrection of life: but they that haue done euill, vnto the reſurrection of condemnation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 11.24.</note> 
               <hi>Martha</hi> therefore truely ſaid to Chriſt of <hi>Lazarus, I know that hee ſhall riſe againe at the laſt Day. Martha</hi> knew this to bee true, and ſo did <hi>Iob:</hi> and in this point let vs all be reſolued:<note place="margin">Iob 19. 2. King 4. Luke 7. Math. 9. Iohn 11.</note> for as truely as <hi>Elizeus</hi> called to life a dead Boy: Chriſt the Widdowes ſonne in <hi>Naim,</hi> and <hi>Iairus</hi> Daughter, and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus:</hi> ſo wee ſhall be raiſed againe to life, and ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this high Iudge, ſitting in his Imperiall Throne of Maieſtie. I pray God that wee may appeare before him cloathed with his holineſſe and righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Now although <hi>ſome ſhall be aliue at the laſt Day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſ. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>yet they ſhall not preuent them that ſleepe: for they ſhall bee caught vp with them alſo in the Clouds, to meet the Lord in the Aire, and ſhall come to Iudgement:</hi> that both <hi>the dead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>and they that then ſhall bee liuing, may receiue the things that are done in their bodies, according to that which they haue done, whether it be good or bad.</hi> For <hi>God by his Sonne Chriſt Ieſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 17.31.</note> 
               <hi>will Iudge the world in righteouſneſſe.</hi> It ſhall therefore goe well with the righteous, the godly, but ill with the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. It ſhall be with the godly and the wicked at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection in the laſt Day,<note place="margin">Gen. 40.</note> as it was with <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, his chiefe Butler, and his chiefe Baker. Both of them were taken out of Priſon; the one to be reſtored to his Office, to miniſter before the King, but the other to be put to torments and cruell death. In like maner ſhall it bee with the Elect, and Reprobate; faithfull, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull; the godly and the wicked at this generall and great Aſſize: both ſhall ariſe out of their cloſe priſon (I meane their Graues) but the one ſort to be euer with the Lord, and to be euer in a continuall ioyfull practice, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring praiſes, and Songs of Thankſgiuing: ſaying, <hi>Saluation, and glory, and honour bee to the Lord our God, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> The other to bee baniſhed from the preſence of the Lord, and to bee finally adiudged to euerlaſting fire and torments. Therefore (O godly man) hold on and goe
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19782:55"/> forward in a godly courſe of life. Thou ſhalt haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and ioy at the laſt, euen a ſolace ſempiterne and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall. For <hi>eye hath not ſeene, eare hath not heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>what good things the Lord hath prepared for them that loue him:</hi> and the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of Gods Children is incorruptible, vndefiled, and neuer fadeth away, But if thou art a wicked man, and haſt walked in the broad way that leadeth to deſtruction, and continueſt in thy wicked life without repentance, then thou ſhalt riſe in the laſt Day, but to iudgement, to torment, to bee caſt into the lake of fire and brimſtone, where are paines endleſſe,<note place="margin">Luke 16.</note> caſeleſſe, and remedileſſe. Looke to the example of the rich Glutton.</p>
            <p>At this day and time of account, Kings, Queenes, Princes, Earles, Barons and Baronets, Knights, Eſquires, Gentlemen, Yeomen, rich and poore, young and old, all, one as well as another, ſhall bee demanded, how they haue occupied their Talents, as wee may gather by the Parable.<note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> The Virgins that expect the Bridegroome with Oyle and Lampes prepared, ſhall be bleſſed. The wicked ſhall be ſifted with ſtraight examination, and ſhall giue an account of a thouſand matters, whereof they would haue ſcorned to haue been told of in this life, by Miniſter, or Magiſtrate: as how they haue ſpent their time? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they haue fought againſt the world, the Fleſh, and the Diuell? Of which, and many other things, they muſt giue an account of,<note place="margin">The ſinners Tryall.</note> yea, of euery idle word. And heere wee are to note, that as when perſons are tryed at our Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes, vpon matters of life and death, there are vſually ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſers and witneſſes, written and printed Lawes and Bookes, by which men are tryed: (for no man is condemned vpon a bare accuſation, without teſtimonie, ſome apparant proofe, or at leaſtwiſe ſome great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilitie that cannot bee ſpoken againſt, and the breach of the ſome branch of the Lawes:) So the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſpeaking after the manner of men, proue, that there
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19782:55"/> ſhal be both accuſers and witneſſes againſt a falſe Steward, a wicked man at this great Aſsize.</p>
            <p>The accuſers are a mans owne thoughts, after which ſort the thoughts of the Gentiles are ſaid to accuſe them, or excuſe them,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.15, 16.</note> at the day when God ſhall iudge the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of men by Ieſus Chriſt. A mans wicked thoughts then, are ſinnes; and, vnleſſe a man repent him of them, deſerue death. And therefore <hi>Peter</hi> bad <hi>Simon Magus</hi> pray to God, if perhaps the thoughts of his heart may bee forgiuen him. And for this cauſe our Sauiour ſpeaking of an euill heart, ſaith, <hi>that out of it proceede euill thoughts:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 15.19.</note> from theſe wicked thoughts, come many euill and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked words, whereof the ſinner muſt giue an account, yea,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.36.</note> many ſinnes and wickedneſſes that ſhall correct a man, and many turnings backe that ſhall reprooue him.<note place="margin">Ier. 2.19.</note> Our thoughts therefore may well bee ſaid to accuſe vs at this day of reckoning. And here it is ſtrange to ſee, how wonderfully worldly men are deceiued in this point: they will ſay, Thought is free; as though it were lawfull for them to thinke at pleaſure without ſinning, or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. It is true, that man may thinke what he will, freed from mans knowledge and puniſhment. For as it is true, that no man knoweth the thoughts of man; ſo it is as true, that no man can iuſtly inflict puniſhment vpon man for his thoughts: for he knoweth not them. Onely God, the ſearcher of the hearts and reynes, knoweth mans thoughts, and puniſheth them if they are wicked, and that deſeruedly. For euill thoughts defile man,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.19, 20.</note> and therefore worthily are condemned, <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.17.</p>
            <p>The witneſſes againſt man, are foure.
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Heauen and Earth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Ruſt of the Gold and Siluer of wicked rich men.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>A mans Conſcience.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:19782:56"/>
            <p>Firſt, God is a witneſſe, who knoweth all things, yea, the very ſecrets of the heart; therefore the trueſt and beſt witneſſe. This is proued, <hi>Malachy</hi> 3.5.<note place="margin">Mal. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>I will</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>come neere to you in iudgement, and I will be a ſwift wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe against the Southſayers, and againſt the Adulterers, and againſt falſe ſwearers, and againſt thoſe that wrongfully keepe backe the hirelings wages, and vex the widdow and the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and oppreſſe the ſtranger, and feare not mee, ſaith the Lord.</hi> This righteous Lord, and true witneſſe, will ſet before mans face, the things that hee hath done. Hee vvill bring to light the hidden things of darknes, &amp; make mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt the counſels of the heart, that euery one that thinketh well, and doth well, may haue praiſe of God: and he that thinketh not well,<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> nor doth well, may bee caſt into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting fire, prepared for the Diuell and his Angels.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 4.26.</note>The ſecond witneſſe, <hi>Heauen and earth.</hi> The Lord ſaith to Iſrael: when thou ſhalt beget children, and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens children, and ſhalt haue remained long in the land, if yee corrupt your ſelues, and make any grauen image, or likeneſſe of any thing, and worke euill in the ſight of the Lord thy God, to prouoke him to anger, I call Heauen and Earth to record againſt you this day, that yee ſhall ſhortly periſh from the land whereunto ye goe ouer Iordan to poſſeſſe it: yee ſhall not prolong your dayes therein, but ſhall vtterly bee deſtroyed. The like place we haue, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.19.<note place="margin">Deut. 30.19.</note> Where the Lord calleth Heauen and Earth to witneſſe againſt them, ſaying, that he had ſet before them life, and death, a bleſsing, and a curſe, and bids them chuſe life, that they may liue with their ſeed. Beloued Chriſtians, let vs take heed what we doe heere on the earth. For our ſayings &amp; doings are knowne and ſeene from aboue: and the earth, vpon which our ſinnes are committed, can beare witneſſe of the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, if our words and deeds are euill.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the ruſt of the gold and ſiluer of couetous worldlings, ſhall be a witneſſe againſt them, which hath
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19782:56"/> beene layd vp till it ruſted, for want of vſing and well em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying to the vſe of the poore. And as their gold and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is eaten vp and fretted with ruſt: ſo they, for not vſing their treaſure well, ſhall be eaten vp and deuoured with the fire of hell, that is, they ſhall be tormented with euerlaſting flames of fire. This doth <hi>Iames</hi> teach vs, ſaying,<note place="margin">Iam. 5.1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>Goe to now, ye rich men: weepe and howle for your miſeries that ſhall come vpon you: your riches are corrupt; and your garments are moth-eaten: your gold and ſiluer is cankred, and the ruſt of them ſhall be a witneſſe againſt you, and ſhall eate your fleſh as it were fire. Ye haue heaped vp treaſures for the laſt dayes.</hi> How fooliſh then are greedie couetous men,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> which heape vp wrath againſt the day of wrath, and of the declaration of the iuſt iudgement of God?<note place="margin">Mat. 5.</note> How much better were it for them to lay vp treaſures, not vpon earth, where the ruſt and moth doth corrupt, and where theeues breake thorow and ſteale; but rather to lay vp treaſures in heauen; where neither ruſt nor moth doth corrupt, and where theeues doe not breake thorow nor ſteale?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, a mans conſcience ſhall witneſſe with him or againſt him, as the Apoſtle doth teſtifie,<note place="margin">Rom. 2.</note> ſpeaking thus of the Gentiles: When the Gentiles (ſaith he) which haue not the Law, doe of nature the things conteined in the Law, they hauing not the Law are a law vnto themſelues, which ſhew the effect of the Law, written in their hearts; their conſcience alſo bearing witneſſe, and their thoughts accuſing one another or excuſing, at the day when God ſhall iudge the ſecrets of men by Ieſus Chriſt according to my Goſpel. Note (I beſeech you) the Apoſtles words: He ſaith, That the conſcience of the Gentiles ſhall beare witneſſe: and he telleth when ſhe ſhall doe this; to wit, when God ſhall iudge the ſecrets of men by Ieſus Chriſt, meaning, the day of Iudgement. But that I may ſpeake more plainely, note, I beſeech you (beloued Chriſtians) that as mens doings are two-fold: good, or bad: They are good which proceed from faith, and are agreeable to
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19782:57"/> the Law of God: and they are euill, which proceed from infidelitie, and are repugnant to the Lawes of God: So the motions of mens hearts are two-fold; either ioyfull, which concomitate good deedes; or ſorrowfull, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes accompany euill deedes. Hereupon it commeth to paſſe, that one Conſcience may bee called good, another bad.<note place="margin">Omnis Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia cum ſcientia.</note> Now a good conſcience, is a ioyfull motion of the heart, ariſing from a certaine knowledge of wel-doing: or it is the iudgement of the mind, grounded vpon know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge concerning a mans good deeds, miniſtring ioy vnto him. Hereupon <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Our reioycing is this, the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of a good conſcience.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> bended his wit, and will, and laboured earneſtly to haue a good conſcience towards God and man; and he had ſuch an one, and with it could truly ſay, <hi>I am pure from the blood of all men.</hi> And further, at his end, his conſcience ſo comforted, ſtrengthened, and emboldened him, that he without any ſcruple or heſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.7.8.</note> ſaid, <hi>I haue fought a good fight, I haue finiſhed my courſe, I haue kept the faith, &amp;c.</hi> A good conſcience makes a merrie heart, whiles wee liue, makes vs to ſleepe more quietly, then if we layd our heades on a Doune-pillow: and when death approcheth, ſhe cauſeth man not to feare to die; and then will not forſake him, when all worldly vanities and ſhadowes vaniſh &amp; fade away: and yet ſhe wil doe him the beſt ſeruice that ſhe can; ſhee will plead for him, and witneſſe with him. O what a treaſure is a good conſcience! She is as it were mount Tabor, a glimpſe of glory vpon earth, a comfortreſſe of thy heart at the houre of death, and a faithfull friend and witneſſe, to ſtand by thee at the day of Iudgement, when thou ſhalt haue moſt need. But an euill conſcience is in this world, as it were, an helliſh Hagge, an infernall Furie, euer tormenteth man, followeth him; ſhe alwayes keepeth a true record of all mans euill thoughts, words, and workes, troubleth man with direfull ſuggeſtions and temptations; ſhe is neuer at peace and quietneſſe; ſhe bringeth man to deſtruction, as
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19782:57"/> it may appeare by the examples of <hi>Cain, Iudas, Arrius,</hi> and many others: and yet ſhe hath not done, but conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing an enemy, at the laſt Day will witneſſe againſt a man all his ſinnes: his ſwearing, forſwearing, lying, ſtea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, iniuries, oppreſſions, and all other his workes of the fleſh and darkneſſe. She will not, nor cannot forget them. For all mens faults are ſo perfectly knowne vnto her, and ſo firmely impreſſed in her, that ſhee is compared to a booke; a booke of remembrance, wherein all things are ſo perfectly recorded, that they cannot be forgotten.<note place="margin">Reu. 20 12.</note> 
               <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thou haſt ſealed vp our ſinnes in a bagge:</hi> to ſhew the exact and ſtrict kind of keeping of them againſt that Day of account: So that not an euill thought, not an euil word, not an euill deed, can be forgotten, they are all ſo ſurely recorded; and the time of opening this booke, and reading them ouer to the hearing of the world, is the day of Iudgement. For then all mens faults ſhall be knowne, and in them that haue offended, they ſhall be puniſhed. Foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh men and women think, that all their wicked thoughts, all their idle and euill words paſſe away with the wind: but it is not ſo: for in this booke they are written and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded; and once the booke ſhall be opened, and thy ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret ſinnes diſcouered. Now if we come to the liues of men and women, alaſſe, they are moſt wicked; they are nothing elſe but a continuall practice of ſinne. Well, let vs labour to keepe a good conſcience, an vnblotted, and vnblurred booke, and then we ſhall preuent and eſcape the danger.</p>
            <p>The booke and touchſtone of the triall,<note place="margin">The Booke and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone.</note> whereby all our thoughts, words, and workes ſhall be examined and tried, is the Word of God: it is (I ſay) the Rule and Line, by which they ought to be leuelled, ſquared, and wrought by. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> That at the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, God ſhall iudge the ſecrets of men by Ieſus Chriſt, according to his Goſpel: he meaneth that Goſpel whereof he was a preacher, not an authour. Our thoughts, words,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19782:58"/> and workes muſt be tryed by the Word of God. If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our thoughts, words, and workes are not agreeable to the Word of God, to Gods rules and commandements, they are as odious, diſtaſtefull, and vnpleaſing vnto the Lord, as the offering vp of bruſed things were in the time of the Law. Therefore let the Word of God (O man) be a lanterne to thy feet, and a light vnto thy pathes, that thou mayeſt not wander out of the old ancient wayes of the Lord, but goe the ſtraight wayes to Heauen, alwayes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting thy ſteps by this Word of God.</p>
            <p>When the poore wretched ſinner, accuſed by his own thoughts, is found culpable in his words and workes, and is conuicted by euident and plaine teſtimonies (as before) becauſe he made no conſcience of his wayes, and neuer directed his goings according to the Word of God: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold in what lamentable caſe he ſhall ſtand in:<note place="margin">The lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble caſe of the ſinner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</note> For aboue him he ſhall haue the Iudge offended for his wickedneſſe: beneath him, the burning pit of Hell open, and boyling, ready to ſwallow him vp: on his right hand, his ſinnes accuſing: on his left hand, the Diuels, as it were Iaylors, and Executioners, ready to execute Gods Sentence vpon him: within him, his conſcience ſhall gnaw him, paine him, grieue him, and teſtifie againſt him: before him, iudgement without mercy; behinde him, his euill life: on euery ſide, all damned ſoules bewailing, and which way ſoeuer you caſt your eyes, you ſhall behold a burning fire. <hi>O conſider this, ye that forget God, leſt hee teare you in pieces, and there be none to deliuer you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sentence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of godly, and vngodly; and firſt, of the godly.</note>The iuſt Iudge will pronounce ſentence righteouſly, both of the Sheepe on his right hand, and Goates on his left hand, of both godly, and vngodly; iuſt, and vniuſt; faithfull, and vnfaithfull. Sentence ſhall bee giuen of the godly, according to the Goſpel, not onely offering, but now giuing ſaluation to Gods faithfull children, by the merits of Ieſus Chriſt. And the ſentence will bee a kinde inuitation, or rather receiuing to ioy, in theſe words. <hi>Come
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:19782:58"/> ye bleſſed of my Father, inherite the Kingdome prepared for you from the beginning of the world, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the contrary, ſentence ſhall be giuen of the Goates, of the wicked and vngodly on the Iudges left hand, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rigour of the Law, with all it maledictions, tortures, and torments, then preſently to be put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt a lewd liuer: theſe ſhall then indure their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued endleſſe puniſhments. The Sentence againſt theſe is, <hi>Depart ye curſed, into euerlaſting fire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sentence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen againſt the wicked.</note> 
               <hi>prepared for the Diuell and his Angels, &amp;c.</hi> All this is ratified with a clauſe of an irreuocable ſentence, to wit, <hi>Theſe ſhall goe into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting paine, &amp;c.</hi> Of theſe paines of Hell, as alſo of the ioyes of Heauen, I had thought to haue written: that by the conſideration of the one, the wicked may bee deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from ſinning, and ſo auoid the puniſhment; and by the conſideration of the other, they may be allured to well doing, to ſeeke thoſe things that are aboue, and tread the ſtraight way that leadeth to euerlaſting life. But hauing ſpent ſo much time already, as I could well ſpare, I will end for this preſent, promiſing (if my labours are accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and God granteth time of life to performe it) that I will write of the ſame at ſome other conuenient time. I will therefore now end, praying all Chriſtians to liſten to the exhortation following: Beloued, let vs prepare our ſelues for this iudgement dayly and euery moment. Let the commandement of the Lord ſtirre vs vp to watch, prouide, and be in a readineſſe.<note place="margin">Luk. 12.35.</note> 
               <hi>Let your loynes bee girded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and your lights burning, and yee your ſelues like vnto men that wait for their Maſter when he will returne from the wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that when he commeth and knocketh, they may open vnto him immediately. Bleſſed are thoſe ſeruants, whom the Lord when he commeth, ſhall finde waking, &amp;c.</hi> Let the example of the ſudden floud propoſed by <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.</note> ſtrike a care into vs, and make vs afraid to be ſecure. Let the conſideration of the High Iudge, which iudgeth with iuſtice and equitie all men of euery order, age and kinde, make vs prepare
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19782:59"/> our ſelues againſt this day. Let the ſignes now accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and fulfilled, make vs fully reſolued that the Day is at hand, and ſtrike a care into vs to bee prepared againſt the Lords comming. Let the vncertaine houre to vs when it ſhall come, and yet certain that once it will come, and ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then we thinke, make vs obſeruant and watchfull. To conclude, let the execution it ſelfe, to wit, euerlaſting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and euerlaſting puniſhments, wanting all eaſe and mitigation of torments, ſtrike a feare in vs not to offend, and make vs carefull to pleaſe God. <hi>For God,</hi> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle hath,<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.</note> 
               <hi>will render vengeance in flaming fire, to them which know him not, and that obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt: Which ſhall bee puniſhed with euerlaſting damnation from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power, when he ſhall come to be glorified in his Saints, and to be made maruellous in all them that beleeue.</hi> Let vs prepare our ſelues againſt that Day;<note place="margin">Aug. ad Demet. Epiſt. <hi>142.</hi>
               </note> wherein <hi>Mundi gloria finienda eſt,</hi> that is, the glory of the world muſt take his end: I ſay, againſt that day and time, which ſhall take tardy in deceitfull ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie many, and therefore compared to the comming in of the Floud,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3. 1. Theſ. 5.</note> in the dayes of <hi>Noah;</hi> and to the comming of a Thiefe. If a band of men ſhould enter into a Citie, and begin to deſtroy with fire and ſword, would not euery man tremble and quake? If we thus feare our mortall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and the hand of man, what ſhall wee doe, when as the fearefull Trumpet ſhall ſound from Heauen, and at that voice of the Archangell more cleere and ſhrill then any Trumpet; all the whole world ſhall rumble? when we ſhall ſee not weapons made with hands, but the whole powers of Heauen to be mooued, and to threaten venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance vnto vs. If a man-ſlayer, or any other wicked perſon, of whom puniſhment were to be taken by the iudgement of an earthly Iudge, will tremble, and quake, at the ſight of the Iudge, and others ſtanding about in iudgement, and at the bloudy hand of the Hangman, or Tormenter, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he know that his end will bee but ſhort: then
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19782:59"/> (beloued) conſider what ſhame, feare, dolour, and griefe will bee at the Day of Iudgement, when all the euils and ſorrowes, that can bee imagined and deuiſed, ſhall bee broached, and ready to be inflicted vpon the wicked men of this world. Theſe, and many other euils ſhall befall them which are holden with many cares of this world, and thinke not of this laſt end of all things. But we which repent, beleeue, and thinke of Chriſts comming, conceiue ioy, and wiſh for his comming, as the certaine time of our Redemption, and reward, ſaying, <hi>Come, Lord Ieſu, Come.</hi> To this Lord Ieſus, together with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, three Perſons, in one Eſſence, be rende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all honour, and glory, power, and ſeruice, in Heauen, and in Earth, henceforth and for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
